<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/teaching.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-18T07:46:08-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/teaching.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy | Teaching</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Curating Art and Science</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2022/curating/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Curating Art and Science" /><published>2022-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2022/curating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2022/curating/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Curating Art and Science, a course offered in museum studies, history, and cultural studies in fall 2022 at Claremont Graduate University. This course will explore the history of interactions between art, science, and technology, and how to curate exhibitions on the subject. It is partly based on the instructors’ work, as part of the Getty Foundation’s Pacific Standard Time 2024 program on art, science, and LA, to develop a multi-sited, campus-wide exhibition at Caltech on Caltech’s own uses of visual culture over the last century to produce science, to communicate it, and to foster scientific identity and community. Our readings will emphasize the 20th century US, and sometimes specifically Caltech’s own history, but student projects may extend beyond this geographical and chronological context.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will be divided into three modules:</p>

<ol>
	<li><b>Art and Science:</b> During the first part of the semester, we will think about the relationships between art, science, technology, and visual culture more generally, studying foundational texts on scientific illustration, the influence of science on modern and contemporary art, technological art, and the architecture of scientific institutions.</li>
	<li><b>Curating:</b> The second part of the semester takes an in-depth look at the history of exhibitions, both in the science and visual arts realms, and explores the nature and roles of archives and collections as sources for display. We will pay particular attention to contemporary curatorial theory and practice as it has evolved from the 1960s to the present. There will be site visits to the Benton Museum at Pomona College, where we will see an installation by California Light and Space artist Helen Pashgian; the Huntington Library, where we view a site-specific installation by artist Lita Albuquerque and meet with senior curators working on art and science exhibitions; and the Caltech Archives and Special Collections, where we will explore the records kept by scientific institutions. Other guests will join the conversation to deepen our understanding of discourse and standards in the field.</li>
	<li><b>Disciplinary Histories and Student Presentations:</b> During the third part of the semester, we will focus on the histories of visual culture in specific scientific disciplines, as well as art and architecture, often reading case studies from Caltech’s own history. Students will curate, design, and present possible exhibition displays on these topics drawing on the Caltech Archives and other local collections.</li>
</ol>

<p>Throughout the semester, students will investigate a range of visual practices at Caltech and other scientific institutions according to the specific scientific, artistic, and institutional functions they serve. What kinds of information do scientific images convey, and how do we best look at them in their varying contexts? How do we account for the choices scientists and artists make when they represent their work, and what cultural biases or preferences might their images contain? How do scientific images relate to other images in art, technology, and popular culture?</p>

<p>This course does not require any specific background preparation. For those unfamiliar with the academic study of visual culture, additional reading in James Elkins and Erna Fiorentini, <cite>Visual Worlds: Looking, Images, Visual Disciplines</cite> (Oxford University Press, 2020) may be useful for context.</p>

<h3>Student Learning Outcomes</h3>

<p>Upon successful completion of this course, students will be able to:</p>

<ol>
	<li>Understand the complex interactions between art, science, technology, and visual culture in the 20th and early 21st centuries, especially as they relate to the California Institute of Technology, other American science institutions, and Southern California.</li>
	<li>Navigate art and science discourses in the humanities.</li>
	<li>Reflect on and engage critically with trends and issues in contemporary curatorial practice.</li>
	<li>Collaborate with project partners.</li>
	<li>Strengthen research, writing, and presentation skills, communicating in a variety of formats and for diverse audiences.</li>
	<li>Create compelling exhibitions with an understanding of different spaces and their design, as well as the selection, care, and management of display objects.</li>
	<li>Know artists, scholars, curators, and design professionals working in the field.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Assignments</h3>

<ol>
	<li><b>Exhibition review</b> (500 words) of a local exhibition of your choice which engages with both art and science. Specific guidelines for this review will be posted online and discussed in class. Reviews are due electronically before class on October 24, 2022.</li>
	<li><b>Exhibition proposal</b> of a concept, items, didactic text, and layout for a small display on an art/science theme either chosen from a list provided by the course instructors or proposed by the student. Elements of the proposal will include a short introductory text (500 words), a checklist of 15–30 display items, a sample wall text (250 words) and didactic exhibition label (100 words), and space selection and layout/fabrication ideas. You may work independently or collaborate with one or more partners. In addition to handing in proposal materials, each student will present on their proposal during the third portion of the semester. Your presentation will be assessed based on the comprehensiveness and originality of your ideas; their viability in a real-life gallery, museum, or library setting; and your creative communication skills. Specific guidelines for a successful exhibition proposal will be posted online and discussed in class. Proposals are due on your assigned presentation day, between November 7 and December 12.</li>
	<li><b>Curatorial essay</b> (15–20 pages, no more than 5000 words) providing historical, cultural, aesthetic, or other scholarly analysis of your proposal exhibition, or, with permission of the instructors, of another topic. Specific guidelines for the creation of a curatorial essay will be posted online and discussed in class. Curatorial essays are due electronically on December 16.</li>
</ol>

<p>Your grade for the course will be based 20% on the exhibition review, 30% each on the exhibition proposal and curatorial essay, and 20% on your engaged and insightful participation in class.</p>

<p>We’ll discuss readings during every class, so please read everything assigned before the class meeting it’s listed under. Please submit assignments by email to both instructors.</p>

<h3>Schedule of Class Topics and Readings</h3>

<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>August 29: Introduction</h5>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4>Art and Science</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>September 12: Scientific Images</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>James Elkins, <cite><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctv3s8n8p">The Domain of Images</a></cite> (Cornell University Press, 1999), 3–51.</li>
			<li>Horst Bredekamp, Vera Dünkel, and Birgit Schneider, eds., <cite>The Technical Image: A History of Styles in Scientific Imagery</cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2015), 1–45.</li>
			<li>Bruno Latour, “<a href="http://www.bruno-latour.fr/sites/default/files/21-DRAWING-THINGS-TOGETHER-GB.pdf">Visualization and Cognition: Drawing Things Together</a>,” <cite>Knowledge and Society</cite> 6 (1986): 1–40.</li>
			<li>Lorraine Daston and Peter Galison, <cite><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctv1c9hq4d">Objectivity</a></cite> (Zone, 2007), 9–53.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>September 19: Science in Art</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>James Elkins and Erna Fiorentini, <cite>Visual Worlds: Looking, Images, Visual Disciplines</cite> (Oxford University Press, 2020), 339–362.</li>
			<li>Chiara Ambrosio, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03080188.2016.1223586">Cubism and the Fourth Dimension</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 41 (2016): 202–221.</li>
			<li>Linda Dalrymple Henderson, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/776982">X Rays and the Quest for Invisible Reality in the Art of Kupka, Duchamp, and the Cubists</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 47 (1988): 323–340.</li>
			<li>Vanja V. Malloy, “From Macrocosm to Microcosm: Examining the Role of Modern Science in American Art,” in <cite>Dimensionism: Modern Art in the Age of Einstein</cite>, ed. Vanja V. Malloy (Mead Art Museum, Amherst College and MIT Press, 2018), 71–97.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>September 26: The Architecture of Science</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Sophie Forgan, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0039-3681(89)90017-4">The Architecture of Science and the Idea of a University</a>,” <cite>Studies in History and Philosophy of Science</cite> 20 (1989): 405–434.</li>
			<li>Robert E. Kohler, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/007327530204000405">Labscapes: Naturalizing the Lab</a>,” <cite>History of Science</cite> 40 (2002): 473–501.</li>
			<li>Thomas F. Gieryn, “Two Faces on Science: Building Identities for Molecular Biology and Biotechnology,” in <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb08330.0001.001">The Architecture of Science</a></cite>, ed. Peter Galison and Emily Thompson (MIT Press, 1999), 423–455.</li>
			<li>Thomas F. Gieryn, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/595773">Laboratory Design for Post-Fordist Science</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 99 (2008): 796–802.</li>
			<li>Peter Galison and Caroline A. Jones, “Factory, Laboratory, Studio: Dispersing Sites of Production,” in Galison and Thompson, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb08330.0001.001">Architecture of Science</a></cite>, 497–540.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 3: Art and Technology</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Fred Turner, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1470412907087201">Romantic Automatism: Art, Technology, and Collaborative Labor in Cold War America</a>,” <cite>Journal of Visual Culture</cite> 7 (2008): 5–26.</li>
			<li>Anne Collins Goodyear, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20206559">From Technophilia to Technophobia: The Impact of the Vietnam War on the Reception of ‘Art and Technology,’</a>” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 41, no. 2 (2008): 169–173.</li>
			<li>Matthew Wisnioski, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/con.2013.0006">Why MIT Institutionalized the Avant-Garde: Negotiating Aesthetic Virtue in the Postwar Defense Institute</a>,” <cite>Configurations</cite> 21 (2013): 85–116.</li>
			<li>W. Patrick McCray, “Fallout and Spinoff: Commercializing the Art-Technology Nexus,” in <cite>Hybrid Practices: Art in Collaboration with Science and Technology in the Long 1960s</cite>, ed. David Cateforis, Steven Duval, and Shepherd Steiner (University of California Press, 2019), 61–77.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4>Curating</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>October 10: Showing Is Telling: Contemporary Curatorial Practice</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: <a href="https://www.timdurfee.com/">Tim Durfee</a>, Principal of Tim Durfee Studio and Professor of Media Design Practices, Art Center College of Design</i></li>
			<li>Robert Storr, “Show and Tell,” in <cite>What Makes a Great Exhibition?</cite> ed. Paula Marincola (Reaktion, 2006), 14–31.</li>
			<li>Kate Fowle, “Who Cares? Understanding the Role of the Curator Today,” in <cite>Cautionary Tales: Critical Curating</cite>, ed. Steven Rand and Heather Kouris (apexart, 2007).</li>
			<li>Hans Ulrich Obrist, <cite>Ways of Curating</cite> (Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2014), 14–16, 22–35.</li>
			<li>Jens Hofmann and Maria Lind, “<a href="https://www.moussemagazine.it/magazine/jens-hoffmann-maria-lind-2011/">To Show or Not to Show</a>,” <cite>Mousse Magazine</cite>, no. 31 (November 2011).</li>
			<li>Adrian George, <cite>The Curator’s Handbook: Museums, Commercial Galleries, Independent Spaces</cite> (Thames and Hudson, 2015), 152–206.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 17: Archives and Collections</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: <a href="http://www.elinoharaslavick.com/">elin o’Hara slavick</a>, artist and curator</i></li>
			<li>Elizabeth Yale, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43956377">The History of Archives: The State of the Discipline</a>,” <cite>Book History</cite> 18 (2015): 332–359.</li>
			<li>Lorraine Daston, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/667826">The Sciences of the Archive</a>,” <cite>Osiris</cite> 27 (2012): 156–187.</li>
			<li>Allan Sekula, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/778312">The Body and the Archive</a>,” <cite>October</cite>, no. 39 (Winter 1986): 3–64.</li>
			<li>Jennifer Tucker, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/501104">The Historian, the Picture, and the Archive</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 97 (2006): 111–120.</li>
			<li>George, <cite>Curator’s Handbook, 30–48 and 56–87.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 24: Exhibiting Art, Exhibiting Science</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: Dan Lewis, Dibner Senior Curator of the History of Science and Technology, Huntington Library</i></li>
			<li>Sharon Macdonald, “Exhibitions of Power and Powers of Exhibitions: An Introduction to the Politics of Display,” in <cite>The Politics of Display: Museums, Science, and Culture</cite>, ed. Sharon Macdonald (Routledge, 1998), 1–24.</li>
			<li>Ivan Karp and Steven D. Lavine, eds., <cite>Exhibiting Cultures: The Poetics and Politics of Museum Display</cite> (Smithsonian Institution Press, 1991), 1–56.</li>
			<li>Tony Bennet, “The Exhibitionary Complex,” in <cite>Thinking About Exhibitions</cite>, ed. Reesa Greenberg, Bruce W. Fergusson, and Sandy Nairne (Routledge, 1996), 81–112.</li>
			<li>Terry Smith, <cite>Thinking Contemporary Curating</cite> (Independent Curators International, 2012), 57–100.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 31: From White Cube to Black Box: Contemporary Curatorial Thought</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: Rebecca McGrew, Senior Curator, Benton Museum of Art, Pomona College</i></li>
			<li>Brian O’Doherty, “<a href="https://www.artforum.com/print/197603/inside-the-white-cube-notes-on-the-gallery-space-part-i-38508">Inside the White Cube: Notes on the Gallery Space, Part I</a>,” <cite>Artforum</cite>, March 1976.</li>
			<li>Okwui Enwezor, “The Black Box,” in <cite>Documenta 11_Platform 5: Exhibition, Catalogue</cite> (Hatje Cantz, 2002).</li>
			<li>Carolee Thea, “Okwui Enwezor,” in <cite>On Curating: Interviews with Ten International Curators</cite> (Distributed Art Publishers, 2009), 43–53.</li>
			<li>Paul O’Neill, <cite>The Culture of Curating and the Curating of Culture(s)</cite> (MIT Press, 2016), 9–49.</li>
			<li>Smith, <cite>Thinking Contemporary Curating</cite>, 178–246.</li>
			<li>Irit Rogoff, “<a href="https://xenopraxis.net/readings/rogoff_smuggling.pdf">‘Smuggling’: An Embodied Criticality</a>,” August 2006.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4>Disciplinary Histories and Student Presentations</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>November 7: Astronomy and Planetary Science</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Alex Soojung-Kim Pang, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4027716">‘Stars Should Henceforth Register Themselves’: Astrophotography at the Early Lick Observatory</a>,” <cite>British Journal for the History of Science</cite> 30 (1997): 177–205.</li>
			<li>Omar W. Nasim, “<a href="https://www.mprl-series.mpg.de/studies/12/10/index.html">Handling the Heavens: Things and the Photo-Objects of Astronomy</a>,” in <cite>Photo-Objects: On the Materiality of Photographs and Photo Archives in the Humanities and Sciences</cite>, ed. Julia Bärnighausen, Costanza Caraffa, Stefanie Klamm, Franka Schneider, and Petra Wodtke (Max-Planck-Gesellschaft zur Förderung der Wissenschaften, 2019), 161–175.</li>
			<li>Elizabeth A. Kessler, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2021.0198">Technology’s Palette: Voyager’s Eyes and the Hyperchromatic Enhancement of Jupiter and Saturn</a>,” <cite>Technology and Culture</cite> 62 (2021): 1087–1118.</li>
			<li>Janet Vertesi, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/9780262525381.003.0002"><i>Drawing As</i>: Distinctions and Disambiguation in Digital Images of Mars</a>,” in <cite>Representation in Scientific Practice Revisited</cite>, ed. Catelijne Coopmans, Janet Vertesi, Michael Lynch, and Steve Woolgar (MIT Press, 2014), 15–36.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>November 14: Biology</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Nick Hopwood, “<a href="https://publicdomainreview.org/essay/copying-pictures-evidencing-evolution">Copying Pictures, Evidencing Evolution</a>,” <cite>Public Domain Review</cite>, May 18, 2016.</li>
			<li>Maura C. Flannery, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1576571">Images of the Cell in Twentieth-Century Art and Science</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 31 (1998): 195–204.</li>
			<li>Christopher Kelty and Hannah Landecker, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/1526381042464536">A Theory of Animation: Cells, L-Systems, and Film</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite>, no. 17 (2004): 31–63.</li>
			<li>Soraya de Chadarevian, “Models and the Making of Molecular Biology,” in <cite>Models: The Third Dimension of Science</cite>, ed. Soraya de Chadarevian and Nick Hopwood (Stanford University Press, 2004), 339–368.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>November 21: Chemistry</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Christoph Meinel, “Molecules and Croquet Balls,” in de Chadarevian and Hopwood, <cite>Models</cite>, 242–275.</li>
			<li>Alberto Cambrosio, Daniel Jacobi, and Peter Keating, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/rep.2005.89.1.94">Arguing with Images: Pauling’s Theory of Antibody Formation</a>,” <cite>Representations</cite> 89, (2005): 94–130.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>November 28: Art and Architecture</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Stefanos Polyzoides, “<a href="https://www.classicist.org/pdf/classicist15/#page=10">Bertram Goodhue and the Architecture of Caltech, 1915 to 1939</a>,” <cite>Classicist</cite>, no. 15 (2018): 8–19.</li>
			<li>Zabet Patterson, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/grey.2009.1.36.36">From the Gun Controller to the Mandala: The Cybernetic Cinema of John and James Whitney</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite>, no. 36 (2009): 36–57.</li>
			<li>Stephen Nowlin, “<a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/670950">@Caltech: Art, Science and Technology, 1969–1971</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 50 (2017): 443–447.</li>
			<li>Lisa Lynch, “‘Out-liers,’ ‘Insiders,’ and Practical Harvest: Art as Technology Transfer in a Research Environment,” <cite>Research in Science and Technology Studies</cite> 13 (2002): 239–265.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>December 5: Physics</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Peter Galison and Alexi Assmus, “Artificial Clouds, Real Particles,” in <cite>The Uses of Experiment: Studies in the Natural Sciences</cite>, ed. David Gooding, Trevor Pinch, and Simon Schaffer (Cambridge University Press, 1989), 225–274.</li>
			<li>David Kaiser, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2902893">Stick Figure Realism: Conventions, Reification, and the Persistence of Feynman Diagrams, 1948–1964</a>,” <cite>Representations</cite> 70 (2000): 49–86.</li>
			<li>James Elkins, <cite>Six Stories from the End of Representation: Images in Painting, Photography, Astronomy, Microscopy, Particle Physics, and Quantum Mechanics, 1980–2000</cite> (Stanford University Press, 2008), 156–223.</li>
			<li>Colleen O’Reilly, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/44011808">Pedagogical Interventions: The Physics Photographs of Berenice Abbott</a>,” <cite>RACAR: revue d'art canadienne / Canadian Art Review</cite> 41, no. 2 (2016): 77–90.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>December 12: Conclusion</h5>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="biology" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="physics" /><category term="astronomy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Curating Art and Science, a course offered in museum studies, history, and cultural studies in fall 2022 at Claremont Graduate University. This course will explore the history of interactions between art, science, and technology, and how to curate exhibitions on the subject. It is partly based on the instructors’ work, as part of the Getty Foundation’s Pacific Standard Time 2024 program on art, science, and LA, to develop a multi-sited, campus-wide exhibition at Caltech on Caltech’s own uses of visual culture over the last century to produce science, to communicate it, and to foster scientific identity and community. Our readings will emphasize the 20th century US, and sometimes specifically Caltech’s own history, but student projects may extend beyond this geographical and chronological context.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Evolution Debates</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution Debates" /><published>2017-01-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution/"><![CDATA[<p>As the evolution of life generally and humanity in particular became scientific orthodoxy in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, scientists and other intellectuals debated what this meant. Some conceptions of God were compatible with evolution and others were not, for example, but the inverse was also true: certain conceptions of evolution were compatible with God and others were not. And at the same time, some conceptions of evolution emphasized cooperation and suggested humans would achieve the happiest lives through socialism, while others emphasized the roles of competition and “survival of the fittest” and suggested that capitalism was a better system for human achievement. Some theories of human evolution justified white supremacy, while others suggested racial equality. As a result, debates about biology were often also debates about religion and politics, and the three fields were repeatedly re-formed together.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>This is a syllabus for The Evolution Debates, a course offered for four units of credit in spring 2017 as HIST 255g at the University of Southern California. This course will explore the history of ideas about evolution and human origins from about 1800 to the present. We’ll focus on debates and controversies, both within biology and geology and at intersections of science, religion, and politics, as well as famous incidents like Charles Darwin’s voyage on the Beagle and the Scopes Monkey Trial. More broadly, we’ll study the development of evolutionary theory, the histories of creationism and theistic evolutionism, and the roles of debates about human evolution’s political consequences in the histories of eugenics and scientific racism.</p>

<p>This is a General Education course in the category of Humanistic Inquiry. We’ll use the history of evolutionary thought to understand how scientists, theologians, and others have thought about what it means to be human and to live together in organized societies—and about how we became such social animals. In the process, we’ll interpret not only scientific texts for both professional and popular audiences, but also novels, visual art, film, and works of philosophy and theology. We’ll read carefully in order both to understand how arguments work and how the ideas of evolutionary thinkers have been shaped by the particular times, places, and experiences in which they lived, as well as by changing media and systems of publishing and scientific communication.</p>

<p>The course will meet for lectures on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday mornings, 9 to 9:50, from January 9 to April 28, in Von Kleinsmid Center room 102. I will be available for office hours on Mondays from 10:00 to 12:00 in Social Sciences Building room 281, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>

<p>This course is organized around substantial reading assignments of primary sources, which is to say texts written by biologists, geologists, philosophers, theologians, and other participants in the evolution debates. We’ll discuss readings during <!--both lecture and discussion sections-->every class, so please read everything assigned before the class meeting it’s listed under. Each week I will expect you post a short reaction to the reading by Sunday (or by Tuesday on weeks when the class doesn’t meet on Monday) using <a href="https://blackboard.usc.edu/webapps/blogs-journals/execute/viewBlog?course_id=_166003_1&blog_id=_72576_1">Blackboard’s blog feature</a>. You can use this as an opportunity to raise questions, to comment on arguments you found particularly surprising or compelling, or to suggest ways the reading might relate to previous readings or forthcoming assignments.</p>

<p>You are required to buy two books, both of which are also available at the USC Bookstore. Please buy these specific editions, so we can refer to the same page numbers and editor’s notes:</p>
<ul>
	<li><cite><a href="http://greenlion.com/books/Darwin_GC.html">Selections from Darwin’s Origin of Species: The Shape of the Argument</a></cite>, edited by Nicholas Maistrellis, Green Cat Books edition (2009).</li>
	<li>H.G. Wells, <cite><a href="http://books.wwnorton.com/books/webad.aspx?id=11735">The Time Machine</a></cite>, edited by Stephen Arata, Norton Critical Edition (2008).</li>
</ul>

<p>All other required readings for the course will be available online; for the first half of the semester, we’ll mostly be reading texts available through the web repository <a href="https://www.hathitrust.org/">HathiTrust</a> (and linked to below). When we get to more recent texts, I’ll make scanned copies of the excerpts we’re reading available to you.</p>

<p>My lectures will provide historical context for these readings, introduce you to debates between historians about their significance, and describe the roles of historical figures beyond those whose work you’re reading. You’re therefore not required to read a textbook for the course, but if you’d like one to refer to or to follow along in for an additional perspective on this history, I’ve included page numbers below for relevant sections of Peter J. Bowler, <cite><a href="http://www.ucpress.edu/book.php?isbn=9780520261280">Evolution: The History of an Idea</a></cite>, third edition (2003), which is available from the USC Bookstore and on reserve at Leavey Library’s circulation desk, and listed with them some other books for further reading or as sources for writing papers. Two other useful reference sources will be the <cite>Dictionary of Scientific Biography</cite> and the <cite><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</a></cite>, each of which is useful for finding introductory information on particular scientists and philosophers and citations for books and articles that provide more detailed information.</p>

<p>Your first substantial writing assignment, due February 10, will be a paper approximately five pages long in which you develop <a href="review">your own analysis of a review of <cite>The Origin of Species</cite></a>, contextualizing it in the life of its author, with attention to their other scientific, religious, political, and philosophical interests and commitments, and in the editorial agenda of the publication in which it appears. We’ll spend some time in class looking at different ways you might find such reviews and research their authors and publications.</p>

<p>Your second writing assignment, due April 7, will be an <a href="book">online exhibit on a particular book in the evolution debates as a material text</a>. In this exhibit, you’ll demonstrate what you can learn from looking at a physical book about its intended audience and how it was meant to be read. We’ll spend some time in class in advance of this assignment thinking about books in precisely this way, and will visit the USC Libraries’ Special Collections to look at original editions of books on evolution including some of those we’ve read ourselves. You’ll also have an opportunity to present the book you’re thinking about to the class on March 3.</p>

<p>Your last essay assignment, of approximately five pages and due April 28, will be to analyze what was at stake in a particular controversy about evolution. What did the people involved care about? What did they want to persuade others of? How did they use the idea of evolution to do so?</p>

<p>Additionally, there will be a midterm exam during class on March 10 and a final exam on May 5. These exams may involve short answer questions, longer essay questions, or a combination. In any case, the purpose will be more to evaluate your understanding of how ideas about evolution and its scientific, social, and religious consequences have changed over time, and less to test your memory of specific names or dates.</p>

<p>Your grade for the course will be based 15% on each of the two essays, 15% on the online exhibit, 15% on each of the two exams, 10% on reading responses, and 15% on your engaged and insightful participation in class.</p>


<h3 id="schedule">Schedule of Class Topics and Readings</h3>

<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 9: What Are the Evolution Debates?</h5>
		<ul>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Peter J. Bowler, <cite>Evolution: The History of an Idea</cite>, third edition (2003), 1–26.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="stable">Is Nature Stable or Changing?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, January 11: The Great Chain of Being and the System of Nature <!--(29 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Charles Bonnet, <cite>The Contemplation of Nature</cite> (1764), translated and abridged in John Wesley, <cite>A Survey of the Wisdom of God in the Creation</cite> (1777), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc2.ark:/13960/t83j3c60t">volume 4</a>, 49–51, 58–62, 87–96.</li>
			<li>Carl Linnaeus, <cite>A General System of Nature</cite> (1735–1768), revised by Johann Friedrich Gmelin (1788–1793) and translated by William Turton (1800), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=ncs1.ark:/13960/t1fj2zn1z">volume 1</a>, 1–11.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 48–71; Arthur O. Lovejoy, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.05488.0001.001">The Great Chain of Being: A Study of the History of an Idea</a></cite> (1936); Michel Foucault, <cite>The Order of Things: An Archeology of the Human Sciences</cite> (1966; 1970); Londa Schiebinger, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2166840">Why Mammals Are Called Mammals: Gender Politics in Eighteenth-Century Natural History</a>” (1993).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, January 13: Evolution in an Age of Revolutions <!--(32 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Jean-Baptiste Lamarck, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044066262601">Zoological Philosophy</a></cite> (1809), translated by Hugh Elliot (1914), 1–8, 35–46, 68–70, 106–114.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 71–95; Adrian Desmond, <cite>The Politics of Evolution: Morphology, Medicine, and Reform in Radical London</cite> (1989).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 16: <i>No class for Martin Luther King, Jr. Day</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, January 18: <i>No class</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, January 20: Natural Theology <!--(62 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Thomas Malthus, <cite><a href="https://archive.org/details/essayonprinciple00malt_1">An Essay on the Principle of Population</a></cite> (1798), 11–17, 356–371.</li>
			<li>William Paley, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uva.x001197535">Natural Theology</a></cite> (1802), 1–21, 454–459, 467–469, 473–481.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 96–106.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 23: Catastrophe and Uniformity <!--(39 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Georges Cuvier, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015032031943">Essay on the Theory of the Earth</a></cite> (1813), translated by Robert Kerr (1815), 5–17.</li>
			<li>Charles Lyell, <cite>Principles of Geology</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433066370341">volume 1</a> (1830), 1–4; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044103125563">volume 2</a> (1832), 18–32; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433066370366">volume 3</a> (1833), 1–7.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 106–134; Charles Coulston Gillespie, <cite>Genesis and Geology: A Study in the Relations of Scientific Thought, Natural Theology, and Social Opinion in Great Britain, 1790–1850</cite> (1951); Martin S. Rudwick, <cite>Bursting the Limits of Time: The Reconstruction of Geohistory in the Age of Revolution</cite> (2005) and <cite>Worlds Before Adam: The Reconstruction of Geohistory in the Age of Reform</a></cite> (2008).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, January 25: Popular Evolutionism <!--(48 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Robert Chambers, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044107245359">The Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</a></cite> (1844), 113–119, 145–147, 153–161, 174–178, and 268–291.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 134–140; James Secord, <cite>Victorian Sensation: The Extraordinary Publication, Reception, and Secret Authorship of <cite>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</cite></cite> (2000).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="darwin">Darwin and Wallace’s Answers</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, January 27: The Voyages of Charles Darwin and Alfred Russell Wallace <!--(10 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Charles Darwin, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015074623516">Journal and Remarks</a></cite> (1839), 453–457, 461–465.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 141–155; Janet Browne, <cite>Charles Darwin: Voyaging</cite> (1995).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 30: “One Long Argument” <!--(65 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Charles Darwin, <cite>On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection</cite> (1859), edited by Nicholas Maistrellis, Green Cat Books edition (2009), 5–7, 13–26, 31–42, 47–65, 71–77, 83–94, 99–105.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 155–176; Piers Hale, <cite>Political Descent: Malthus, Mutualism, and the Politics of Evolution in Victorian England</cite> (2014), 1–65; Janet Browne, <cite>Charles Darwin: The Power of Place</cite> (2002).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 1: The Reception of Darwinism</h5>
		<ul>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 177–202; Alvar Ellegård, <cite>Darwin and the General Reader: The Reception of Darwin’s Theory of Evolution in the British Periodical Press, 1859–1872</cite> (1958); David L. Hull, <cite>Darwin and His Critics: The Reception of Darwin’s Theory of Evolution by the Scientific Community</cite> (1973); <cite>The Comparative Reception of Darwinism</cite>, edited by Thomas F. Glick (1974); <cite>Disseminating Darwinism: The Role of Place, Race, Religion, and Gender</cite>, edited by Ronald L. Numbers and John Stenhouse (1999); <cite>The Reception of Charles Darwin in Europe</cite>, edited by Eve-Marie Engels and Thomas F. Glick (2008).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 3: <i>Introduction to Special Collections</i></h5>
		<ul>	
			<li><i>Meet in <a href="https://libraries.usc.edu/locations/special-collections">USC Special Collections</a>, Doheny Memorial Library room 206.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="atheistic">Is Darwinism Atheistic?</h4>
<ul>
	<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 202–207; James Moore, <cite>The Post-Darwinian Controversies: A Study of the Protestant Struggle to Come to Terms with Darwin in Great Britain and America, 1870–1900</cite> (1979); Jon H. Roberts, <cite>Darwinism and the Divine in America: Protestant Intellectuals and Organic Evolution, 1859–1900</cite> (1988).</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 6: Anti-Evolutionism <!--(24 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>	
			<li>Charles Hodge, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044019200393">What Is Darwinism?</a></cite> (1874), 1–2, 40–48, 52–53, 168–178.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 8: Christian Darwinism <!--(29 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>George Frederick Wright, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015074659486;seq=371">Concerning the True Doctrine of Final Cause or Design in Nature</a>,” <cite>Bibliotheca Sacra</cite> 34 (1877): 357–385.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 10: <i>The Evolution Debates in Special Collections</i></h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Meet in USC Special Collections.</i></li>
			<li><i>Paper due <a href="review">contextualizing a review of <cite>The Origin of Species</cite></a>.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="humans">How Did Humans Evolve?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 13: Monogenism and Polygenism <!--(36 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Louis Agassiz, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433081670469;seq=118">The Diversity of Origin of the Human Races</a>,” <cite>Christian Examiner</cite> 49 (1850): 110–113, 126–128, 136–138, 141–145.</li>
			<li>Frederick Douglass, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.69015000002739">The Claims of the Negro, Ethnologically Considered</a></cite> (1854), 9–10, 12–18, 34–35.</li>
			<li>Charles Darwin, <cite>The Descent of Man, and Selection in Relation to Sex</cite> (1871), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=osu.32435064734387">volume 1</a>, 9–10, 220–227.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 207–216, 292–297.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 15: Sexual Selection <!--(31 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Darwin, <cite>Descent of Man</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=osu.32435064734387">volume 1</a>, 245–251, 263–266; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hw2p3s">volume 2</a>, 301–302, 310–314.</li>
			<li>Eliza Burt Gamble, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.rslxyf">The Evolution of Woman</a></cite> (1894), 19–31.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 313–315; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 106–154; Cynthia Eagle Russett, <cite>Sexual Science: The Victorian Construction of Womanhood</cite> (1989); Kimberly A. Hamlin, <cite>From Eve to Evolution: Darwin, Science, and Women’s Rights in Gilded Age America</cite> (2014).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 17: Herbert Spencer’s Universal Evolutionism <!--(29 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044014674535">First Principles</a></cite> (1862), 146–174. (An earlier version of this chapter, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.31158008177155;seq=254">Progress: Its Law and Cause</a>,” <cite>Westminster Review</cite> 67 (1857), is also available.)</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 220–223; Mark Francis, <cite>Herbert Spencer and the Invention of Modern Life</cite> (2007); <cite>Global Spencerism: The Communication and Appropriation of a British Evolutionist</cite>, edited by Bernard Lightman (2015).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 20: <i>No class for Presidents Day</i></h5>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="politics">The Politics of Evolution: Competitive or Cooperative?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 22: Individualism <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044011566569">Social Statics</a></cite> (1851), 16–38.</li>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite>The Principles of Biology</cite> (1864), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044009912734">volume 1</a>, 443–445.</li>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite>The Principles of Sociology</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.ah5dvt">volume 3</a> (1896), 608–611.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 274–277, 298–302; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 66–105.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 24: Liberalism <!--(20 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Thomas Henry Huxley, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101065273508;seq=171">The Struggle for Existence: A Programme</a>,” <cite>Nineteenth Century</cite>, February 1888, 161–180.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 216–220; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 155–221.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 27: Socialism <!--(25 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Peter Kropotkin, “Mutual Aid Among Animals,” <cite>Nineteenth Century</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101065273474;seq=351">September 1890</a>, 337–349, 354; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101065273474;seq=712">November 1890</a>, 709–719.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 305–307, 315–317; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 222–251; Daniel Todes, <cite>Darwin Without Malthus: The Struggle for Existence in Russian Evolutionary Thought</cite> (1989).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 1: Communism <!--(26 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Lewis Henry Morgan, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044011479847">Ancient Society</a></cite> (1877), 3–18, 551–554.</li>
			<li>Frederick Engels, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015024944756">The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State</a></cite> (1884), translated by Ernest Untermann (1902), 102–103, 116–119.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 284–292.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 3: <i>Presentations on Special Collections</i></h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Meet in USC Special Collections.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="eclipse">The Eclipse of Darwinism: What Are the Mechanisms of Evolution?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, March 6: Neo-Darwinism and Neo-Lamarckism <!--(27 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Ernst Haeckel, <cite>The History of Creation</cite> (1868), translated by Edwin Ray Lankester (1876), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=inu.30000041570254">volume 1</a>, 280–292.</li>
			<li>Edwin Ray Lankester, <cite>Degeneration: A Chapter in Darwinism</cite> (1880), excerpted in H.G. Wells, <cite>The Time Machine</cite> (1895), edited by Stephen Arata, Norton Critical Edition (2008), 160–163.</li>
			<li>H.G. Wells, “Zoological Retrogression” (1891), excerpted in Wells, <cite>Time Machine</cite>, 133–135.</li>
			<li>August Weismann, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hc4pef">The Germ-Plasm: A Theory of Heredity</a></cite> (1892), translated by W. Newton Parker and Harriet R&ouml;nnfeldt (1893), ix–xv.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 224–256; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 252–353; Peter J. Bowler, <cite>The Eclipse of Darwinism: Anti-Darwinian Evolution Theories in the Decades around 1900</cite> (1983).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 8: “The Deathbed of Darwinism”? <!--(36 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Alexander Patterson, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015028720707">The Other Side of Evolution</a></cite> (1903), vii–xix, 120–136.</li>
			<li>Vernon Kellogg, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.$b572418">Darwinism To-Day</a></cite> (1907), 1–7.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Ronald L. Numbers, <cite>The Creationists: From Scientific Creationism to Intelligent Design</cite> (1992; 2006).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 10: <i>Midterm exam</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>March 12–19: <i>No class for spring break</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, March 20: Evolutionary Fiction <!--(71 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>H.G. Wells, <cite>Time Machine</cite> (1895), 1–71.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 22: Genetics and Eugenics <!--(27 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Francis Galton, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.$b676997;view=2up;seq=168">Hereditary Talent and Character</a>,” <cite>Macmillan’s Magazine</cite>, June 1865, 157–166.</li>
			<li>William Bateson, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=umn.31951d00400715m;seq=64">Problems of Heredity as a Subject for Horticultural Investigation</a>,” <cite>Journal of the Royal Horticultural Society</cite> 25 (1900): 54–61.</li>
			<li>Charles Davenport, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hc19hh">Heredity in Relation to Eugenics</a></cite> (1911), iii–vi, 1–5.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 256–273, 307–313; Diane Paul, <cite>Controlling Human Heredity, 1865 to the Present</cite> (1995).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 24: <i>No class</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, March 27: Creative Evolution <!--(55 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Henri Bergson, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044021581178">Creative Evolution</a></cite> (1907), translated by Arthur Mitchell (1911), ix–xv, 84–97, 163–165, 176–185, 251–271.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 317–322; R. C. Grogin, <cite>The Bergsonian Controversy in France, 1900–1914</cite> (1988).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 29: The Scopes Monkey Trial and the Revival of Creationism <!--(27 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>William Jennings Bryan, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015026299282">In His Image</a></cite> (1922), 86–94, 102–109, 122–127, 132–135.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 375–381; Numbers, <cite>Creationists</cite>; Edward J. Larson, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.00666.0001.001">Summer for the Gods: The Scopes Trial and America’s Continuing Debate over Science and Religion</a></cite> (1997); Adam R. Shapiro, <cite>Trying Biology: The Scopes Trial, Textbooks, and the Antievolution Movement in American Schools</cite> (2013).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="synthesis">The Evolutionary Synthesis: Is Evolution Progressive?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 31: Population Genetics and the Modern Synthesis <!--(17 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>R.A. Fisher, <cite><a href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/title/27468">The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection</a></cite> (1930), vii–x, 256–258.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, <cite>Genetics and the Origin of Species</cite> (1937), <a href="readings/Genetics%20and%20the%20Origin%20of%20Species.pdf">3–12</a>.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 325–340; Vassiliki Betty Smokovitis, <cite>Unifying Biology: The Evolutionary Synthesis and Evolutionary Biology</cite> (1996); Robert D. Kohler, <cite>Lords of the Fly: Drosophila Genetics and the Experimental Life</cite> (1994).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 3: Evolutionary Progress <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Julian Huxley, <cite>Evolution: The Modern Synthesis</cite> (1942), <a href="readings/Evolution.pdf">556–569, 576–578</a>.</li> <!--Pages missing from scan, and add 575-->
			<li>George Gaylord Simpson, <cite>The Meaning of Evolution</cite> (1949), <a href="readings/The%20Meaning%20of%20Evolution.pdf">240–246</a>.</li>
			<li>George Gaylord Simpson, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/40970168">The Concept of Progress in Organic Evolution</a>,” <cite>Social Research</cite> 41 (1974): 46–51.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 340–346; Michael Ruse, <cite>Monad to Man: The Concept of Progress in Evolutionary Biology</cite> (1996).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 5: The Teilhardian Synthesis <!--(68 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, <cite>The Phenomenon of Man</cite> (1938/1955), translated by Bernard Wall (1959), <a href="readings/The%20Phenomenon%20of%20Man.pdf">11–14, 27–28, 180–184, 237–245, 257–272, 291–299</a>.</li>
			<li>Peter Medawar, <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2252158">review of <cite>The Phenomenon of Man</cite></a>, <cite>Mind</cite> 70 (1961): 99–106.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, <cite>The Biology of Ultimate Concern</cite> (1967), <a href="readings/The%20Biology%20of%20Ultimate%20Concern.pdf">114–122, 133–137</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 7: <i>No class</i></h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Online exhibit due <a href="book">on an evolutionary book as a material text</a>.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 10: Scientific Creationism <!--(22 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>John C. Whitcomb and Henry M. Morris, <cite>The Genesis Flood</cite> (1961), <a href="readings/The%20Genesis%20Flood.pdf">xix–xxii, xxv–xxix, 63–70</a>.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4444260">Nothing in Biology Makes Sense Except in the Light of Evolution</a>,” <cite>American Biology Teacher</cite> 35 (1973): 125–129.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Numbers, <cite>Creationists</cite>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 12: The Evolution of Human Race <!--(34 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Carleton Putnam, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.b3365886">Race and Reason: A Yankee View</a></cite> (1961), vii–viii, 1, 36–37, 40–41.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, “<a href="https://academic.oup.com/jhered/article/52/4/189/812767/A-BOGUS-SCIENCE-OF-RACE-PREJUDICE">A Bogus ‘Science’ of Race Prejudice</a>,” <cite>Journal of Heredity</cite> 52 (1961): 189–190.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, <cite>Mankind Evolving: The Evolution of the Human Species</cite> (1962), <a href="readings/Mankind%20Evolving.pdf">253–257, 266–271, 285–286</a>.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, “<a href="http://www.nature.com/scientificamerican/journal/v208/n2/pdf/scientificamerican0263-169.pdf">A Debatable Account of the Origin of Races</a>,” <cite>Scientific American</cite>, February 1963, 169–170, 172.</li>
			<li>Richard Lewontin, “The Apportionment of Human Diversity,” <cite>Evolutionary Biology</cite> 6 (1972): <a href="readings/The%20Apportionment%20of%20Human%20Diversity.pdf">381–387, 396–397</a>.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 278–284, 302–305, 353–356; Lee D. Baker, <cite>From Savage to Negro: Anthropology and the Construction of Race, 1896–1954</cite> (1998); John P. Jackson, Jr., <cite>Science for Segregation: Race, Law, and the Case against Brown v. Board of Education</cite> (2005).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 14: Periodic Extinctions and Punctuated Equilibria <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Niles Eldridge, “<a href="readings/A%20Battle%20of%20Words.pdf">‘A Battle of Words,’</a>” in <cite>The Third Culture</cite>, edited by John Brockman (1995), 120–125.</li>
			<li>Niles Eldridge and Stephen Jay Gould, “<a href="http://www.blackwellpublishing.com/ridley/classictexts/eldredge.pdf">Punctuated Equilibria: An Alternative to Phyletic Gradualism</a>,” in <cite>Models in Paleobiology</cite>, edited by Thomas J.M. Schopf (1972), 83–98, 108–115.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 347–353; David Sepkoski, <cite>Rereading the Fossil Record: The Growth of Paleobiology as an Evolutionary Discipline</cite> (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="adaptationism">Adaptationism: Does Natural Selection Explain All Traits?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 17: Biology as an Information Science <!--(32 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>George C. Williams, “<a href="readings/A%20Package%20of%20Information.pdf">‘A Package of Information,’</a>” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 39–47.</li>
			<li>Richard Dawkins, <cite>The Selfish Gene</cite> (1976), <a href="readings/The%20Selfish%20Gene.pdf">1–11</a>.</li>
			<li>Richard Dawkins, “<a href="readings/A%20Survival%20Machine.pdf">‘A Survival Machine,’</a>” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 75–86.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 356–361.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 19: Sociobiology <!--(22 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>E.O. Wilson, <cite>Sociobiology</cite> (1975), <a href="readings/Sociobiology.pdf">3–6, 547–551, 559–565, 574–575</a>.</li>
			<li>Sociobiology Study Group of Science for the People, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1297246">Sociobiology: Another Biological Determinism</a>,” <cite>BioScience</cite> 26 (1976): 182, 184–186.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 21: The Descent of Woman <!--(39 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Elaine Morgan, <cite>The Descent of Woman</cite> (1972), <a href="readings/The%20Descent%20of%20Woman.pdf">1–13, 26–33</a>.</li>
			<li>Sarah Blaffer Hrdy, <cite>The Woman That Never Evolved</cite> (1981), <a href="readings/The%20Woman%20That%20Never%20Evolved.pdf">1–15, 189–191</a>.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Donna Haraway, <cite>Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</cite> (1989); Erika Lorraine Milam, <cite>Looking for a Few Good Males: Female Choice in Evolutionary Biology</cite> (2010).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 24: Critiques of Adaptationism <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Stephen Jay Gould, “<a href="readings/The%20Pattern%20of%20Life%27s%20History.pdf">‘The Pattern of Life’s History,’</a>” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 52–64.</li>
			<li>Stephen Jay Gould and Richard C. Lewontin, “<a href="http://www.blackwellpublishing.com/ridley/classictexts/gould.pdf">The Spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian Paradigm</a>,” <cite>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London</cite> 205 (1979): 581–597.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 361–374.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 26: The Revival of Natural Theology <!--(47 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Richard Dawkins, <cite>The Blind Watchmaker</cite> (1986), <a href="readings/The%20Blind%20Watchmaker.pdf">1–9</a>.</li>
			<li>William A. Dembski, “<a href="readings/The%20Logical%20Underpinnings%20of%20Intelligent%20Design.pdf">The Logical Underpinnings of Intelligent Design</a>,” in <cite>Debating Design: From Darwin to DNA</cite>, edited by William A. Dembski and Michael Ruse (2004), 311–329.</li>
			<li>Michael J. Behe, “Irreducible Complexity: Obstacle to Darwinian Evolution,” in Dembski and Ruse, <cite>Debating Design</cite>, <a href="readings/Irreducible%20Complexity.pdf">352–355</a>.</li>
			<li>Kenneth R. Miller, “<a href="readings/The%20Flagellum%20Unspun.pdf">The Flagellum Unspun: The Collapse of ‘Irreducible Complexity,’</a>” in Dembski and Ruse, <cite>Debating Design</cite>, 81–95.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Numbers, <cite>Creationists</cite>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 28: Symbiogenesis <!--(41 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Lynn Margulis, “<a href="readings/Gaia%20Is%20a%20Tough%20Bitch.pdf">‘Gaia Is a Tough Bitch,’</a>” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 130–140.</li>
			<li>Lynn Margulis and Dorion Sagan, <cite>Acquiring Genomes: A Theory of the Origin of Species</cite> (2002), <a href="readings/Acquiring%20Genomes.pdf">xi–xvi, 11–23, 51–56, 201–205</a>.</li>
			<li><i>Paper due analyzing the stakes of a particular evolution controversy.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, May 5: <i>Final exam from 8:00 to 10:00</i></h5>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="biology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="science" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="geology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="white supremacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the evolution of life generally and humanity in particular became scientific orthodoxy in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, scientists and other intellectuals debated what this meant. Some conceptions of God were compatible with evolution and others were not, for example, but the inverse was also true: certain conceptions of evolution were compatible with God and others were not. And at the same time, some conceptions of evolution emphasized cooperation and suggested humans would achieve the happiest lives through socialism, while others emphasized the roles of competition and “survival of the fittest” and suggested that capitalism was a better system for human achievement. Some theories of human evolution justified white supremacy, while others suggested racial equality. As a result, debates about biology were often also debates about religion and politics, and the three fields were repeatedly re-formed together.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">America and the Cold War World, 1945–1991</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2016/coldwar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America and the Cold War World, 1945–1991" /><published>2016-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2016/coldwar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2016/coldwar/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for America in the Cold War World, 1945–1991, a course offered in fall 2016 as HIST 465 at the University of Southern California. This is a course on the political and cultural history of the United States in its global context. We’ll seek to understand how the rivalry between the United States and the Soviet Union shaped how Americans lived their lives and exercised power, paying particular attention to American science, technology, media, popular culture, and family life, as well as to Americans’ engagements with the rest of the world.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Thursday afternoons, 2:00 to 4:50, from August 25 to December 1 in Verna and Peter Dauterive Hall room 107. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours on Wednesdays from 3:00 to 5:00 in Social Sciences Building room 281, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>

<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you read and think about them before each class meeting. Each week I will expect you post a short reaction to the reading the day before class using <a href="https://blackboard.usc.edu/webapps/blogs-journals/execute/viewBlog?course_id=_158350_1&blog_id=_68289_1">Blackboard’s blog feature</a>. You can use this as an opportunity to raise questions, to comment on arguments you found particularly surprising or compelling, or to suggest ways the reading might relate to previous readings or forthcoming assignments.</p>

<p>Your first larger assignment will be to develop your own analysis of <a href="film">a film</a> in the context of the Cold War, and to present it in a short paper of about five pages. Your second assignment will be a contribution to an <a href="http://coldwar.collopy.net/exhibits/show/assignment/assignment1">online exhibit</a> on America in the Cold War that we’ll produce together as a class. A final assignment will require you to develop your own historical analysis of an event, person, or cultural or political phenomenon, and to present an argument about how your subject shaped, and was shaped by, America in the Cold War world. That final project, which may build on your work for either of the earlier two assignments, may take the form of a traditional research paper of 15–20 pages, or you may speak with me about presenting it in another medium; in either case, you will have the opportunities to get feedback on a short proposal and a brief presentation as you work on your project. Your grade for the course will be based 20% on your film analysis, 20% on your contribution to the online guide, 30% on your final project, and 30% on your reading responses and engaged and insightful participation in discussions.</p>

<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>Please purchase the following three books, or plan to borrow them from Leavey Library’s circulation desk, where they will be on reserve. The first two are available at the <a href="https://uscbookstore.com/">USC Bookstores</a>; <cite>The Culture of the Cold War</cite> is out of print, so please seek out a used or library copy.</p>

<ul>
	<li>Robert J. McMahon, <cite>The Cold War: A Very Short Introduction</cite> (2003).</li>
	<li>Jeremi Suri, <cite>Power and Protest: Global Revolution and the Rise of Detente</cite> (2003).</li>
	<li>Stephen J. Whitfield, <cite>The Culture of the Cold War</cite>, second edition (1996, revised from 1991 original).</li>
</ul>

<p>All other readings will be available through links below. If you prefer print to reading off a screen, though, you may still want to buy or borrow a few more books. The ones we’ll be reading substantial chunks of, which will also be available on reserve at Leavey, include:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Thomas Borstelmann, <cite>The Cold War and the Color Line: American Race Relations in the Global Arena</cite> (2001).</li>
	<li>Michael D. Gordin, <cite>Five Days in August: How World War II Became a Nuclear War</cite> (2007).</li>
	<li>Van Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left: An Interpretive History</a></cite> (2005).</li>
	<li>Elaine Tyler May, <cite>Homeward Bound: American Families in the Cold War Era</cite>, revised edition (2008, revised from 1988 original).</li>
	<li>Lisa McGirr, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.02237.0001.001">Suburban Warriors: The Origins of the New American Right</a></cite> (2002).</li>
	<li>Odd Arne Westad, <cite>The Global Cold War: Third World Interventions and the Making of Our Times</cite> (2005).</li>
</ul>

<p class="box">Boxes like this one contain suggestions for additional reading. You might want to read beyond the assigned reading based on your curiosity, as research for an assignment, or ideally for both reasons, as you use an assignment to pursue your own interests.</p>


<h3>Schedule</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>August 25: Introduction</h4>
		<ul>
			<li><i>In class:</i> George Orwell, “<a href="http://orwell.ru/library/articles/ABomb/english/e_abomb">You and the Atomic Bomb</a>” (1945), Harry Truman, “<a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/truman-hiroshima/">Statement by the President of the United States</a>” (1945), and Stanley Kubrick, <cite>Dr. Strangelove or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb</cite> (1964).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 1: The Atomic Age <!--(148 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Eric Schlosser, “<a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/almost-everything-in-dr-strangelove-was-true">Almost Everything in <cite>Dr. Strangelove</cite> Was True</a>,” <cite>New Yorker</cite> (2014).</li>
			<li>Michael D. Gordin, <cite><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt163tcm5">Five Days in August: How World War II Became a Nuclear War</a></cite> (2007), chapters 1, 3, and 6–7.</li>
			<li>Naomi Oreskes, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qf6k8.5">Science in the Origins of the Cold War</a>,” in <cite>Science and Technology in the Global Cold War</cite>, edited by Naomi Oreskes and John Krige (2014).</li>
			<li>Paul Boyer, <cite>By the Bomb’s Early Light: American Thought and Culture at the Dawn of the Atomic Age</cite> (1985), <a href="readings/By%20the%20Bomb's%20Early%20Light.pdf">chapters 1 and 26–27, and epilogue</a>.</li>
			<li class="box">For more on Cold War science, see Audra J. Wolfe, <cite>Competing with the Soviets: Science, Technology, and the State in Cold War America</cite> (2013) and its bibliography. On nuclear weapons in the context of the U.S. military, see Eric Schlosser, <cite>Command and Control: Nuclear Weapons, the Damascus Accident, and the Illusion of Safety</cite> (2013), and Alex Wellerstein’s blog <a href="http://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/">Restricted Data</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 8: Soviet and American Systems <!--(129 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Robert J. McMahon, <cite>The Cold War: A Very Short Introduction</cite> (2003), chapters 1–2.</li>
			<li>Odd Arne Westad, <cite>The Global Cold War: Third World Interventions and the Making of Our Times</cite> (2005), <a href="readings/The%20Global%20Cold%20War.pdf">introduction and chapters 1–2</a>.</li>
			<li>Raymond Williams, “Capitalism,” “Communism,” “Democracy,” “Imperialism,” “Liberal,” and “Socialist,” in <cite><a href="readings/Keywords.pdf">Keywords: A Vocabulary for Culture and Society</a></cite>, revised edition (1983, revised from 1976 original).</li>
			<li>David F. Ruccio, “<a href="http://search.credoreference.com/content/entry/nyupacs/capitalism/">Capitalism</a>,” in <cite>Keywords for American Cultural Studies</cite>, edited by Bruce Burgett and Glenn Hendler (2014).</li>
			<li>Nikhil Pal Singh, “<a href="http://search.credoreference.com/content/entry/nyupacs/liberalism/">Liberalism</a>,” in Burgett and Hendler, <cite>Keywords for American Cultural Studies</cite>.</li>
            <li class="box">John Lewis Gaddis, <cite>The Cold War: A New History</cite> (2005) is a standard history of the Cold War as a bipolar conflict. <cite><a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/series/cambridge-history-of-the-cold-war/DEFB061DD8FD3DA500549912A13F03CE">The Cambridge History of the Cold War</a></cite>, edited by Melvyn P. Leffler and Odd Arne Westad (2010), is an extensive, three-volume collection of essays. For more on the cultural Cold War, see Audra J. Wolfe’s <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160314004755/http://backlist.cc/lists/cultural-cold-war">introductory bibliography</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 15: Anticommunism and the Domestic Cold War <!--(150 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Stephen J. Whitfield, <cite>The Culture of the Cold War</cite>, second edition (1996, revised from 1991 original), chapters 1–2, 4, 6, and 8–9.</li>
			<li class="box">Starting places for additional reading include Ellen Schrecker, <cite>Many Are the Crimes: McCarthyism in America</cite> (1998); Thomas Doherty, <cite>Cold War, Cool Medium: Television, McCarthyism, and American Culture</cite> (2003); and David K. Johnson, <cite>The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government</cite> (2004).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 22: Nuclear Families <!--(144 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Kenneth T. Jackson, <cite>Crabgrass Frontier: The Suburbanization of the United States</cite> (1985), <a href="readings/Crabgrass%20Frontier.pdf">chapters 13–14</a>.</li>
			<li>Elaine Tyler May, <cite>Homeward Bound: American Families in the Cold War Era</cite>, revised edition (2008, revised from 1988 original), introduction and chapters 1, 4, and 6–7.</li>
			<li class="box">For more on redlining and segregation, see chapter 11 of <cite>Crabgrass Frontier</cite> and Ta-Nehisi Coates, “<a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2014/06/the-case-for-reparations/361631/">The Case for Reparations</a>” (2014). Ta-Nehisi Coates, “<a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2014/06/home-is-where-the-hatred-is/373510/">Home is Where the Hatred Is</a>” (2014) is a bibliography. On how experts changed cities during the Cold War, see Jennifer S. Light, <cite>From Warfare to Welfare: Defense Intellectuals and Urban Problems in Cold War America</cite> (2003).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>September 29: The Global Cold War <!--(149 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McMahon, <cite>Cold War</cite>, chapters 3–5.</li>
			<li>Westad, <cite>Global Cold War</cite>, <a href="readings/The%20Global%20Cold%20War%20chapter%203.pdf">chapter 3</a>.</li>
			<li>Greg Grandin, <cite>The Last Colonial Massacre: Latin America in the Cold War</cite> (2004), <a href="readings/The%20Last%20Colonial%20Massacre.pdf">preface and introduction</a>.</li>
			<li>Jacob Darwin Hamblin, <cite>Arming Mother Nature: The Birth of Catastrophic Environmentalism</cite> (2013), <a href="readings/Arming%20Mother%20Nature.pdf">chapter 6</a>.</li>
			<li class="box">There are many directions to go for additional reading, but for samples of recent essays see <cite>Environmental Histories of the Cold War</cite>, edited by J. R. McNeill and Corinna R. Unger (2010), and <cite>The Cold War in the Third World</cite>, edited by Robert J. McMahon (2013). The Korean War is conspicuously absent from cultural histories of the Cold War, but for diplomatic and military history see Bruce Cumings, <cite>The Korean War: A History</cite> (2010); Wada Haruki, <cite>The Korean War: An International History</cite>, translated by Frank Baldwin (2014); and Allan R. Millett, <cite>The Korean War</cite>, The Essential Bibliography Series (2007).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>Monday, October 3: Paper due <a href="film">contextualizing a film</a></h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 6: Black Liberation Movements I <!--(136 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Thomas Borstelmann, <cite>The Cold War and the Color Line: American Race Relations in the Global Arena</cite> (2001), prologue and chapters 2–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 13: Black Liberation Movements II <!--(147 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Borstelmann, <cite>Cold War and the Color Line</cite>, chapters 5–6, and epilogue.</li>
			<li>Van Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left: An Interpretive History</a></cite> (2005), chapter 9.</li>
			<li>Ryan J. Kirkby, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/crv.2011.0001">‘The Revolution Will Not Be Televised’: Community Activism and the Black Panther Party, 1966–1971</a>,” <cite>Canadian Review of American Studies</cite> (2011).</li>
			<li class="box">Chapters 4 and 9 of <a href="http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/bbm%3A978-1-4039-8014-4%2F1.pdf">the bibliography of <cite>Rethinking the New Left</cite></a> are important starting points for further reading, as is the <a href="http://www.aaihs.org/blackpanthersyllabus/">#blackpanthersyllabus</a>, compiled by Keisha N. Blain, Ashley Farmer, and Dara Vance (2016). Joshua Bloom and Waldo E. Martin, Jr., <cite>Black Against Empire: The History and Politics of the Black Panther Party</cite> (2012) is a detailed narrative history of the BPP.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4 class="newpage">October 20: The Vietnam War <!--(154 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Jeremi Suri, <cite>Power and Protest: Global Revolution and the Rise of Detente</cite> (2003), introduction and chapters 4–5.</li>
			<li>Christian G. Appy, <cite>American Reckoning: The Vietnam War and Our National Identity</cite> (2015), <a href="readings/American%20Reckoning.pdf">introduction and chapter 5</a>.</li>
			<li>Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left</a></cite>, chapter 8.</li>
			<li class="box">Even without leaving campus you can find hundreds of books on the Vietnam War, as you can see for yourself by browsing DS557 to DS559 in Doheny Library. Starting places for further reading include the rest of <cite>American Reckoning</cite>; Mark Atwood Lawrence, <cite>The Vietnam War: A Concise International History</cite> (2008); and <cite>A Vietnam War Reader: A Documentary History from American and Vietnamese Perspectives</cite>, edited by Michael H. Hunt (2010).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 27: Detente and New Radicalisms <!--(154 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McMahon, <cite>Cold War</cite>, chapter 7.</li>
			<li>Suri, <cite>Power and Protest</cite>, chapter 6 and conclusion.</li>
			<li>Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left</a></cite>, chapters 10–13.</li>
			<li class="box">Again, <a href="http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/bbm%3A978-1-4039-8014-4%2F1.pdf">the bibliography of <cite>Rethinking the New Left</cite></a> is a good starting point for further reading.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>Monday, October 31: Contribution due to <a href="http://coldwar.collopy.net/exhibits/show/assignment/assignment1">online exhibit</a></h4>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>November 3: New Conservatisms I <!--(150 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lisa McGirr, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.02237.0001.001">Suburban Warriors: The Origins of the New American Right</a></cite> (2002), introduction and chapters 2–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 10: New Conservatisms II <!--(142 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McGirr, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.02237.0001.001">Suburban Warriors</a></cite>, chapters 5–6, and epilogue.</li>
			<li>Corey Robin, <cite>The Reactionary Mind: Conservatism from Edmund Burke to Sarah Palin</cite> (2011), <a href="readings/The%20Reactionary%20Mind.pdf">pages 3–17</a>.</li>
			<li>Daniel T. Rodgers, <cite>Age of Fracture</cite> (2011), prologue and chapter 1.</li>
			<li class="box">Other starting places for reading on Cold War conservatism include Rick Perlstein’s trilogy <cite>Before the Storm: Barry Goldwater and the Unmaking of the American Consensus</cite> (2001), <cite>Nixonland: The Rise of a President and the Fracturing of America</cite> (2008), and <cite>The Invisible Bridge: The Fall of Nixon and the Rise of Reagan</cite> (2014), as well as <a href="http://www.publicbooks.org/feature/trump-syllabus-20">Trump Syllabus 2.0</a>, compiled by N. D. B. Connolly and Keisha N. Blain (2016), and Sean Wilentz, <cite>The Age of Reagan: A History, 1974–2008</cite> (2008).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>Monday, November 14: Final project proposal due</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 17: Ends of the Cold War and Beyond <!--(139 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McMahon, <cite>Cold War</cite>, chapter 8.</li>
			<li>Francis Fukuyama, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24027184">The End of History?</a>” <cite>National Interest</cite>, Summer 1989.</li>
			<li>John Lewis Gaddis, <cite>We Now Know: Rethinking Cold War History</cite> (1997), <a href="readings/We%20Now%20Know.pdf">chapter 10</a>.</li>
			<li>Jon Wiener, <cite>How We Forgot the Cold War: A Historical Journey across America</cite> (2012), <a href="readings/How%20We%20Forgot%20the%20Cold%20War.pdf">introduction, chapters 1 and 21, conclusion, and epilogue</a>.</li>
			<li>Appy, <cite>American Reckoning</cite>, <a href="readings/American%20Reckoning%20chapter%2011.pdf">chapter 11</a>.</li>
			<li class="box">Few historians have yet written extensively about the 1980s and beyond, though <cite>Age of Fracture</cite> and <cite>The Age of Reagan</cite> are important exceptions. For more historiography of the Cold War, see <cite>Cold War Triumphalism: The Misuse of History after the Fall of Communism</cite>, edited by Ellen Schrecker (2004), and <cite>Uncertain Empire: American History and the Idea of the Cold War</cite>, edited by Joel Isaac and Duncan Bell (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 24: <i>No class for Thanksgiving</i></h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 1: Final project presentations</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 8: Final project due</h4>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="war" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="liberalism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="white supremacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for America in the Cold War World, 1945–1991, a course offered in fall 2016 as HIST 465 at the University of Southern California. This is a course on the political and cultural history of the United States in its global context. We’ll seek to understand how the rivalry between the United States and the Soviet Union shaped how Americans lived their lives and exercised power, paying particular attention to American science, technology, media, popular culture, and family life, as well as to Americans’ engagements with the rest of the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technology and Society</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology and Society" /><published>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesday evenings, 6:00 to 9:00, from September 2 to December 9 in Williams Hall room 219. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Tuesdays from 5:00 to 6:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>
<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you <a href="reading">read and think about them</a> before each class meeting. Your engaged and insightful participation in discussions will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<p>The other assignments consist of three short papers, of approximately five pages each. I’ll provide more detailed prompts, but in short <a href="politics">the first paper</a> should present an argument about whether and how a particular technology “has politics,” <a href="observing">the second</a> should describe and analyze your observation of people using technology, and <a href="history">the third</a> should present a brief history of a technology of your choice. You will have an opportunity to submit a draft, get my feedback, and revise your paper before I grade it. Each paper will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>The following four books, which we’ll be reading cover-to-cover or nearly so, are available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> is also available online, and other readings will be available through links below.</p>
<ul id="books">
	<li>Lynn White, Jr., <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> (1962).</li>
	<li>Thomas J. Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet: Technology and Culture from the Renaissance to the Present</cite>, second edition (2011, revised from 2004 original).</li>
	<li>Ruth Schwartz Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother: The Ironies of Household Technology from the Open Hearth to the Microwave</cite> (1983).</li>
	<li>David Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old: Technology and Global History since 1900</cite> (2007).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Schedule</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>September 2: Introduction</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 9: Technologies of Feudalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Langdon Winner, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/20024652">Do Artifacts Have Politics?</a>” (1980).</li>
			<li>White, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite>, preface and chapters 1 and 2.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, preface and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 16: Roots of Capitalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lewis Mumford, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01149.0001.001">Technics and Civilization</a></cite> (1934), objectives and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Cynthia Cockburn, <cite>Machinery of Dominance: Women, Men, and Technical Know-How</cite> (1985), <a href="readings/Machinery%20of%20Dominance.pdf">introduction and chapter 1</a>.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 2.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 23: Print Culture</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Marshall McLuhan, <cite>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</cite> (1964), <a href="readings/Understanding%20Media.pdf">chapters 1, 16, and 18</a>.</li>
			<li>Elizabeth Eisenstein, <cite>The Printing Revolution in Early Modern Europe</cite>, second edition (2005, abridged from <cite>The Printing Press as an Agent of Change: Communications and Cultural Transformations in Early-Modern Europe</cite>, 1979), <a href="readings/The%20Printing%20Revolution%20in%20Early%20Modern%20Europe.pdf">introduction and chapters 2 and 3</a>.</li>
			<li>Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar, <cite>Laboratory Life: The Construction of Scientific Facts</cite>, second edition (1986, revised from 1979 original), <a href="readings/Laboratory%20Life.pdf">pages 43–53</a>.</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule" style="page-break-before: always">
		<h4>September 30: The Industrialization of Manufacturing</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 3.</li>
			<li>Walter Licht, <cite>Industrializing America: The Nineteenth Century</cite> (1995), <a href="readings/Industrializing%20America.pdf">introduction and chapters 2 and 3</a>.</li>
			<li>Judith A. McGaw, “<a href="readings/Gender%20and%20Papermaking.pdf">Gender and Papermaking</a>” (1998, abridged from <cite>Most Wonderful Machine: Mechanization and Social Change in Berkshire Paper Making, 1801–1885</cite>, 1987).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 7: The Industrialization of Time and Space</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 4.</li>
			<li>Wolfgang Schivelbusch, <cite>The Railway Journey: The Industrialization of Time and Space in the 19th Century</cite> (1986), <a href="readings/The%20Railway%20Journey.pdf">chapters 1–6</a>.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 14: The Industrialization of Housework</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother</cite>, chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 21: Technological Systems</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Thomas P. Hughes, <cite>American Genesis: A Century of Invention and Technological Enthusiasm 1870–1970</cite> (1989), <a href="readings/American%20Genesis.pdf">introduction and chapter 5</a>.</li>
			<li>Leo Marx, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2010.0009"><i>Technology</i>: The Emergence of a Hazardous Concept</a>” (2010, revised from 1997 original).</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>October 28: Modern Cities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 6.</li>
			<li>David Nye, <cite>Electrifying America: Social Meanings of a New Technology, 1880–1940</cite> (1990), preface and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 4: Modern Media</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Friedrich A. Kittler, <cite>Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</cite> (1999, translated from 1986 German original), <a href="readings/Gramophone,%20Film,%20Typewriter.pdf">pages 1–37</a>.</li>
			<li>Susan J. Douglas, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01134.0001.001">Inventing American Broadcasting, 1899–1922</a></cite> (1987), introduction and chapter 6.</li>
			<li>Claude S. Fischer, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb00141.0001.001">America Calling: A Social History of the Telephone to 1940</a></cite> (1992), chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 11: Alternative Modernities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5.</li>
			<li>Paul R. Josephson, <cite>Would Trotsky Wear a Bluetooth? Technological Utopianism under Socialism, 1917–1989</cite> (2010), <a href="readings/Would%20Trotsky%20Wear%20a%20Bluetooth.pdf">introduction and chapter 1</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 18: The Industrialization of Violence</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 7.</li>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 6 and 7.</li>
			<li>Paul N. Edwards, <cite><a href="http://cognet.mit.edu/book/closed-world">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (1996), pages 1–27.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>November 25: <i>No class</i></h4>
		<ul>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 2: Globalization</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 3, 4, 8 and conclusion.</li>
			<li>Carroll Pursell, <cite>The Machine in America: A Social History of Technology</cite>, second edition (2007, revised from 1994 original), <a href="readings/The%20Machine%20in%20America.pdf">chapter 13</a>.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 9: Technological Systems Revisited</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapters 9 and 10.</li>
			<li>Nathan Ensmenger, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2012.0126">The Digital Construction of Technology: Rethinking the History of Computers in Society</a>” (2012).</li>
			<li>Paolo Pedercini, “<a href="http://www.molleindustria.org/blog/videogames-and-the-spirit-of-capitalism/">Videogames and the Spirit of Capitalism</a>” (2014).</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyberculture</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyberculture" /><published>2013-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Cyberculture (STSC/SOCI 260), a course on histories and cultures of the internet offered in summer 2013 at the University of Pennsylvania. The course might also be called “Several Ways of Looking at the Internet,” “Histories and Cultures of the Internet,” or “Introduction to Internet Studies.” In this course, we will explore how people use the internet to develop new conceptions of identity, build virtual communities, and affect political change. Each class we’ll study an aspect of the history and culture of the internet, covering topics such as hackers, virtuality, sovereignty, and algorithms. We’ll read books, articles, and blogs about historical and contemporary cultures of computing, from Spacewar players and phone phreaks in the 1970s to Google, Facebook, World of Warcraft, WikiLeaks, and Anonymous today. In addition, we’ll explore some of these online communities and projects ourselves, and develop our own analyses of them.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesdays and Thursdays, 1:00 to 4:10, from May 21 to June 27 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 392. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Thursdays from 12:00 to 1:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you read and think about them before each class meeting.</p>

<p>The main component of this course other than discussions is a final project, which will involve developing your own analysis of an online community or phenomenon incorporating some ways of looking at the internet from the course. Such a project could take the form of a traditional research paper of 10–15 pages or an online presentation involving a similar amount of research and analysis; possibilities range from videos and webcomics to Twitter or Tumblr experiments and beyond. Although you are not required to make your project publicly available online, I can suggest from my own experience that it can be more exciting to produce for an audience beyond your instructor and would be happy to talk with you about appropriate online venues for sharing your project.</p>

<p>In order to help you progress toward completing your project over the course of the semester, I will ask that you meet with me to discuss your ideas for your project on May 28 or 30, submit a short (one to three page) proposal by June 6, present a progress report to the class June 11 or 13, submit a draft to me by June 20, and submit the final project on June 27, the last day of class. I will provide feedback at each of these stages. Your grade for the course will be based 20% on your proposal, 20% on your presentation, 30% on your final project, and 30% on your engaged and insightful participation in discussions.</p>

<h3>News</h3>
<p>One of the things we’ll do in this course is use recent history to find ways to think about current events. Accordingly, you may find it interesting or useful for your project to follow some news. <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/"><cite>The Atlantic</cite>’s technology channel</a> is among the best sources. <a href="http://www.wired.com/"><cite>Wired</cite></a> has many sections and blogs of varying quality, and their security blog <a href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/">Threat Level</a> is particularly good.</p>

	<p>The best source for cyberculture news might be Twitter, though, provided you follow the right people. My account is <a href="http://twitter.com/collopy">@collopy</a>, and I’ve made a list of <a href="http://twitter.com/collopy/cyberculture/">some Twitter users relevant to this course</a> that you can subscribe to, including the authors of texts on this syllabus. If you find anything online you’d like to share with the class, please tweet it using the (admittedly silly) hashtag <a href="http://twitter.com/search/realtime?q=%23cyberpenn">#cyberpenn</a>.</p>

<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>Please find a list of required readings below. Many readings are freely available online (and linked here), and I will make most of the others available to students. The exception is <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture</cite> by Fred Turner, the one book we’ll be reading in its entirety, which is available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. Other books are also available at the Penn Book Center for those who would like to own them.</p>

<h3 style="page-break-before: always">Foundations</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>May 21: Introduction</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Mitchell Kapor and John Perry Barlow, “<a href="http://w2.eff.org/Misc/Publications/John_Perry_Barlow/HTML/eff.html">Across the Electronic Frontier</a>” (1990).</li>
			<li>John Perry Barlow, “<a href="http://w2.eff.org/Censorship/Internet_censorship_bills/barlow_0296.declaration">A Declaration of the Independence of Cyberspace</a>” (1996).</li>
			<li>Bruce Schneier, “<a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2013/01/power_and_the_i.html">Power and the Internet</a>” (2013).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>May 23: Hackers</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Steven Levy, <cite>Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution</cite> (1984), <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/729/pg729.html">chapters 1 and 2</a>.</li>
			<li>Adrian Johns, <cite>Piracy: The Intellectual Property Wars from Gutenberg to Gates</cite> (2009), <a href="readings/Piracy.pdf">chapter 16</a>.</li>
			<li>Stewart Brand, “<a href="http://wheels.org/spacewar/stone/rolling_stone.html">Spacewar: Fanatic Life and Symbolic Death Among the Computer Bums</a>” (originally in <cite>Rolling Stone</cite>, 1972).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>May 28: Cybernetics</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Fred Turner, <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</cite> (2006), introduction and chapters 1–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
			<h4>May 30: Networks (“The New Economy”)</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Turner, <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture</cite>, chapters 5–8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h3>Virtual Community</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>June 4: Virtuality</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Julian Dibbell, “<a href="http://juliandibbell.com/texts/bungle_vv.html">A Rape in Cyberspace: How an Evil Clown, a Haitian Trickster Spirit, Two Wizards, and a Cast of Dozens Turned a Database Into a Society</a>” (originally in <cite>The Village Voice</cite>, 1993).</li>
		    <li>Sherry Turkle, <cite>Life on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet</cite> (1995), <a href="readings/Life%20on%20the%20Screen.pdf">chapters 7–9</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 6: Identity</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lisa Nakamura, <cite>Cybertypes: Race, Ethnicity, and Identity on the Internet</cite> (2002), <a href="readings/Cybertypes.pdf">introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 11: Play</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Bonnie Nardi, <cite><a href="http://doi.org/10.3998/toi.8008655.0001.001">My Life as a Night Elf Priest: An Anthropological Account of World of Warcraft</a></cite> (2010), prologue, chapters 1, 2, and 6–9, and coda.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 13: Networks (Social Network Sites)</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>danah boyd, “<a href="http://www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf">Why Youth (Heart) Social Network Sites: The Role of Networked Publics in Teenage Social Life</a>” (2007).</li>
		    <li>danah boyd, “<a href="http://www.danah.org/papers/2011/WhiteFlight.pdf">White Flight in Networked Publics? How Race and Class Shaped American Teen Engagement with MySpace and Facebook</a>” (2011).</li>
		    <li>Nathan Jurgenson, “<a href="http://mdpi.com/1999-5903/4/1/83/pdf">When Atoms Meet Bits: Social Media, the Mobile Web and Augmented Revolution</a>” (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h3>Politics</h3>
<ul>
		<li>
			<h4>June 18: Sovereignty</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Lawrence Lessig, <cite><a href="http://codev2.cc/download+remix/Lessig-Codev2.pdf">Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace, Version 2.0</a></cite> (2006, revised from 1999), prefaces and chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 20: Resistance</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Andy Greenberg, <cite>This Machine Kills Secrets: How WikiLeakers, Cypherpunks, and Hacktivists Aim to Free the World’s Information</cite> (2012), <a href="readings/This%20Machine%20Kills%20Secrets.pdf">prologue and chapters 1, 3, and 4</a>.</li>
		    <li>Gabriella Coleman, “<a href="http://canopycanopycanopy.com/15/our_weirdness_is_free">Our Weirdness Is Free</a>” (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 25: Algorithms</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Tarleton Gillespie, “<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Gillespie_2014_The-Relevance-of-Algorithms.pdf">The Relevance of Algorithms</a>” (2012).</li>
		    <li>Eli Pariser, <cite>The Filter Bubble: How the New Personalized Web Is Changing What We Read and How We Think</cite> (2011), <a href="readings/The%20Filter%20Bubble.pdf">introduction and chapters 1, 4, and 6</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
			<h4>June 27: Networks (Infrastructure)</h4>
	    <ul>
	        <li>Andrew Blum, <cite>Tubes: A Journey to the Center of the Internet</cite> (2012), <a href="readings/Tubes.pdf">prologue and chapters 1, 2, and 7</a>.</li>
	    </ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Cyberculture (STSC/SOCI 260), a course on histories and cultures of the internet offered in summer 2013 at the University of Pennsylvania. The course might also be called “Several Ways of Looking at the Internet,” “Histories and Cultures of the Internet,” or “Introduction to Internet Studies.” In this course, we will explore how people use the internet to develop new conceptions of identity, build virtual communities, and affect political change. Each class we’ll study an aspect of the history and culture of the internet, covering topics such as hackers, virtuality, sovereignty, and algorithms. We’ll read books, articles, and blogs about historical and contemporary cultures of computing, from Spacewar players and phone phreaks in the 1970s to Google, Facebook, World of Warcraft, WikiLeaks, and Anonymous today. In addition, we’ll explore some of these online communities and projects ourselves, and develop our own analyses of them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emergence of Modern Science</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2012/emergence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emergence of Modern Science" /><published>2012-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2012/emergence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2012/emergence/"><![CDATA[In this course, we will explore the lives, ideas, and influence of those who created modern science from the Renaissance to today. We will think about what problems scientific ideas solved, what made them controversial and exciting, and how they were related to contemporary art, religion, and politics. Our focus will be on the spaces in which science was done, the tools and techniques used, and the media through which it was communicated. Topics will range widely, from Newtonian mechanics to atomic weapons, from Darwin to DNA sequencing, and from an eighteenth-century defecating mechanical duck to the first twentieth-century computer game.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this course, we will explore the lives, ideas, and influence of those who created modern science from the Renaissance to today. We will think about what problems scientific ideas solved, what made them controversial and exciting, and how they were related to contemporary art, religion, and politics. Our focus will be on the spaces in which science was done, the tools and techniques used, and the media through which it was communicated. Topics will range widely, from Newtonian mechanics to atomic weapons, from Darwin to DNA sequencing, and from an eighteenth-century defecating mechanical duck to the first twentieth-century computer game.]]></summary></entry></feed>