<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/chemistry.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-09T13:43:57-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/chemistry.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Beckmans at Caltech, 1923–1939</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2025/beckmans/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beckmans at Caltech, 1923–1939" /><published>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2025/beckmans</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2025/beckmans/"><![CDATA[From 1923 to 1939, Arnold Beckman was first a graduate student and then a professor at Caltech. Peter Sachs Collopy, PhD discusses Arnold and Mabel Beckman’s relationships with Caltech and how Caltech changed during this period.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="electronics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From 1923 to 1939, Arnold Beckman was first a graduate student and then a professor at Caltech. Peter Sachs Collopy, PhD discusses Arnold and Mabel Beckman’s relationships with Caltech and how Caltech changed during this period.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art and Science at Caltech: Four Histories</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2024/art-and-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art and Science at Caltech: Four Histories" /><published>2024-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2024/art-and-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2024/art-and-science/"><![CDATA[The *Crossing Over* exhibition, which unfolds across three independent spaces on the Caltech campus, draws on the research of 12 scholars in the visual culture of Caltech science. Their collective work is captured in the exhibit and a companion exhibition catalog that weave together the history of science with historical and contemporary art.

In a discussion, moderated by Caltech archivist Peter Sachs Collopy, four of the contributing scholars discuss the many forms of collaboration between art and science: from drawings of molecules to the architecture of the Caltech campus itself, and in the context of films, from a Frank Capra television special on subatomic particles to how outer space is illustrated by scientists and engineers at JPL and producers in Hollywood.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="art" /><category term="astronomy" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="media" /><category term="physics" /><category term="science" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Crossing Over exhibition, which unfolds across three independent spaces on the Caltech campus, draws on the research of 12 scholars in the visual culture of Caltech science. Their collective work is captured in the exhibit and a companion exhibition catalog that weave together the history of science with historical and contemporary art. In a discussion, moderated by Caltech archivist Peter Sachs Collopy, four of the contributing scholars discuss the many forms of collaboration between art and science: from drawings of molecules to the architecture of the Caltech campus itself, and in the context of films, from a Frank Capra television special on subatomic particles to how outer space is illustrated by scientists and engineers at JPL and producers in Hollywood.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Passing in the Hallway: Art and Technology at Caltech, 1968–1972</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/passing-in-the-hallway/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Passing in the Hallway: Art and Technology at Caltech, 1968–1972" /><published>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/passing-in-the-hallway</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/passing-in-the-hallway/"><![CDATA[In 1969, Caltech converted seven rooms in its defunct Earhart Plant Research Laboratory into an art studio, hosting artists who worked in the media of plastics and computer animation. In the long 1960s, artists and scientists embraced each others’ professional practices, and universities created new centers for art and technology. Artists and scientists did not come to these new programs with the same motivations and expectations. Many artists were interested in synthesizing art with science and engineering, but most scientists and engineers who engaged in art were seeking a break from their technical work rather than a different mode of it, making genuine collaboration the exception rather than the rule.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="art" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="computing" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="media" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="California" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 1969, Caltech converted seven rooms in its defunct Earhart Plant Research Laboratory into an art studio, hosting artists who worked in the media of plastics and computer animation. In the long 1960s, artists and scientists embraced each others’ professional practices, and universities created new centers for art and technology. Artists and scientists did not come to these new programs with the same motivations and expectations. Many artists were interested in synthesizing art with science and engineering, but most scientists and engineers who engaged in art were seeking a break from their technical work rather than a different mode of it, making genuine collaboration the exception rather than the rule.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/crossing-over/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020" /><published>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/crossing-over</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/crossing-over/"><![CDATA[Science is as much a visual practice as a textual or quantitative one. For centuries, scientists have used microscopes, telescopes, painting, illustration, printing, and photography to perceive nature and communicate what they see in it, often in collaboration with artists. In the twentieth century, scientists also came to view creativity as an essential resource and looked to art to foster it.

*Crossing Over* is an interdisciplinary publication that looks at one prominent university—the California Institute of Technology (Caltech) in Pasadena—as a site for scientific and artistic image production. Uncovering the rich pictorial record embedded in its Archives and Special Collections, a team of visual culture scholars examines Caltech through a series of tightly focused case studies. How, the authors ask, have science and engineering institutions like Caltech used scientific representation, art, and architecture to construct themselves and produce discovery and invention? This book reveals new facets of life and work at Caltech that will be illuminating even to those familiar with the school, showcasing views that informed—and were informed by—the vibrant visual culture of Southern California.

This volume was published to accompany [an exhibition](/exhibits/2024/crossing-over) on view at the California Institute of Technology from September 27 to December 15, 2024. It is a [finalist](https://www.collegeart.org/news/2025/11/13/announcing-the-2026-morey-book-award-and-barr-awards-shortlists/) for the College Art Association’s 2026 Alfred H. Barr Jr. Award for Smaller Museums, Libraries, Collections, and Exhibitions.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="art" /><category term="astronomy" /><category term="biology" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="computing" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="geology" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="media" /><category term="physics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="war" /><category term="California" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Science is as much a visual practice as a textual or quantitative one. For centuries, scientists have used microscopes, telescopes, painting, illustration, printing, and photography to perceive nature and communicate what they see in it, often in collaboration with artists. In the twentieth century, scientists also came to view creativity as an essential resource and looked to art to foster it. Crossing Over is an interdisciplinary publication that looks at one prominent university—the California Institute of Technology (Caltech) in Pasadena—as a site for scientific and artistic image production. Uncovering the rich pictorial record embedded in its Archives and Special Collections, a team of visual culture scholars examines Caltech through a series of tightly focused case studies. How, the authors ask, have science and engineering institutions like Caltech used scientific representation, art, and architecture to construct themselves and produce discovery and invention? This book reveals new facets of life and work at Caltech that will be illuminating even to those familiar with the school, showcasing views that informed—and were informed by—the vibrant visual culture of Southern California. This volume was published to accompany an exhibition on view at the California Institute of Technology from September 27 to December 15, 2024. It is a finalist for the College Art Association’s 2026 Alfred H. Barr Jr. Award for Smaller Museums, Libraries, Collections, and Exhibitions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020</title><link href="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2024/crossing-over/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020" /><published>2024-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/exhibits/2024/crossing-over</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2024/crossing-over/"><![CDATA[*Crossing Over* was an expansive public exhibition that wove together the history of science with historical and contemporary art. How, it asked, have scientists and engineers used images and collaborated with artists to discover, invent, and communicate? How have artists been inspired by Caltech science? Spread across six sites at Caltech, the exhibition featured displays of over 200 objects, most drawn from the Caltech Archives and Special Collections, including rare books, paintings, drawings, photographs, scientific instruments, molecular models, and video.

September 27 – December 15, 2024]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="exhibits" /><category term="art" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="science" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="astronomy" /><category term="biology" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="geology" /><category term="physics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="technology" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Crossing Over was an expansive public exhibition that wove together the history of science with historical and contemporary art. How, it asked, have scientists and engineers used images and collaborated with artists to discover, invent, and communicate? How have artists been inspired by Caltech science? Spread across six sites at Caltech, the exhibition featured displays of over 200 objects, most drawn from the Caltech Archives and Special Collections, including rare books, paintings, drawings, photographs, scientific instruments, molecular models, and video. September 27 – December 15, 2024]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Curating Art and Science</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2022/curating/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Curating Art and Science" /><published>2022-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2022/curating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2022/curating/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Curating Art and Science, a course offered in museum studies, history, and cultural studies in fall 2022 at Claremont Graduate University. This course will explore the history of interactions between art, science, and technology, and how to curate exhibitions on the subject. It is partly based on the instructors’ work, as part of the Getty Foundation’s Pacific Standard Time 2024 program on art, science, and LA, to develop a multi-sited, campus-wide exhibition at Caltech on Caltech’s own uses of visual culture over the last century to produce science, to communicate it, and to foster scientific identity and community. Our readings will emphasize the 20th century US, and sometimes specifically Caltech’s own history, but student projects may extend beyond this geographical and chronological context.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will be divided into three modules:</p>

<ol>
	<li><b>Art and Science:</b> During the first part of the semester, we will think about the relationships between art, science, technology, and visual culture more generally, studying foundational texts on scientific illustration, the influence of science on modern and contemporary art, technological art, and the architecture of scientific institutions.</li>
	<li><b>Curating:</b> The second part of the semester takes an in-depth look at the history of exhibitions, both in the science and visual arts realms, and explores the nature and roles of archives and collections as sources for display. We will pay particular attention to contemporary curatorial theory and practice as it has evolved from the 1960s to the present. There will be site visits to the Benton Museum at Pomona College, where we will see an installation by California Light and Space artist Helen Pashgian; the Huntington Library, where we view a site-specific installation by artist Lita Albuquerque and meet with senior curators working on art and science exhibitions; and the Caltech Archives and Special Collections, where we will explore the records kept by scientific institutions. Other guests will join the conversation to deepen our understanding of discourse and standards in the field.</li>
	<li><b>Disciplinary Histories and Student Presentations:</b> During the third part of the semester, we will focus on the histories of visual culture in specific scientific disciplines, as well as art and architecture, often reading case studies from Caltech’s own history. Students will curate, design, and present possible exhibition displays on these topics drawing on the Caltech Archives and other local collections.</li>
</ol>

<p>Throughout the semester, students will investigate a range of visual practices at Caltech and other scientific institutions according to the specific scientific, artistic, and institutional functions they serve. What kinds of information do scientific images convey, and how do we best look at them in their varying contexts? How do we account for the choices scientists and artists make when they represent their work, and what cultural biases or preferences might their images contain? How do scientific images relate to other images in art, technology, and popular culture?</p>

<p>This course does not require any specific background preparation. For those unfamiliar with the academic study of visual culture, additional reading in James Elkins and Erna Fiorentini, <cite>Visual Worlds: Looking, Images, Visual Disciplines</cite> (Oxford University Press, 2020) may be useful for context.</p>

<h3>Student Learning Outcomes</h3>

<p>Upon successful completion of this course, students will be able to:</p>

<ol>
	<li>Understand the complex interactions between art, science, technology, and visual culture in the 20th and early 21st centuries, especially as they relate to the California Institute of Technology, other American science institutions, and Southern California.</li>
	<li>Navigate art and science discourses in the humanities.</li>
	<li>Reflect on and engage critically with trends and issues in contemporary curatorial practice.</li>
	<li>Collaborate with project partners.</li>
	<li>Strengthen research, writing, and presentation skills, communicating in a variety of formats and for diverse audiences.</li>
	<li>Create compelling exhibitions with an understanding of different spaces and their design, as well as the selection, care, and management of display objects.</li>
	<li>Know artists, scholars, curators, and design professionals working in the field.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Assignments</h3>

<ol>
	<li><b>Exhibition review</b> (500 words) of a local exhibition of your choice which engages with both art and science. Specific guidelines for this review will be posted online and discussed in class. Reviews are due electronically before class on October 24, 2022.</li>
	<li><b>Exhibition proposal</b> of a concept, items, didactic text, and layout for a small display on an art/science theme either chosen from a list provided by the course instructors or proposed by the student. Elements of the proposal will include a short introductory text (500 words), a checklist of 15–30 display items, a sample wall text (250 words) and didactic exhibition label (100 words), and space selection and layout/fabrication ideas. You may work independently or collaborate with one or more partners. In addition to handing in proposal materials, each student will present on their proposal during the third portion of the semester. Your presentation will be assessed based on the comprehensiveness and originality of your ideas; their viability in a real-life gallery, museum, or library setting; and your creative communication skills. Specific guidelines for a successful exhibition proposal will be posted online and discussed in class. Proposals are due on your assigned presentation day, between November 7 and December 12.</li>
	<li><b>Curatorial essay</b> (15–20 pages, no more than 5000 words) providing historical, cultural, aesthetic, or other scholarly analysis of your proposal exhibition, or, with permission of the instructors, of another topic. Specific guidelines for the creation of a curatorial essay will be posted online and discussed in class. Curatorial essays are due electronically on December 16.</li>
</ol>

<p>Your grade for the course will be based 20% on the exhibition review, 30% each on the exhibition proposal and curatorial essay, and 20% on your engaged and insightful participation in class.</p>

<p>We’ll discuss readings during every class, so please read everything assigned before the class meeting it’s listed under. Please submit assignments by email to both instructors.</p>

<h3>Schedule of Class Topics and Readings</h3>

<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>August 29: Introduction</h5>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4>Art and Science</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>September 12: Scientific Images</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>James Elkins, <cite><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctv3s8n8p">The Domain of Images</a></cite> (Cornell University Press, 1999), 3–51.</li>
			<li>Horst Bredekamp, Vera Dünkel, and Birgit Schneider, eds., <cite>The Technical Image: A History of Styles in Scientific Imagery</cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2015), 1–45.</li>
			<li>Bruno Latour, “<a href="http://www.bruno-latour.fr/sites/default/files/21-DRAWING-THINGS-TOGETHER-GB.pdf">Visualization and Cognition: Drawing Things Together</a>,” <cite>Knowledge and Society</cite> 6 (1986): 1–40.</li>
			<li>Lorraine Daston and Peter Galison, <cite><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctv1c9hq4d">Objectivity</a></cite> (Zone, 2007), 9–53.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>September 19: Science in Art</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>James Elkins and Erna Fiorentini, <cite>Visual Worlds: Looking, Images, Visual Disciplines</cite> (Oxford University Press, 2020), 339–362.</li>
			<li>Chiara Ambrosio, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03080188.2016.1223586">Cubism and the Fourth Dimension</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 41 (2016): 202–221.</li>
			<li>Linda Dalrymple Henderson, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/776982">X Rays and the Quest for Invisible Reality in the Art of Kupka, Duchamp, and the Cubists</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 47 (1988): 323–340.</li>
			<li>Vanja V. Malloy, “From Macrocosm to Microcosm: Examining the Role of Modern Science in American Art,” in <cite>Dimensionism: Modern Art in the Age of Einstein</cite>, ed. Vanja V. Malloy (Mead Art Museum, Amherst College and MIT Press, 2018), 71–97.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>September 26: The Architecture of Science</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Sophie Forgan, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0039-3681(89)90017-4">The Architecture of Science and the Idea of a University</a>,” <cite>Studies in History and Philosophy of Science</cite> 20 (1989): 405–434.</li>
			<li>Robert E. Kohler, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/007327530204000405">Labscapes: Naturalizing the Lab</a>,” <cite>History of Science</cite> 40 (2002): 473–501.</li>
			<li>Thomas F. Gieryn, “Two Faces on Science: Building Identities for Molecular Biology and Biotechnology,” in <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb08330.0001.001">The Architecture of Science</a></cite>, ed. Peter Galison and Emily Thompson (MIT Press, 1999), 423–455.</li>
			<li>Thomas F. Gieryn, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/595773">Laboratory Design for Post-Fordist Science</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 99 (2008): 796–802.</li>
			<li>Peter Galison and Caroline A. Jones, “Factory, Laboratory, Studio: Dispersing Sites of Production,” in Galison and Thompson, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb08330.0001.001">Architecture of Science</a></cite>, 497–540.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 3: Art and Technology</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Fred Turner, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1470412907087201">Romantic Automatism: Art, Technology, and Collaborative Labor in Cold War America</a>,” <cite>Journal of Visual Culture</cite> 7 (2008): 5–26.</li>
			<li>Anne Collins Goodyear, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20206559">From Technophilia to Technophobia: The Impact of the Vietnam War on the Reception of ‘Art and Technology,’</a>” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 41, no. 2 (2008): 169–173.</li>
			<li>Matthew Wisnioski, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/con.2013.0006">Why MIT Institutionalized the Avant-Garde: Negotiating Aesthetic Virtue in the Postwar Defense Institute</a>,” <cite>Configurations</cite> 21 (2013): 85–116.</li>
			<li>W. Patrick McCray, “Fallout and Spinoff: Commercializing the Art-Technology Nexus,” in <cite>Hybrid Practices: Art in Collaboration with Science and Technology in the Long 1960s</cite>, ed. David Cateforis, Steven Duval, and Shepherd Steiner (University of California Press, 2019), 61–77.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4>Curating</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>October 10: Showing Is Telling: Contemporary Curatorial Practice</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: <a href="https://www.timdurfee.com/">Tim Durfee</a>, Principal of Tim Durfee Studio and Professor of Media Design Practices, Art Center College of Design</i></li>
			<li>Robert Storr, “Show and Tell,” in <cite>What Makes a Great Exhibition?</cite> ed. Paula Marincola (Reaktion, 2006), 14–31.</li>
			<li>Kate Fowle, “Who Cares? Understanding the Role of the Curator Today,” in <cite>Cautionary Tales: Critical Curating</cite>, ed. Steven Rand and Heather Kouris (apexart, 2007).</li>
			<li>Hans Ulrich Obrist, <cite>Ways of Curating</cite> (Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2014), 14–16, 22–35.</li>
			<li>Jens Hofmann and Maria Lind, “<a href="https://www.moussemagazine.it/magazine/jens-hoffmann-maria-lind-2011/">To Show or Not to Show</a>,” <cite>Mousse Magazine</cite>, no. 31 (November 2011).</li>
			<li>Adrian George, <cite>The Curator’s Handbook: Museums, Commercial Galleries, Independent Spaces</cite> (Thames and Hudson, 2015), 152–206.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 17: Archives and Collections</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: <a href="http://www.elinoharaslavick.com/">elin o’Hara slavick</a>, artist and curator</i></li>
			<li>Elizabeth Yale, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43956377">The History of Archives: The State of the Discipline</a>,” <cite>Book History</cite> 18 (2015): 332–359.</li>
			<li>Lorraine Daston, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/667826">The Sciences of the Archive</a>,” <cite>Osiris</cite> 27 (2012): 156–187.</li>
			<li>Allan Sekula, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/778312">The Body and the Archive</a>,” <cite>October</cite>, no. 39 (Winter 1986): 3–64.</li>
			<li>Jennifer Tucker, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/501104">The Historian, the Picture, and the Archive</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 97 (2006): 111–120.</li>
			<li>George, <cite>Curator’s Handbook, 30–48 and 56–87.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 24: Exhibiting Art, Exhibiting Science</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: Dan Lewis, Dibner Senior Curator of the History of Science and Technology, Huntington Library</i></li>
			<li>Sharon Macdonald, “Exhibitions of Power and Powers of Exhibitions: An Introduction to the Politics of Display,” in <cite>The Politics of Display: Museums, Science, and Culture</cite>, ed. Sharon Macdonald (Routledge, 1998), 1–24.</li>
			<li>Ivan Karp and Steven D. Lavine, eds., <cite>Exhibiting Cultures: The Poetics and Politics of Museum Display</cite> (Smithsonian Institution Press, 1991), 1–56.</li>
			<li>Tony Bennet, “The Exhibitionary Complex,” in <cite>Thinking About Exhibitions</cite>, ed. Reesa Greenberg, Bruce W. Fergusson, and Sandy Nairne (Routledge, 1996), 81–112.</li>
			<li>Terry Smith, <cite>Thinking Contemporary Curating</cite> (Independent Curators International, 2012), 57–100.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>October 31: From White Cube to Black Box: Contemporary Curatorial Thought</h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Guest: Rebecca McGrew, Senior Curator, Benton Museum of Art, Pomona College</i></li>
			<li>Brian O’Doherty, “<a href="https://www.artforum.com/print/197603/inside-the-white-cube-notes-on-the-gallery-space-part-i-38508">Inside the White Cube: Notes on the Gallery Space, Part I</a>,” <cite>Artforum</cite>, March 1976.</li>
			<li>Okwui Enwezor, “The Black Box,” in <cite>Documenta 11_Platform 5: Exhibition, Catalogue</cite> (Hatje Cantz, 2002).</li>
			<li>Carolee Thea, “Okwui Enwezor,” in <cite>On Curating: Interviews with Ten International Curators</cite> (Distributed Art Publishers, 2009), 43–53.</li>
			<li>Paul O’Neill, <cite>The Culture of Curating and the Curating of Culture(s)</cite> (MIT Press, 2016), 9–49.</li>
			<li>Smith, <cite>Thinking Contemporary Curating</cite>, 178–246.</li>
			<li>Irit Rogoff, “<a href="https://xenopraxis.net/readings/rogoff_smuggling.pdf">‘Smuggling’: An Embodied Criticality</a>,” August 2006.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4>Disciplinary Histories and Student Presentations</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>November 7: Astronomy and Planetary Science</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Alex Soojung-Kim Pang, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4027716">‘Stars Should Henceforth Register Themselves’: Astrophotography at the Early Lick Observatory</a>,” <cite>British Journal for the History of Science</cite> 30 (1997): 177–205.</li>
			<li>Omar W. Nasim, “<a href="https://www.mprl-series.mpg.de/studies/12/10/index.html">Handling the Heavens: Things and the Photo-Objects of Astronomy</a>,” in <cite>Photo-Objects: On the Materiality of Photographs and Photo Archives in the Humanities and Sciences</cite>, ed. Julia Bärnighausen, Costanza Caraffa, Stefanie Klamm, Franka Schneider, and Petra Wodtke (Max-Planck-Gesellschaft zur Förderung der Wissenschaften, 2019), 161–175.</li>
			<li>Elizabeth A. Kessler, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2021.0198">Technology’s Palette: Voyager’s Eyes and the Hyperchromatic Enhancement of Jupiter and Saturn</a>,” <cite>Technology and Culture</cite> 62 (2021): 1087–1118.</li>
			<li>Janet Vertesi, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/9780262525381.003.0002"><i>Drawing As</i>: Distinctions and Disambiguation in Digital Images of Mars</a>,” in <cite>Representation in Scientific Practice Revisited</cite>, ed. Catelijne Coopmans, Janet Vertesi, Michael Lynch, and Steve Woolgar (MIT Press, 2014), 15–36.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>November 14: Biology</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Nick Hopwood, “<a href="https://publicdomainreview.org/essay/copying-pictures-evidencing-evolution">Copying Pictures, Evidencing Evolution</a>,” <cite>Public Domain Review</cite>, May 18, 2016.</li>
			<li>Maura C. Flannery, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1576571">Images of the Cell in Twentieth-Century Art and Science</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 31 (1998): 195–204.</li>
			<li>Christopher Kelty and Hannah Landecker, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/1526381042464536">A Theory of Animation: Cells, L-Systems, and Film</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite>, no. 17 (2004): 31–63.</li>
			<li>Soraya de Chadarevian, “Models and the Making of Molecular Biology,” in <cite>Models: The Third Dimension of Science</cite>, ed. Soraya de Chadarevian and Nick Hopwood (Stanford University Press, 2004), 339–368.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>November 21: Chemistry</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Christoph Meinel, “Molecules and Croquet Balls,” in de Chadarevian and Hopwood, <cite>Models</cite>, 242–275.</li>
			<li>Alberto Cambrosio, Daniel Jacobi, and Peter Keating, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/rep.2005.89.1.94">Arguing with Images: Pauling’s Theory of Antibody Formation</a>,” <cite>Representations</cite> 89, (2005): 94–130.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>November 28: Art and Architecture</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Stefanos Polyzoides, “<a href="https://www.classicist.org/pdf/classicist15/#page=10">Bertram Goodhue and the Architecture of Caltech, 1915 to 1939</a>,” <cite>Classicist</cite>, no. 15 (2018): 8–19.</li>
			<li>Zabet Patterson, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/grey.2009.1.36.36">From the Gun Controller to the Mandala: The Cybernetic Cinema of John and James Whitney</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite>, no. 36 (2009): 36–57.</li>
			<li>Stephen Nowlin, “<a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/670950">@Caltech: Art, Science and Technology, 1969–1971</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 50 (2017): 443–447.</li>
			<li>Lisa Lynch, “‘Out-liers,’ ‘Insiders,’ and Practical Harvest: Art as Technology Transfer in a Research Environment,” <cite>Research in Science and Technology Studies</cite> 13 (2002): 239–265.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>December 5: Physics</h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Peter Galison and Alexi Assmus, “Artificial Clouds, Real Particles,” in <cite>The Uses of Experiment: Studies in the Natural Sciences</cite>, ed. David Gooding, Trevor Pinch, and Simon Schaffer (Cambridge University Press, 1989), 225–274.</li>
			<li>David Kaiser, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2902893">Stick Figure Realism: Conventions, Reification, and the Persistence of Feynman Diagrams, 1948–1964</a>,” <cite>Representations</cite> 70 (2000): 49–86.</li>
			<li>James Elkins, <cite>Six Stories from the End of Representation: Images in Painting, Photography, Astronomy, Microscopy, Particle Physics, and Quantum Mechanics, 1980–2000</cite> (Stanford University Press, 2008), 156–223.</li>
			<li>Colleen O’Reilly, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/44011808">Pedagogical Interventions: The Physics Photographs of Berenice Abbott</a>,” <cite>RACAR: revue d'art canadienne / Canadian Art Review</cite> 41, no. 2 (2016): 77–90.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>December 12: Conclusion</h5>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="biology" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="physics" /><category term="astronomy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Curating Art and Science, a course offered in museum studies, history, and cultural studies in fall 2022 at Claremont Graduate University. This course will explore the history of interactions between art, science, and technology, and how to curate exhibitions on the subject. It is partly based on the instructors’ work, as part of the Getty Foundation’s Pacific Standard Time 2024 program on art, science, and LA, to develop a multi-sited, campus-wide exhibition at Caltech on Caltech’s own uses of visual culture over the last century to produce science, to communicate it, and to foster scientific identity and community. Our readings will emphasize the 20th century US, and sometimes specifically Caltech’s own history, but student projects may extend beyond this geographical and chronological context.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chemistry Comes to Caltech</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/chemistry-comes-to-caltech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chemistry Comes to Caltech" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/chemistry-comes-to-caltech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/chemistry-comes-to-caltech/"><![CDATA[As we mentioned in our presentations two weeks ago, the Throop of the 1910s and the Caltech of the 1920s were deeply shaped by astrophysicist George Ellery Hale’s vision for the institution. Hale came to Pasadena to found and direct Mount Wilson Observatory, but had just as much influence as a trustee of the local college.

Hale’s own education had been at MIT, which became a model both for what Throop should be and for what it should not. Among his instructors in 1887 was the chemist Arthur Amos Noyes, who was only two years older and had just earned his BS and MS, also from MIT. The two men became friends. At the end of the year, Noyes—like many young American scientists of his time—travelled to Germany to study for his PhD. He conducted research on the solubility of salts in the laboratory of physical chemist Wilhelm Ostwald, and earned his PhD from the University of Leipzig in 1890, the same year Hale earned his BS.

Noyes returned to MIT and taught organic, analytical, and physical chemistry, publishing a textbook on each. “A characteristic of *Chemical Principles* was the use of problems so phrased as to lead the student to derive the basic equations,” wrote one of Noyes’ students’ students, Linus Pauling. His “books have been described as revolutionizing the teaching of analytical chemistry and physical chemistry in America.” Noyes also founded the *Review of American Chemical Research*, which became *Chemical Abstracts*. In 1904, he became the youngest president yet of the American Chemical Society.

Noyes’ research, meanwhile, concerned the chemical properties of rare elements and incorporating them into chemical analysis. In 1903, Noyes founded the Research Laboratory of Physical Chemistry at MIT, which trained the first MIT students to receive PhDs. Even though he had spent his entire career there, Noyes often found himself at odds with his colleagues, particularly about pedagogy. Engineers should study physics, chemistry, and mathematics, he argued, telling a group of freshmen that without science “you would be only rule-of-thumb engineers, who could imitate, but not initiate.” Noyes and Hale also agreed that engineers should study the arts and humanities.

From 1907 to 1909, Noyes served as acting president of MIT. He left the position frustrated, and Hale began wooing him to come to Throop and build a new research institute together. “If you chose,” wrote Hale, “you would be given a free hand to develop the Engineering School [or] to devote yourself entirely to chemical research, simply giving us the privilege of discussing with you the problems encountered in working out the educational scheme.”

At first, Noyes declined, but in 1913 Hale sweetened the offer. If Noyes would only visit and teach for two months, wrote Hale, Throop would provide him a new laboratory building. Noyes agreed, and all that remained for Throop was to raise funds to build the laboratory. “I don’t know where this building is coming from,” Hale confessed in a letter to his wife.

Trustee Charles Warner Gates, who had amassed his fortune in the Arkansas lumber industry before retiring to South Pasadena, pledged $25,000 toward the project. He soon recruited his brother and business partner Peter Goddard Gates to contribute as well. Arthur Fleming, who had donated more to Throop than anyone else, promised another $20,000 for equipment and salaries, but only on the condition that Noyes agree to resettle permanently in Pasadena. College president James A.B. Scherer, who until now had left negotiations to Hale, wired Noyes to urge him to accept the offer, calling it “Throop’s superlative opportunity.”

Noyes, though, made a counteroffer. He would split his time between Throop and MIT for two years as an experiment. In 1915, the parties agreed on this arrangement. Noyes, a lifelong bachelor, would travel across the country alone by train several times over the next few years. On one visit to Throop, he addressed the school’s 91 students on his belief that science was necessary for engineering: “Industrial research is not the main research opportunity of educational institutions,” he told them. “The main field for education institutions is research in pure science itself—a study of fundamental principles and phenomena, without immediate reference to practical application.… Scientific investigation is the spring that feeds the stream of technical progress, and if the spring dries up the stream is sure to disappear.” Given the option of leaving the university, Noyes became still more assertive about his opinions at MIT as well; “I have become much more warlike,” he wrote to Hale.

As we heard from Loma two weeks ago, Throop’s leaders selected Los Angeles architect Elmer Grey to design the Gates Laboratory of Chemistry. They also asked Bertram Goodhue, who they had hired to develop a campus plan for Throop, to consult, and he designed a facade in the Spanish Colonial Revival style for which he was known.

On March 10, 1916, three years after it was first proposed, construction of the two-story, reinforced-concrete building began. When completed a year later, it contained, floor-by-floor, supply rooms and dedicated laboratories for technical analysis, chemical engineering, industrial chemistry, and photochemistry in the basement. The first floor contained a lecture hall, an additional supply room, and laboratories for organic and inorganic chemistry. The second floor contained a library, a shop, and additional laboratories for physical chemistry, analytical chemistry, and research. Here are some of the laboratories. “I remember very specially the aromatic smell of the Gates Laboratory,” Caltech chemist John Roberts later recalled of touring the building as a teenager. “They used to run chemistry demonstrations in the big lab, and those were absolutely fascinating. It was a marvelous thing for a young person to be exposed to that.” Noyes’ himself sometimes preferred not to leave the laboratory, and kept a cot and food in his office.

The building’s exterior featured carved stone and wrought-iron trim. Here you can see Gates in the foreground with Pasadena Hall—soon renamed Throop Hall—beyond it, and the Old Dorm beyond that. The road to upper right is California Boulevard; the one the lower left is the part of San Pasqual since replaced by a path through campus.

Noyes began spending a few months a year at Throop, and in 1919 he left MIT and made Pasadena his fulltime home. In Boston, Noyes was an avid sailor and named his yacht Research. In Pasadena, he bought a large touring car, a Cadillac, and invited new graduate students on camping trips in the desert.

During conversations about changing Throop’s name in 1919, Noyes voiced a strong opinion: “Even more vital” than new buildings, he wrote to Scherer, “both on the financial and on the educational and research side, would be the change of its name to the California Institute of… I do not care very much what word or words are put in place of the dots. I am still inclined to think that Science and Engineering is the best. The main thing is to remove the name Throop and to get attached to the Institution the name of the great state of California.” Two months later, the trustees followed Noyes’ advice, more or less, adopting the name California Institute of Technology.

During that first visit as faculty, Noyes brought along his former student Charles Lalor Burdick from MIT. Burdick had also studied in Germany, where he had travelled in July 1914, the month World War I began, on the last regular German ship to sail from New York to Hamburg. As he completed his PhD, Burdick worked alongside “then two young, comparatively unknowns by the names of [Otto] Hahn and [Lise] Meitner,” who later discovered nuclear fission. He then conducted postdoctoral research with Fritz Haber, famous for his work on the Haber-Bosch process for nitrogen fixation in order to synthesize ammonia, which made possible the production of synthetic fertilizer and explosives. Haber would become equally famous for the poison gas he developed during World War I; Burdick seems to have worked on more basic research in physical chemistry, but was part of Haber’s lab during the same period of time. Burdick also attended lectures by physicists Max Planck and Albert Einstein.

Then, in early 1916, at the advice of Noyes, Burdick moved on London to work with William Henry Bragg. “Noyes expressed his strong belief,” wrote Burdick, “in the importance of x-ray atomic structure analysis for the future of theoretical chemistry, and his wish to get something of the kind started at MIT. It was not so simple for an impecunious, young, PhD of American neutrality without connections to get from Berlin to London during the period of the Zeppelin raids and unrestricted submarine warfare, but… it was accomplished.”

Bragg and his son Lawrence had founded the field of x-ray crystallography, determining the structures of crystals by observing how they diffract x-rays. “An interesting presentation could be made,” wrote Burdick, “of the primitiveness of the equipment then available, the old-fashioned induction coil with Leyden-jar containers and a mercury interruptor, the gas-filled x-ray tubes of unpredictable and uncertain output and ‘hardness,’ and gold-leaf electroscopes with the strangest static aberrations when it came to measuring ionization intensities.” Burdick spent six months in London, then returned to MIT, where Noyes asked him to build an improved x-ray spectrometer. A few months later, when Noyes brought Burdick to Throop, Burdick, Throop chemist James H. Ellis, and Pasadena instrument maker Fred Hensen built another spectrometer. “The things which made the original Caltech spectrometer probably the best of its day,” wrote Burdick, “were its high-power output and relative constancy of measured electrical energy to the tube. This gave possibilities for narrower spectrometer slits, precise angle measurement, sharp reflection peaks, and better measurement of relative reflection intensities of the spectral orders than had probably ever been made before.”

The US entered World War I in April 1917, redirecting research towards the war effort. Hale had recently founded the National Research Council for precisely this purpose, and Noyes served as chairman of both the Council itself and its Sub-Committee on Nitrates and Ammonia, among many other administrative appointments. Now on the other side of the war from his advisor Haber, Burdick worked on a problem Haber had tackled earlier, nitrogen fixation, for the US Ordnance Reserve.

After the war, Throop chemists returned to x-ray crystallography, which dominated chemistry research here for several years. In 1920, the newly-renamed Caltech awarded its first PhD to a student of Noyes, Roscoe Dickinson, for using x-ray crystallography to determine the structures of wulfenite, scheelite, sodium chlorate, and sodium bromate. “By the end of 1922,” wrote Linus Pauling later, “twenty papers had been published by members of the Division [of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering], of which fifteen were on the determination of the structure of crystals.”

Pauling himself arrived as a graduate student that fall, and began studying crystal structures under the direction of Noyes and Dickinson, who remained at Caltech as a professor and became his advisor. Here you can see his glass plate x-ray diffraction photograph of nickel chlorostannate hexahydrate crystal, one of several in the Caltech Archives. And the accompanying envelope with Pauling’s notes, and the publication resulting from this research. Pauling earned his PhD for x-ray crystallography work in 1925, then spent two years in Europe studying quantum physics with scientists including Neils Bohr and Erwin Schrödinger. In 1927, he returned to Caltech as a professor and began researching the quantum mechanics of the chemical bond, work for which he won the Nobel Prize in 1954.

With additional funding from Charles and Peter Gates, Caltech expanded Gates Laboratory in 1927. Bertram Goodhue had passed away in 1924, but his associates designed an annex that originally contained a new library and additional laboratories, offices, and classrooms. The Gates Annex incorporated Byzantine, Native American, Mayan, and Spanish influences.

Gates Laboratory of Chemistry remained a hub of research and teaching until the 1971 San Fernando earthquake left it so badly damaged that all activities in the building had to be relocated. After the earthquake, Gates was slated for demolition. Instead, the Institute elected to save the laboratory for future renovation. Its interior was gutted and the walls reinforced with structural steel and gunite. The building remained empty for nearly a decade, awaiting further repair.

Then, in 1980, funding from the Ralph M. Parsons and James Irvine foundations made possible the renovations necessary to convert the former laboratory into an administrative center. The building reopened in 1983. A year later, the Los Angeles Conservancy awarded the project its Preservation Award for “leadership in restoration and adaptive reuse of the Parsons-Gates Hall of Administration.”]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As we mentioned in our presentations two weeks ago, the Throop of the 1910s and the Caltech of the 1920s were deeply shaped by astrophysicist George Ellery Hale’s vision for the institution. Hale came to Pasadena to found and direct Mount Wilson Observatory, but had just as much influence as a trustee of the local college. Hale’s own education had been at MIT, which became a model both for what Throop should be and for what it should not. Among his instructors in 1887 was the chemist Arthur Amos Noyes, who was only two years older and had just earned his BS and MS, also from MIT. The two men became friends. At the end of the year, Noyes—like many young American scientists of his time—travelled to Germany to study for his PhD. He conducted research on the solubility of salts in the laboratory of physical chemist Wilhelm Ostwald, and earned his PhD from the University of Leipzig in 1890, the same year Hale earned his BS. Noyes returned to MIT and taught organic, analytical, and physical chemistry, publishing a textbook on each. “A characteristic of Chemical Principles was the use of problems so phrased as to lead the student to derive the basic equations,” wrote one of Noyes’ students’ students, Linus Pauling. His “books have been described as revolutionizing the teaching of analytical chemistry and physical chemistry in America.” Noyes also founded the Review of American Chemical Research, which became Chemical Abstracts. In 1904, he became the youngest president yet of the American Chemical Society. Noyes’ research, meanwhile, concerned the chemical properties of rare elements and incorporating them into chemical analysis. In 1903, Noyes founded the Research Laboratory of Physical Chemistry at MIT, which trained the first MIT students to receive PhDs. Even though he had spent his entire career there, Noyes often found himself at odds with his colleagues, particularly about pedagogy. Engineers should study physics, chemistry, and mathematics, he argued, telling a group of freshmen that without science “you would be only rule-of-thumb engineers, who could imitate, but not initiate.” Noyes and Hale also agreed that engineers should study the arts and humanities. From 1907 to 1909, Noyes served as acting president of MIT. He left the position frustrated, and Hale began wooing him to come to Throop and build a new research institute together. “If you chose,” wrote Hale, “you would be given a free hand to develop the Engineering School [or] to devote yourself entirely to chemical research, simply giving us the privilege of discussing with you the problems encountered in working out the educational scheme.” At first, Noyes declined, but in 1913 Hale sweetened the offer. If Noyes would only visit and teach for two months, wrote Hale, Throop would provide him a new laboratory building. Noyes agreed, and all that remained for Throop was to raise funds to build the laboratory. “I don’t know where this building is coming from,” Hale confessed in a letter to his wife. Trustee Charles Warner Gates, who had amassed his fortune in the Arkansas lumber industry before retiring to South Pasadena, pledged $25,000 toward the project. He soon recruited his brother and business partner Peter Goddard Gates to contribute as well. Arthur Fleming, who had donated more to Throop than anyone else, promised another $20,000 for equipment and salaries, but only on the condition that Noyes agree to resettle permanently in Pasadena. College president James A.B. Scherer, who until now had left negotiations to Hale, wired Noyes to urge him to accept the offer, calling it “Throop’s superlative opportunity.” Noyes, though, made a counteroffer. He would split his time between Throop and MIT for two years as an experiment. In 1915, the parties agreed on this arrangement. Noyes, a lifelong bachelor, would travel across the country alone by train several times over the next few years. On one visit to Throop, he addressed the school’s 91 students on his belief that science was necessary for engineering: “Industrial research is not the main research opportunity of educational institutions,” he told them. “The main field for education institutions is research in pure science itself—a study of fundamental principles and phenomena, without immediate reference to practical application.… Scientific investigation is the spring that feeds the stream of technical progress, and if the spring dries up the stream is sure to disappear.” Given the option of leaving the university, Noyes became still more assertive about his opinions at MIT as well; “I have become much more warlike,” he wrote to Hale. As we heard from Loma two weeks ago, Throop’s leaders selected Los Angeles architect Elmer Grey to design the Gates Laboratory of Chemistry. They also asked Bertram Goodhue, who they had hired to develop a campus plan for Throop, to consult, and he designed a facade in the Spanish Colonial Revival style for which he was known. On March 10, 1916, three years after it was first proposed, construction of the two-story, reinforced-concrete building began. When completed a year later, it contained, floor-by-floor, supply rooms and dedicated laboratories for technical analysis, chemical engineering, industrial chemistry, and photochemistry in the basement. The first floor contained a lecture hall, an additional supply room, and laboratories for organic and inorganic chemistry. The second floor contained a library, a shop, and additional laboratories for physical chemistry, analytical chemistry, and research. Here are some of the laboratories. “I remember very specially the aromatic smell of the Gates Laboratory,” Caltech chemist John Roberts later recalled of touring the building as a teenager. “They used to run chemistry demonstrations in the big lab, and those were absolutely fascinating. It was a marvelous thing for a young person to be exposed to that.” Noyes’ himself sometimes preferred not to leave the laboratory, and kept a cot and food in his office. The building’s exterior featured carved stone and wrought-iron trim. Here you can see Gates in the foreground with Pasadena Hall—soon renamed Throop Hall—beyond it, and the Old Dorm beyond that. The road to upper right is California Boulevard; the one the lower left is the part of San Pasqual since replaced by a path through campus. Noyes began spending a few months a year at Throop, and in 1919 he left MIT and made Pasadena his fulltime home. In Boston, Noyes was an avid sailor and named his yacht Research. In Pasadena, he bought a large touring car, a Cadillac, and invited new graduate students on camping trips in the desert. During conversations about changing Throop’s name in 1919, Noyes voiced a strong opinion: “Even more vital” than new buildings, he wrote to Scherer, “both on the financial and on the educational and research side, would be the change of its name to the California Institute of… I do not care very much what word or words are put in place of the dots. I am still inclined to think that Science and Engineering is the best. The main thing is to remove the name Throop and to get attached to the Institution the name of the great state of California.” Two months later, the trustees followed Noyes’ advice, more or less, adopting the name California Institute of Technology. During that first visit as faculty, Noyes brought along his former student Charles Lalor Burdick from MIT. Burdick had also studied in Germany, where he had travelled in July 1914, the month World War I began, on the last regular German ship to sail from New York to Hamburg. As he completed his PhD, Burdick worked alongside “then two young, comparatively unknowns by the names of [Otto] Hahn and [Lise] Meitner,” who later discovered nuclear fission. He then conducted postdoctoral research with Fritz Haber, famous for his work on the Haber-Bosch process for nitrogen fixation in order to synthesize ammonia, which made possible the production of synthetic fertilizer and explosives. Haber would become equally famous for the poison gas he developed during World War I; Burdick seems to have worked on more basic research in physical chemistry, but was part of Haber’s lab during the same period of time. Burdick also attended lectures by physicists Max Planck and Albert Einstein. Then, in early 1916, at the advice of Noyes, Burdick moved on London to work with William Henry Bragg. “Noyes expressed his strong belief,” wrote Burdick, “in the importance of x-ray atomic structure analysis for the future of theoretical chemistry, and his wish to get something of the kind started at MIT. It was not so simple for an impecunious, young, PhD of American neutrality without connections to get from Berlin to London during the period of the Zeppelin raids and unrestricted submarine warfare, but… it was accomplished.” Bragg and his son Lawrence had founded the field of x-ray crystallography, determining the structures of crystals by observing how they diffract x-rays. “An interesting presentation could be made,” wrote Burdick, “of the primitiveness of the equipment then available, the old-fashioned induction coil with Leyden-jar containers and a mercury interruptor, the gas-filled x-ray tubes of unpredictable and uncertain output and ‘hardness,’ and gold-leaf electroscopes with the strangest static aberrations when it came to measuring ionization intensities.” Burdick spent six months in London, then returned to MIT, where Noyes asked him to build an improved x-ray spectrometer. A few months later, when Noyes brought Burdick to Throop, Burdick, Throop chemist James H. Ellis, and Pasadena instrument maker Fred Hensen built another spectrometer. “The things which made the original Caltech spectrometer probably the best of its day,” wrote Burdick, “were its high-power output and relative constancy of measured electrical energy to the tube. This gave possibilities for narrower spectrometer slits, precise angle measurement, sharp reflection peaks, and better measurement of relative reflection intensities of the spectral orders than had probably ever been made before.” The US entered World War I in April 1917, redirecting research towards the war effort. Hale had recently founded the National Research Council for precisely this purpose, and Noyes served as chairman of both the Council itself and its Sub-Committee on Nitrates and Ammonia, among many other administrative appointments. Now on the other side of the war from his advisor Haber, Burdick worked on a problem Haber had tackled earlier, nitrogen fixation, for the US Ordnance Reserve. After the war, Throop chemists returned to x-ray crystallography, which dominated chemistry research here for several years. In 1920, the newly-renamed Caltech awarded its first PhD to a student of Noyes, Roscoe Dickinson, for using x-ray crystallography to determine the structures of wulfenite, scheelite, sodium chlorate, and sodium bromate. “By the end of 1922,” wrote Linus Pauling later, “twenty papers had been published by members of the Division [of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering], of which fifteen were on the determination of the structure of crystals.” Pauling himself arrived as a graduate student that fall, and began studying crystal structures under the direction of Noyes and Dickinson, who remained at Caltech as a professor and became his advisor. Here you can see his glass plate x-ray diffraction photograph of nickel chlorostannate hexahydrate crystal, one of several in the Caltech Archives. And the accompanying envelope with Pauling’s notes, and the publication resulting from this research. Pauling earned his PhD for x-ray crystallography work in 1925, then spent two years in Europe studying quantum physics with scientists including Neils Bohr and Erwin Schrödinger. In 1927, he returned to Caltech as a professor and began researching the quantum mechanics of the chemical bond, work for which he won the Nobel Prize in 1954. With additional funding from Charles and Peter Gates, Caltech expanded Gates Laboratory in 1927. Bertram Goodhue had passed away in 1924, but his associates designed an annex that originally contained a new library and additional laboratories, offices, and classrooms. The Gates Annex incorporated Byzantine, Native American, Mayan, and Spanish influences. Gates Laboratory of Chemistry remained a hub of research and teaching until the 1971 San Fernando earthquake left it so badly damaged that all activities in the building had to be relocated. After the earthquake, Gates was slated for demolition. Instead, the Institute elected to save the laboratory for future renovation. Its interior was gutted and the walls reinforced with structural steel and gunite. The building remained empty for nearly a decade, awaiting further repair. Then, in 1980, funding from the Ralph M. Parsons and James Irvine foundations made possible the renovations necessary to convert the former laboratory into an administrative center. The building reopened in 1983. A year later, the Los Angeles Conservancy awarded the project its Preservation Award for “leadership in restoration and adaptive reuse of the Parsons-Gates Hall of Administration.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Becoming Caltech, 1910–1930: Presentations from the Archives</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/becoming-caltech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Becoming Caltech, 1910–1930: Presentations from the Archives" /><published>2020-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/becoming-caltech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/becoming-caltech/"><![CDATA[A century ago, a small institution called Throop Polytechnic Institute dramatically reinvented itself, transforming from a manual arts academy to an engineering school, then expanding into a research institute. In 1920, it became the California Institute of Technology. In summer 2020, Caltech archivists gave a series of livestreamed presentations on the science, engineering, architecture, and community life of early Caltech.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="geology" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="physics" /><category term="biology" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="education" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A century ago, a small institution called Throop Polytechnic Institute dramatically reinvented itself, transforming from a manual arts academy to an engineering school, then expanding into a research institute. In 1920, it became the California Institute of Technology. In summer 2020, Caltech archivists gave a series of livestreamed presentations on the science, engineering, architecture, and community life of early Caltech.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Throops’s Superlative Opportunity”: The Story of the Gates Laboratory of Chemistry</title><link href="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2017/throops-superlative-opportunity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Throops’s Superlative Opportunity”: The Story of the Gates Laboratory of Chemistry" /><published>2017-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/exhibits/2017/throops-superlative-opportunity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2017/throops-superlative-opportunity/"><![CDATA[The Gates Laboratory of Chemistry, constructed in 1917 in part to persuade chemist Arthur A. Noyes to join the faculty, is Caltech’s oldest building and the first to cross the hundred-year threshold. Today, the building is the home of the Institute’s administrative offices and is called the Parsons-Gates Hall of Administration.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="exhibits" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="science" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="architecture" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Gates Laboratory of Chemistry, constructed in 1917 in part to persuade chemist Arthur A. Noyes to join the faculty, is Caltech’s oldest building and the first to cross the hundred-year threshold. Today, the building is the home of the Institute’s administrative offices and is called the Parsons-Gates Hall of Administration.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building a Chemistry Division</title><link href="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2017/building-a-chemistry-division/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Chemistry Division" /><published>2017-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/exhibits/2017/building-a-chemistry-division</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2017/building-a-chemistry-division/"><![CDATA[Over the century since the Gates Laboratory of Chemistry was built, Caltech’s Division of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering has grown exponentially. Here are some of the stories from that history.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="exhibits" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the century since the Gates Laboratory of Chemistry was built, Caltech’s Division of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering has grown exponentially. Here are some of the stories from that history.]]></summary></entry></feed>