<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/cybernetics.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-21T10:20:31-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/cybernetics.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy" /><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="art" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Video and the Self: Closed Circuit | Feedback | Narcissism</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2022/video-and-the-self/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Video and the Self: Closed Circuit | Feedback | Narcissism" /><published>2022-02-24T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2022/video-and-the-self</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2022/video-and-the-self/"><![CDATA[A chapter which I guest edited:

The relationship between video and the self has been one of the central concerns of video theory. Prominent artists such as Vito Acconci, Dan Graham, Joan Jonas, and Bruce Nauman have organized their artistic practice around mediated self-observation, either using video to document and complicate their own expressions of self or building installations with which viewers can see and experience themselves in new ways. Such self-portraiture is the subject of the most widely cited essay in this volume, Rosalind Krauss’s 1976 “Video: The Aesthetics of Narcissism,” and of several essays responding to it.

Even before videotape became an artistic medium in 1965, though, video, self-observation, and narcissism were already the subjects of a theoretical literature produced by psychiatrists and psychologists. If patients saw how disordered they appeared to others, some psychotherapists suggested, they might be motivated to change. Other clinicians rewatched sessions with patients so that either could pause the video to discuss emotions or experiences which they hadn’t articulated, essentially putting themselves back into a moment in the conversation. Some of the most prominent artists and theorists working with video were directly influenced by this video therapy tradition.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="art" /><category term="psychiatry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A chapter which I guest edited: The relationship between video and the self has been one of the central concerns of video theory. Prominent artists such as Vito Acconci, Dan Graham, Joan Jonas, and Bruce Nauman have organized their artistic practice around mediated self-observation, either using video to document and complicate their own expressions of self or building installations with which viewers can see and experience themselves in new ways. Such self-portraiture is the subject of the most widely cited essay in this volume, Rosalind Krauss’s 1976 “Video: The Aesthetics of Narcissism,” and of several essays responding to it. Even before videotape became an artistic medium in 1965, though, video, self-observation, and narcissism were already the subjects of a theoretical literature produced by psychiatrists and psychologists. If patients saw how disordered they appeared to others, some psychotherapists suggested, they might be motivated to change. Other clinicians rewatched sessions with patients so that either could pause the video to discuss emotions or experiences which they hadn’t articulated, essentially putting themselves back into a moment in the conversation. Some of the most prominent artists and theorists working with video were directly influenced by this video therapy tradition.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cybernetics Moment, or Why We Call Our Age the Information Age</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/cybernetics-moment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cybernetics Moment, or Why We Call Our Age the Information Age" /><published>2019-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2019/cybernetics-moment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/cybernetics-moment/"><![CDATA[The historical literature on cybernetics has ballooned in the last 15 years, as scholars have sought to understand how scientists and engineers studying “control and communication in the animal and the machine” (as Norbert Weiner subtitled his book <cite>Cybernetics</cite>) contributed to Soviet and Chilean computer networks, assistive technologies for the deaf, theories of schizophrenia, and experimental music and cinema, to name just a few of their projects. This range of topics raises anew the question—central to historians’ accounts since the early 1990s—of what exactly cybernetics was. As the first book to integrate the many dimensions of cybernetics into a single narrative, <cite>The Cybernetics Moment</cite> presents a new answer to this crucial question.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="computing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The historical literature on cybernetics has ballooned in the last 15 years, as scholars have sought to understand how scientists and engineers studying “control and communication in the animal and the machine” (as Norbert Weiner subtitled his book Cybernetics) contributed to Soviet and Chilean computer networks, assistive technologies for the deaf, theories of schizophrenia, and experimental music and cinema, to name just a few of their projects. This range of topics raises anew the question—central to historians’ accounts since the early 1990s—of what exactly cybernetics was. As the first book to integrate the many dimensions of cybernetics into a single narrative, The Cybernetics Moment presents a new answer to this crucial question.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ego Me Absolvo: Catholicism as Prototype in Paul Ryan’s Experimental Video</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2016/ego-me-absolvo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ego Me Absolvo: Catholicism as Prototype in Paul Ryan’s Experimental Video" /><published>2016-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2016/ego-me-absolvo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2016/ego-me-absolvo/"><![CDATA[In May 1969, a video installation entitled <cite>Everyman’s Moebius Strip</cite> appeared at the Howard Wise Gallery show <cite>TV as a Creative Medium</cite> in New York. When an individual entered a curtained booth, they found a video camera, a blank monitor, and an audio recording prompting participation. “React to the following people,” spoke the recording. “Nixon, your mother, Eldridge Cleaver, Teddy Kennedy, you.… For the next ten seconds do what you want.… Now, let your face be sad.… Turn away from the camera.… Now turn back.… Press the stop button.… Thank you.” After two minutes of this guidance, an attendant played a videotape of the viewer’s face back for them. Like its topological namesake, explained the artist, <cite>Everyman’s Moebius Strip</cite> “is used to take in our outside,” providing the viewer “one continuous (sur)face with nothing to hide.” Since each recording taped over the previous one, each participant received a unique, private experience of communing with the self.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In May 1969, a video installation entitled Everyman’s Moebius Strip appeared at the Howard Wise Gallery show TV as a Creative Medium in New York. When an individual entered a curtained booth, they found a video camera, a blank monitor, and an audio recording prompting participation. “React to the following people,” spoke the recording. “Nixon, your mother, Eldridge Cleaver, Teddy Kennedy, you.… For the next ten seconds do what you want.… Now, let your face be sad.… Turn away from the camera.… Now turn back.… Press the stop button.… Thank you.” After two minutes of this guidance, an attendant played a videotape of the viewer’s face back for them. Like its topological namesake, explained the artist, Everyman’s Moebius Strip “is used to take in our outside,” providing the viewer “one continuous (sur)face with nothing to hide.” Since each recording taped over the previous one, each participant received a unique, private experience of communing with the self.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="war" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="fascism" /><category term="New York" /><category term="California" /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2014/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2014/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2014/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[In the 1960s, video recording technology became portable. Tools that had previously been available only in television studios turned up in art galleries, in psychiatric hospitals, and in the Black Panther Party. This cultural portability was facilitated by a material portability: the technology got smaller, it got cheaper, it got lighter. For instance, this 1970 Sony camera is part of a piece of equipment called a portapak. Between the camera and the deck it was a complete video production studio that was light enough for somebody to carry around and was battery-powered. These recorders used half-inch open reel magnetic tape.

Many of the people using these new video technologies, from artists to psychiatrists to political activists, were particularly interested in what video meant for consciousness. They were interested in the experience of watching yourself on a television monitor. For some psychiatrists this was a self-confrontation experience that could force a person to confront how other people saw them and not merely experience themselves through their own impressions. For some artists this was a meditative experience, that watching yourself could be a path to holistic self-understanding.

Many of these experimental videographers were also interested in pointing cameras at their own monitors, and in the kaleidoscopic visual effects that appeared when they did this. And they referred to both these kaleidoscopic effects, this practice of pointing cameras at monitors, and to watching oneself on a monitor, as feedback, borrowing a term from the field of cybernetics. This idea of taking the message of a system that comes out of that system, like what you see coming out of a television, and putting it back into that system in order to make it reflect upon itself was something that they understood as both an optical and electronic phenomenon that could be harnessed to aesthetic ends, and as a psychological phenomenon that could lead to new kinds of human understanding.

They also thought about this on a broader social scale. If you could watch yourself and understand yourself better, perhaps watching other people, or watching the world through other people's eyes—watching video that they had shot—could help you understand others better. And this seemed a path to a kind of universal consciousness that had been described by Pierre Teilhard de Chardin as the noosphere—the global mind—or by Marshall McLuhan, who as a media theorist was a big influence on experimental video, as the global village.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="video" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="media" /><category term="technology" /><category term="art" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the 1960s, video recording technology became portable. Tools that had previously been available only in television studios turned up in art galleries, in psychiatric hospitals, and in the Black Panther Party. This cultural portability was facilitated by a material portability: the technology got smaller, it got cheaper, it got lighter. For instance, this 1970 Sony camera is part of a piece of equipment called a portapak. Between the camera and the deck it was a complete video production studio that was light enough for somebody to carry around and was battery-powered. These recorders used half-inch open reel magnetic tape. Many of the people using these new video technologies, from artists to psychiatrists to political activists, were particularly interested in what video meant for consciousness. They were interested in the experience of watching yourself on a television monitor. For some psychiatrists this was a self-confrontation experience that could force a person to confront how other people saw them and not merely experience themselves through their own impressions. For some artists this was a meditative experience, that watching yourself could be a path to holistic self-understanding. Many of these experimental videographers were also interested in pointing cameras at their own monitors, and in the kaleidoscopic visual effects that appeared when they did this. And they referred to both these kaleidoscopic effects, this practice of pointing cameras at monitors, and to watching oneself on a monitor, as feedback, borrowing a term from the field of cybernetics. This idea of taking the message of a system that comes out of that system, like what you see coming out of a television, and putting it back into that system in order to make it reflect upon itself was something that they understood as both an optical and electronic phenomenon that could be harnessed to aesthetic ends, and as a psychological phenomenon that could lead to new kinds of human understanding. They also thought about this on a broader social scale. If you could watch yourself and understand yourself better, perhaps watching other people, or watching the world through other people’s eyes—watching video that they had shot—could help you understand others better. And this seemed a path to a kind of universal consciousness that had been described by Pierre Teilhard de Chardin as the noosphere—the global mind—or by Marshall McLuhan, who as a media theorist was a big influence on experimental video, as the global village.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybernetics of the LRAD</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybernetics of the LRAD" /><published>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/"><![CDATA[<p>
	The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/">marketed</a> to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5369190/lrad-sound-cannon-used-on-pittsburgh-g20-protesters">first deployed in the United States</a> at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/14/chicago_cops_new_weapon/singleton/">will likely again</a> project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.
</p>
<!--more-->
<iframe class="video" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TInNg6QbHXc" title="Video player" frameborder="0" allow="picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen;"></iframe>
<p>
	As Aaron Bady <a href="http://thenewinquiry.com/blogs/hearing-like-an-lrad/">points out</a>, the LRAD brings together violence and speech. “To ask the question of whether an LRAD is designed to hurt people or designed to communicate across long distances with people,” writes Bady, “is to mystify its central design function: It is a technology whose purpose is to FORCE you to listen and obey, and one which is less interested in the difference than you’d think.” The LRAD makes it impossible to think of policing—particularly the iconic “order to disperse” delivered to political demonstrators from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haymarket_affair#Bombing_and_gunfire">Chicago in 1886</a> to Pittsburgh in 2009 (shown above)—as a process in which orders come first and force follows only in the case of disobedience. The medium through which orders are communicated is itself forceful; the LRAD is a <em>weapon</em>, which is why the LRAD Corporation sells it, according to their <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/content/view/323">fact sheet</a>, “only to qualified government agencies and commercial entities that are fully trained in the device’s operation.” Bady concludes, then, that the LRAD demonstrates policing is “simply about power. Communication is a means of making you obey,” and, from the perspective of the LRAD, nothing more.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD conflates communication and force not only conceptually but materially: The same sound serves both purposes. It thus taps into a deep seam in twentieth century science and philosophy that is concerned precisely with the relationship between communication and action. It could be interpreted, for instance, in terms of <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/~kbach/spchacts.html">speech act theory</a>: A loud LRAD order to disperse is both a threatening speech act and itself an act of force.
</p>
<p>
	Since the use of violence to establish control is intrinsic to the LRAD, though, its collapsing of communication and force resonates less with speech acts than the mid-century science of cybernetics. As MIT mathematician Norbert Wiener subtitled <a href="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL14113345M/Cybernetics_or_Control_and_communication_in_the_animal_and_the_machine.">his 1948 book</a> in which he named the discipline, cybernetics involved the study of “control and communication in the animal and machine.” The field developed in the late 1940s through collaborations between scientists interested in understanding minds, societies, and machines in the same terms—collaborations such as the <a href="http://asc-cybernetics.org/foundations/history/MacySummary.htm">Macy Conferences</a>—and cyberneticians conflated control and communication in part to establish parallels between these different entities. This collapsing of categories also owed something, though, to the origins of cybernetics in military research.
</p>
<p>
	Wiener did much of his thinking about analogies between humans and mechanical control systems during World War II while designing an “antiaircraft predictor,” designed to aim a gun in order to shoot down a maneuvering plane. Such a predictor was necessary because during the twenty seconds a shell took to reach its target, the pilot would maneuver, apparently unpredictably. In his article “<a href="http://jerome-segal.de/Galison94.pdf">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” and a <a href="http://cabinetmagazine.org/issues/12/najafi2.php">followup interview</a> in <cite>Cabinet</cite>, historian of science <a href="https://galison.scholar.harvard.edu">Peter Galison</a> argues that Wiener conceived of the enemy pilot as essentially mechanical, and his predictor as a machine that mirrored its behavior. “With no access to anything in the enemy plane,” he says, “Wiener simply treated the pilot-plane assembly as a complex machine—a servomechanism—that once characterized could be simulated in order to predict what it would do. And then it could be blown out of the sky.”
</p>
<p>
	Although Wiener’s work stood in a long tradition of <a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL8396574W/Between_Human_and_Machine">control engineering</a>—since his goal was simply to control a gun—his system also relied on interpreting the plane’s motions as communication to the predictor, which then “learned” its patterns by observing with radar. Even though, “because of the antagonistic relationship between attacker and defender, the anti-aircraft operator was obviously in no position to talk to or even see the pilot,” the latter’s movements still revealed—communicated—his intentions. From Wiener’s perspective as an engineer, though, there was no distinction between control and communication in this system; both were simply messages. There were messages conveyed by the pilot to the plane (through a joystick, say), from the plane to the predictor (through radar), from the predictor to the gun (through a mechanical connection), and from the gun to the plane (through a shell), but each relationship was one of both control and communication, of both force and speech.
</p>
<p>
	The U.S. military also embraced this conflation. During the decades after World War II “command and control,” previously two competing models of military management, became a single practice. <em>Command</em> traditionally involved an officer giving an order which was then interpreted and implemented by those below him in a hierarchy, often as more specific commands to their subordinates. It involved the ambiguity we expect from human communication, if not the dialogue. <em>Control</em>, on the other hand, was direct and (at least ideally) unambiguous. Nuclear weapons, which had to be deployed rapidly and only upon the decision of senior commanders, were subject to control rather than command. This distinction collapsed, though, as nuclear weapons were integrated into conventional military tactics. “By the early 1960s,” writes historian of technology <a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a> in <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2937046W/The_Closed_World">The Closed World</a></cite>, “military parlance treated the two as virtually identical. A decade later, ‘command, control, communications, and information’ (C<sup>3</sup>I) had become a single unified process.”
</p>
<p>
	It is from this postwar military ideology that the LRAD and its inventor Elwood Norris emerged. According to <a href="http://keynotespeakers.com/speaker_detail.php?speakerid=4074">his speaking bio</a>, Norris served in the Air Force as a nuclear weapons specialist in the 1950s before becoming an independent inventor. He was <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2009/03/06/smallbusiness/killer_sounds.fsb/">hired by the Navy</a> to design the LRAD in 2000 after the U.S.S. Cole bombing, and the original purpose of the device was to deter guerrillas from U.S. warships. It has since been used to deter Somali pirates from commercial ships and “to blast a series of Arabic phrases, such as ‘Go away or we will kill you,’” in Baghdad and Fallujah.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD, then, is a military technology that has come home to U.S. soil as a command-and-control system for conveying both orders and force from police to civilians. Its erasure of the distinction between control and communication is not a unique phenomenon that emerges when you build a very loud speaker; rather, its inventor designed a speaker loud enough to “influence behavior and create safety zones” because he and his employers already conflated force and speech.
</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="war" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is marketed to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was first deployed in the United States at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and will likely again project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wipe Cycle: Feedback and Experimental Video</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2012/wipe-cycle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wipe Cycle: Feedback and Experimental Video" /><published>2012-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2012/wipe-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2012/wipe-cycle/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="video" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="art" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="media" /><category term="technology" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">History of Cybernetics Bibliography</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="History of Cybernetics Bibliography" /><published>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>If you’ve come here after asking yourself (or Google) what cybernetics is, I recommend starting with Bernard Geoghegan and Benjamin Peters’ entry “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” from the <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite>, and Geoffrey Bowker’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>.” Ronald Kline’s <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment</a></cite> is the synthetic history the field has been waiting for. William Aspray’s “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>” places cybernetics in the context of developments in computing and information theory, while Peter Galison’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” is a classic account of the field’s military origins. The texts listed below survey the many forms cybernetics took in the decades that followed.</p>
	
<p>This bibliography is limited in three ways: It includes only books and articles which focus on cybernetics rather than the related histories of cyborgs and information theory; it includes only texts in English, though there are also substantial French and German literatures on the subject; and it excludes articles and dissertations that have been superseded by books by the same authors. Within these limitations, I welcome references to additional books and articles. I last updated this list on November 26, 2023.</p>

<h3 id="big">The Big Picture <small>(but mostly Anglo-American)</small></h3>
<ol class="start">
	<li>A. A. Verveen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0025-5564(71)90004-6">In Search of Processes: The Early History of Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Mathematical Biosciences</cite> 11 (1971).
	<li>Michael Apter, “Cybernetics: A Case Study of a Scientific Subject-Complex,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sociology-of-science/oclc/591825">The Sociology of Science</a></cite>, edited by Paul Halmos (University of Keele, 1972).</li>
	<li>Robert Lilienfeld, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-systems-theory-an-ideological-analysis/oclc/3275488">The Rise of Systems Theory: An Ideological Analysis</a></cite> (Wiley, 1978).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>,” <cite>Social Studies of Science</cite> 23 (1993).</li>
	<li><a href="http://nkhayles.com/">Katherine Hayles</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-we-became-posthuman-virtual-bodies-in-cybernetics-literature-and-informatics/oclc/39539341">How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in Cybernetics, Literature, and Informatics</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 1999).</li>
	<li>Charles Fran&ccedil;ois, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1099-1743(199905%2F06)16%3A3%3C203%3A%3AAID-SRES210%3E3.0.CO%3B2-1">Systemics and Cybernetics in a Historical Perspective</a>,” <cite>Systems Research and Behavioral Science</cite> 16 (1999).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sonoma.edu/hutchins/faculty/debora-hammond.html">Debora Hammond</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-of-synthesis-exploring-the-social-implications-of-general-systems-theory/oclc/939936819">The Science of Synthesis: Exploring the Social Implications of General Systems Theory</a></cite> (University Press of Colorado, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “The Empty Archive: Cybernetics and the 1960s,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/memory-practices-in-the-sciences/oclc/60776866">Memory Practices in the Sciences</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2008.9">The Historiographic Conceptualization of Information: A Critical Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 30 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://english.emory.edu/home/people/faculty/faculty_pages/johnston.html">John Johnston</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/allure-of-machinic-life-cybernetics-artificial-life-and-the-new-ai/oclc/255975196">The Allure of Machinic Life: Cybernetics, Artificial Life, and the New AI</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2008).</li>
	<li>Philipp Aumann, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2011.78">The Distinctiveness of a Unifying Science: Cybernetics’ Way to West Germany</a>” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 33 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000018">Cybernetic Sense</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/beautiful-data-a-history-of-vision-and-reason-since-1945/oclc/875884461">Beautiful Data: A History of Vision and Reason since 1945</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2014).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment; or, Why We Call Our Age the Information Age</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="http://medientheorie.com/">Claus Pias</a>, “The Age of Cybernetics,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-the-macy-conferences-1946-1953-transactions/oclc/945975579">Cybernetics: The Macy Conferences, 1946–1954; The Complete Transactions</a></cite> (diaphanes, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://ridt.co/">Thomas Rid</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-the-machines-a-cybernetic-history/oclc/921868924">Rise of the Machines: A Cybernetic History</a></cite> (Norton, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a> and <a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite> (2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://elizabethpetrick.com">Elizabeth Petrick</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243919881212">Building the Black Box: Cyberneticians and Complex Systems</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, and Human Values</cite> (2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="origins">Origins</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Otto Mayr, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/origins-of-feedback-control/oclc/102836">The Origins of Feedback Control</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1970).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~bill/">William Aspray</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 7 (1985).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/between-human-and-machine-feedback-control-and-computing-before-cybernetics/oclc/51493422">Between Human and Machine: Feedback, Control, and Computing before Cybernetics</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="us">United States</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20027476">The Americanization of Unity</a>,” <cite>Daedalus</cite> 127 (1998).</li>
	<li>Peter Krieg, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920510581729">The Human Face of Cybernetics: Heinz von Foerster and the History of a Movement That Failed</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 34 (2005).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/">Stuart Umpleby</a>, “<a href="http://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/cybernetics/2005_WAS_History_of_Cybernetics_Movement.doc">A History of the Cybernetics Movement in the United States</a>,” <cite>Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences</cite> 91 (2005).</li>
	<li>Christopher Johnson, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43151893">Analogue Apollo: Cybernetics and the Space Age</a>,” <cite>Paragraph</cite> 31 (2008).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="wiener">Norbert Wiener</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/john-von-neumann-and-norbert-wiener-from-mathematics-to-the-technologies-of-life-and-death/oclc/6304716">John von Neumann and Norbert Wiener: From Mathematics to the Technologies of Life and Death</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1982).</li>
	<li>Pesi Masani, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/norbert-wiener-1894-1964/oclc/19389460">Norbert Wiener, 1894–1964</a></cite> (Birkhauser, 1990).</li>
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 21 (1994).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.unizar.es/sociocybernetics/chen/felix/">Felix Geyer</a> and Johannes van der Zouwen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684929410068334">Norbert Wiener and the Social Sciences</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 23 (1994).
	<li><a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=112">David Jerison</a> and <a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=268">Daniel Stroock</a>, “Norbert Wiener,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://conwayandsiegelman.stillpointpress.net/">Flo Conway and Jim Siegelman</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/dark-hero-of-the-information-age-in-search-of-norbert-wiener-the-father-of-cybernetics/oclc/56656253">Dark Hero of the Information Age: In Search of Norbert Wiener, the Father of Cybernetics</a></cite> (Basic Books, 2004).</li>
	<li><a href="http://maramills.org/">Mara Mills</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-1428852">On Disability and Cybernetics: Helen Keller, Norbert Wiener, and the Hearing Glove</a>,” <cite>differences</cite> 22 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19409419.2013.775544">Toward a Genealogy of a Cold War Communication Science: The Strange Loops of Leo and Norbert Wiener</a>,” <cite>Russian Journal of Communication</cite> 5 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.uni-weimar.de/de/medien/professuren/medienwissenschaft/theorie-medialer-welten/personen/schmidgen/">Henning Schmidgen</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119880662">Cybernetic Times: Norbert Wiener, John Stroud, and the ‘Brain Clock’ Hypothesis</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="ussr">Soviet and Comparative Studies</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/david-holloway">David Holloway</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/284545">Innovation in Science—The Case of Cybernetics in the Soviet Union</a>,” <cite>Science Studies</cite> 4 (1974).</li>
	<li>Peter Elias, “The Rise and Fall of Cybernetics in the US and the USSR,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-newspeak-to-cyberspeak-a-history-of-soviet-cybernetics/oclc/48477582">From Newspeak to Cyberspeak: A History of Soviet Cybernetics</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <a href="http://jerome-segal.de/">J&eacute;r&ocirc;me Segal</a>, and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, “From Communications Engineering to Communications Science: Cybernetics and Information Theory in the United States, France, and the Soviet Union,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-and-ideology-a-comparative-history/oclc/49395331">Science and Ideology: A Comparative History</a></cite>, edited by Mark Walker (Routledge, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="http://ijoc.org/ojs/index.php/ijoc/article/view/212">Betrothal and Betrayal: The Soviet Translation of Norbert Wiener’s Early Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Communications</cite> 2 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-not-to-network-a-nation-the-uneasy-history-of-the-soviet-internet/oclc/927438758">How Not to Network a Nation: The Uneasy History of the Soviet Internet</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://cla.auburn.edu/history/people/faculty/instructors/diana-kurkovsky-west/">Diana Kurkovsky West</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886520">Cybernetics for the Command Economy: Foregrounding Entropy in Late Soviet Planning</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.lafayette.edu/sanbornj/">Joshua Sanborn</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/kri.2022.0044">Cybernetics and Surveillance: The Secret Police Enter the Computer Age</a>,” <cite>Kritika</cite> 23 (2022).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="france">France and “French Theory”</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://socio.umontreal.ca/repertoire-departement/vue/lafontaine-celine/">C&eacute;line Lafontaine</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276407084637">The Cybernetic Matrix of ‘French Theory,’</a>” <cite>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</cite> 24 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~ll2410/">Lydia Liu</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/648527">The Cybernetic Unconscious: Rethinking Lacan, Poe, and French Theory</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 36 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.cornell.edu/jacob-krell">Jacob Krell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886988">What is the ‘Cybernetic’ in the ‘History of Cybernetics’? A French Case, 1968 to the Present</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/en/lehrbereiche-en/general-sociology/team/vincent-august/index">Vincent August</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1368431021991046">Network Concepts in Social Theory: Foucault and Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>European Journal of Social Theory</cite> 24 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1346150607">Code: From Information Theory to French Theory</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2023)</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="chile">Chile</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-revolutionaries-technology-and-politics-in-allendes-chile/oclc/713834502">Cybernetic Revolutionaries: Technology and Politics in Allende’s Chile</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/people/staff/martin-collins">Martin Collins</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2013.776857">introduction to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://usnwc.edu/Faculty-and-Departments/Directory/Michael-Aaron-Dennis">Michael Dennis</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756240">Scientific and Technical Knowledge and the Making of Political Order</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756239">Beyond the Closed World</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://drexel.edu/coas/faculty-research/faculty-directory/TiagoSaraiva/">Tiago Saraiva</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756238">The History of Cybernetics in McOndo</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756237">author response to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="biology">Biology</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-1979-20-206">The Biological Enterprise: Sex, Mind, and Profit from Human Engineering to Sociobiology</a>,” <cite>Radical History Review</cite> no. 20 (1979).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “The High Cost of Information in Post World War II Evolutionary Biology: Ergonomics, Semiotics, and the Sociobiology of Communications Systems,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/philosophical-forum/oclc/1787155">Philosophical Forum</a></cite> 13 (1981–2).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “Signs of Dominance: From a Physiology to a Cybernetics of Primate Society, C.R. Carpenter, 1930–1970,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/studies-in-history-of-biology/oclc/2957828">Studies in History of Biology</a></cite> 6, edited by William Coleman and Camille Limoges (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “A Semiotics of the Naturalistic Field, from C.R. Carpenter to S.A. Altmann, 1930–55,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/primate-visions-gender-race-and-nature-in-the-world-of-modern-science/oclc/19672184">Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</a></cite> (Routledge, 1989).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “The Body of a New Machine: Situating the Organism between Telegraphs and Computers,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/refiguring-life-metaphors-of-twentieth-century-biology/oclc/31606662">Refiguring Life: Metaphors of Twentieth-Century Biology</a></cite> (Columbia University Press, 1995).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/who-wrote-the-book-of-life-a-history-of-the-genetic-code/oclc/41967065">Who Wrote the Book of Life? A History of the Genetic Code</a></cite> (Stanford University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “Taming the Cybernetic Metaphor” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/making-sense-of-life-explaining-biological-development-with-models-metaphors-and-machines/oclc/48100379">Making Sense of Life: Explaining Biological Development with Models, Metaphors, and Machines</a></cite> (Harvard University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sydney.edu.au/arts/history/staff/profiles/warwick.anderson.php">Warwick Anderson</a> and Ian MacKay, “The Science of Self,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/intolerant-bodies-a-short-history-of-autoimmunity/oclc/894511336">Intolerant Bodies: A Short History of Autoimmunity</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="ecology">Ecology</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://faculty.umb.edu/pjt/">Peter Taylor</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4331051">Technocratic Optimism, H.T. Odum, and the Partial Transformation of Ecological Metaphor after World War II</a>,” <cite>Journal of the History of Biology</cite> 21 (1988).</li>
	<li><a href="http://host.jhu.edu/directory/sharon-kingsland/">Sharon Kingsland</a>, “Defining the Ecosystem,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/evolution-of-american-ecology-1890-2000/oclc/56982282">The Evolution of American Ecology, 1890–2000</a></cite> (John Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li>William Bryant, “<a href="http://search.proquest.com/docview/305339541/">Whole System, Whole Earth: The Convergence of Technology and Ecology in Twentieth-Century American Culture</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Iowa, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “Neocybernetics of Gaia: The Emergence of Second-Order Gaia Theory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gaia-in-turmoil-climate-change-biodepletion-and-earth-ethics-in-an-age-of-crisis/oclc/313017382">Gaia in Turmoil: Climate Change, Biodepletion, and Earth Ethics in an Age of Crisis</a></cite>, edited by Eileen Crist and H. Bruce Rinker (MIT Press, 2010).</li>
	<li>Nancy Slack, “Good Friends: Margaret Mead and Gregory Bateson” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/g-evelyn-hutchinson-and-the-invention-of-modern-ecology/oclc/758332328">G. Evelyn Hutchinson and the Invention of Modern Ecology</a></cite> (Yale University Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.usf.edu/arts-sciences/departments/humanities-cultural-studies/faculty/daniel-belgrad.aspx">Daniel Belgrad</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1153210310">The Culture of Feedback: Ecological Thinking in ’70s America</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="social">Social Sciences</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-group/oclc/23047769">Constructing a Social Science for Postwar America: The Cybernetics Group, 1946–1953</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.albany.edu/~gpr/">George Richardson</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-thought-in-social-science-and-systems-theory/oclc/22731896">Feedback Thought in Social Science and Systems Theory</a></cite> (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://emsent.nl/">Esther-Mirjam Sent</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/perspectives_on_science/v008/8.4sent.html">Herbert A. Simon as a Cyborg Scientist</a>,” <cite>Perspectives on Science</cite> 8 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://reilly.nd.edu/people/reilly-fellows/philip-mirowski/">Philip Mirowski</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/machine-dreams-economics-becomes-a-cyborg-science/oclc/45636899">Machine Dreams: Economics Becomes a Cyborg Science</a></cite> (Cambridge University Press, 2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Crowther-Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/herbert-a-simon-the-bounds-of-reason-in-modern-america/oclc/55511492">Herbert A. Simon: The Bounds of Reason in Modern America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/age-of-system-understanding-the-development-of-modern-social-science/oclc/891185841">Age of System: Understanding the Development of Modern Social Science</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.stefanos-geroulanos.com">Stefanos Geroulanos</a> and <a href="https://leifweatherby.org/">Leif Weatherby</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119887098">“Cybernetics and the Human Sciences” special issue introduction</a>, <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119872111">How Disunity Matters to the History of Cybernetics in the Human Sciences in the United States, 1940–80</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li>Poornima Paidipaty, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1463499619899747">‘Tortoises All the Way Down’: Geertz, Cybernetics and ‘Culture’ at the End of the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Anthropological Theory</cite> 20 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="bateson">Gregory Bateson</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://cla.umn.edu/about/directory/profile/lipse001">David Lipset</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gregory-bateson-the-legacy-of-a-scientist/oclc/5894222">Gregory Bateson: The Legacy of a Scientist</a></cite> (Prentice Hall, 1980).</li>
	<li><a href="http://hss.sas.upenn.edu/people/tresch">John Tresch</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2783231">Heredity is an Open System: Gregory Bateson as Descendant and Ancestor</a>,” <cite>Anthropology Today</cite> 14 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.armoniedeldisordine.it/">Leone Montagnini</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777522">Looking for ‘Scientific’ Social Science: The Macy Conferences on Cybernetics in Bateson’s Itinerary</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li>Frank Thomas, Rebekah Waits, and Gail Hartsfield, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777397">The Influence of Gregory Bateson: Legacy or Vestige?</a>” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.northeastern.edu/camd/artdesign/people/william-kaizen/">William Kaizen</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598913">Steps to an Ecology of Communication: <cite>Radical Software</cite>, Dan Graham, and the Legacy of Gregory Bateson</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://history.ua.edu/faculty/erik-peterson/">Erik Peterson</a>, “<a href="http://etd.nd.edu/ETD-db/theses/available/etd-04132010-142514/">Finding Mind, Form, Organism, and Person in a Reductionist Age: The Challenge of Gregory Bateson and C. H. Waddington to Biological and Anthropological Orthodoxy, 1924–1980</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Notre Dame, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="http://sfonline.barnard.edu/feminist-media-theory/schizophrenic-techniques-cybernetics-the-human-sciences-and-the-double-bind/">Schizophrenic Techniques: Cybernetics, the Human Sciences, and the Double Bind</a>,” <cite>S&amp;F Online</cite> 10 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://laps-dept.apps01.yorku.ca/anth/faculty/emeriti/harries.html">Peter Harries-Jones</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/upside-down-gods-gregory-batesons-world-of-difference/oclc/952953457">Upside-Down Gods: Gregory Bateson’s World of Difference</a></cite> (Fordham University Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthonychaney.com/">Anthony Chaney</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/runaway-gregory-bateson-the-double-bind-and-the-rise-of-ecological-consciousness/oclc/1032366653">Runaway: Gregory Bateson, the Double Bind, and the Rise of Ecological Consciousness</a></cite> (University of North Carolina Press, 2017).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="mind">Sciences of Mind</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.sv.uio.no/psi/personer/vit/geirki/">Geir Kirkeb&oslash;en</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/053901895034001002">From a Naked Emperor to Just Clothes: The Rise and Fall of Cybernetic Family Therapy</a>,” <cite>Social Science Information</cite> 34 (1995).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.brown.edu/Departments/CLPS/people/james-anderson">James Anderson</a> and Edward Rosenfeld, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/6626.001.0001">Talking Nets: An Oral History of Neural Networks</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1998).</li>
	<li><a href="https://dlcl.stanford.edu/people/jean-pierre-dupuy">Jean-Pierre Dupuy</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mechanization-of-the-mind-on-the-origins-of-cognitive-science/oclc/44026149">The Mechanization of the Mind: The Origins of Cognitive Science</a></cite>, translated by M. B. DeBevoise (Princeton University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li>Roberto Cordeschi, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/discovery-of-the-artificial-behavior-mind-and-machines-before-and-beyond-cybernetics/oclc/49860160">The Discovery of the Artificial: Behavior, Mind and Machines Before and Beyond Cybernetics</a></cite> (Kluwer Academic Publishers, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1024147708370">From Theory to Data: Representing Neurons in the 1940s</a>,” <cite>Biology and Philosophy</cite> 18 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1162/biot.2006.1.4.418">Cybernetics and Theoretical Approaches in 20th-Century Brain and Behavior Sciences</a>,” <cite>Biological Theory</cite> 1 (2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://socialsciences.exeter.ac.uk/sociology/staff/pickering/">Andrew Pickering</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-brain-sketches-of-another-future/oclc/615626770">The Cybernetic Brain: Sketches of Another Future</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://histsci.fas.harvard.edu/people/rebecca-lemov">Rebecca Lemov</a>, “<a href="http://limn.it/running-amok-in-labyrinthine-systems-the-cyber-behaviorist-origins-of-soft-torture/">Running Amok in Labyrinthine Systems: The Cyber-Behaviorist Origins of Soft Torture</a>,” <cite>Limn</cite> 1 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/dweinste">Deborah Weinstein</a>, “‘Systems Everywhere’: Schizophrenia, Cybernetics, and the Double Bind,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/pathological-family-postwar-america-and-the-rise-of-family-therapy/oclc/800721205">The Pathological Family: Postwar America and the Rise of Family Therapy</a></cite> (Cornell University Press, 2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://mediashiga.net/">John Shiga</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/of-other-networks/">Of Other Networks: Closed-World and Green-World Networks in the Work of John C. Lilly</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://hps.utoronto.ca/staff/chen-pang-yeang/">Chen-Pang Yeang</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/694184">From Modernizing the Chinese Language to Information Science: Chao Yuen Ren’s Route to Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 108 (2017).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthropology.columbia.edu/content/danielle-judith-zola-carr">Danielle Judith Zola Carr</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119874009">‘Ghastly Marionettes’ and the Political Metaphysics of Cognitive Literalism: Anti-Behaviourism, Language, and the Origins of Totalitarianism</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.christinavagt.com">Christina Vagt</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119882883">Design as Aesthetic Education: On the Politics and Aesthetics of Learning Environments</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.princeton.edu/people/katja-guenther">Katja Guenther</a>, “The Dancing Robot: Grey Walter’s Cybernetic Mirror,” in <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1345590894">The Mirror and the Mind: A History of Self-Recognition in the Human Sciences</a></cite> (Princeton University Press, 2022).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="mcculloch">Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://ngp.usc.edu/faculty/profile/?fid=16">Michael Arbib</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0001">Warren McCulloch’s Search for the Logic of the Nervous System</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.psych.uic.edu/department-of-psychiatry-faculty-list/154-about-us/directory/faculty/234-neil-r-smalheiser-md-phd">Neil Smalheiser</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0009">Walter Pitts</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0269889701000266">From Logical Neurons to Poetic Embodiments of Mind: Warren S. McCulloch’s Project in Neuroscience</a>,” <cite>Science in Context</cite> 14 (2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0160-9327(03)00017-6">Integrating Mind and Brain: Warren S. McCulloch, Cerebral Localization, and Experimental Epistemology</a>,” <cite>Endeavour</cite> 27 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/kenaizawa/">Kenneth Aizawa</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000017">Warren McCulloch’s Turn to Cybernetics: What Walter Pitts Contributed</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~philh/">Phil Husbands</a> and <a href="http://cswww.essex.ac.uk/staff/owen/">Owen Holland</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000019">Warren McCulloch and the British Cyberneticians</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/psychology/contact-and-getting-here/people/alan-collins">Alan Collins</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000020">An Asymmetric Relationship: The Spirit of Kenneth Craik and the Work of Warren McCulloch</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, <cite><a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/rebel-genius">Rebel Genius: Warren S. McCulloch’s Transdisciplinary Life in Science</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="politics">Politics and Planning</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/closed-world-computers-and-the-politics-of-discourse-in-cold-war-america/oclc/42636403">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1996).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-warfare-to-welfare-defense-intellectuals-and-urban-problems-in-cold-war-america/oclc/51924188">From Warfare to Welfare: Defense Intellectuals and Urban Problems in Cold War America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.0.0007">Taking Games Seriously</a>,” <cite>Technology and Culture</cite> 49 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bbk.ac.uk/politics/our-staff/academic/antoine-bousquet">Antoine Bousquet</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14682740701791359">Cyberneticizing the American War Machine: Science and Computers in the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Cold War History</cite> 8 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.egs.edu/faculty/brian-holmes/">Brian Holmes</a>, <cite><a href="https://brianholmes.wordpress.com/2009/01/19/book-materials/">Escape the Overcode: Activist Art in the Control Society</a></cite> (Van Abbemuseum, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://geography.utoronto.ca/matt-farish-home-page/">Matthew Ferish</a>, “The Cybernetic Continent: North America as Defense Laboratory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/contours-of-americas-cold-war/oclc/698116870">The Contours of America’s Cold War</a></cite> (University of Minnesota Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://democracycollaborative.org/content/john-duda">John Duda</a>, “<a href="https://www.lwbooks.co.uk/anarchist-studies/21-1/cybernetics-anarchism-and-self-organisation">Cybernetics, Anarchism and Self-Organisation</a>,” <cite>Anarchist Studies</cite> 21 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://rhetoric.berkeley.edu/people/david-bates/">David Bates</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864237">The Political Theology of Entropy: A Katechon for the Cybernetic Age</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eui.eu/DepartmentsAndCentres/HistoryAndCivilization/People/Professors/Guilhot">Nicolas Guilhot</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864244">Automatic Leviathan: Cybernetics and Politics in Carl Schmitt’s Postwar Writings</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.hf.uio.no/ikos/english/people/aca/middle-east-studies/temporary/joakimp/">Joakim Parslow</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0020743821001033">The Mechanical Atatürk: Cybernetics and State Violence in the Second Turkish Republic</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Middle East Studies</cite> 53 (2021).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="popular">Popular Culture and Counterculture</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://homepages.rpi.edu/~eglash/eglash.htm">Ron Eglash</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/095023898335474">Cybernetics in American Youth Subculture</a>,” <cite>Cultural Studies</cite> 12 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://fredturner.stanford.edu/">Fred Turner</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-counterculture-to-cyberculture-stewart-brand-the-whole-earth-network-and-the-rise-of-digital-utopianism/oclc/62533774">From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “<a href="http://www.univie.ac.at/constructivism/journal/7/3/196.clarke">From Information to Cognition: The Systems Counterculture, Heinz von Foerster’s Pedagogy, and Second-Order Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Constructivist Foundations</cite> 7 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.dubberly.com/about">Hugh Dubberly</a> and <a href="http://pangaro.com">Paul Pangaro</a>, “<a href="http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html">How Cybernetics Connects Computing, Counterculture, and Design</a>,” in <cite>Hippie Modernism: The Struggle for Utopia</cite>, edited by Andrew Blauvelt (2015).</li>
	<!--Felicity Scott?-->
</ol>

<h3 id="art">Art</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://daniels.utoronto.ca/people/lobsingerm">Mary Louise Lobsinger</a>, “Cybernetic Theory and the Architecture of Performance: Cedric Price’s Fun Palace,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/anxious-modernisms-experimentation-in-postwar-architectural-culture/oclc/46929153">Anxious Modernisms: Experimentation in Postwar Architectural Culture</a></cite> (Canadian Center for Architecture, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://artexetra.wordpress.com">Edward Shanken</a>, “<a href="http://artexetra.com/CyberneticsArtCultConv.pdf">Cybernetics and Art: Cultural Convergence in the 1960s</a>,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-energy-to-information-representation-in-science-and-technology-art-and-literature/oclc/49821329">From Energy to Information</a></cite>, edited by Bruce Clarke and Linda Henderson (Stanford University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/leonardo/v041/41.2.fernandez.html">Gordon Pask: Cybernetic Polymath</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 41 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598908">Detached from HiStory: Jasia Reichardt and Cybernetic Serendipity</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li>Etan J. Ilfeld, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00326">Contemporary Art and Cybernetics: Waves of Cybernetic Discourse within Conceptual, Video and New Media Art</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 45 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://etiennebenson.com/">Etienne Benson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.7275/R5HT2M7T">Environment between System and Nature: Alan Sonfist and the Art of the Cybernetic Environment</a>,” <cite>communication +1</cite> 3 (2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="film">Film and Video</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.gc.cuny.edu/Page-Elements/Academics-Research-Centers-Initiatives/Doctoral-Programs/Art-History/Faculty-Bios/David-Joselit">David Joselit</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-television-against-democracy/oclc/71322293">Feedback: Television Against Democracy</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://art.stonybrook.edu/faculty/zabet-patterson/">Zabet Patterson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/grey.2009.1.36.36">From the Gun Controller to the Mandala: The Cybernetic Cinema of John and James Whitney</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite> no. 36 (2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://film.fsu.edu/People/Administration/Dr.-Andrew-Syder">Andrew Syder</a>, “<a href="http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15799coll127/id/220820/">“Shaken Out of the Ruts of Ordinary Perception”: Vision, Culture and Technology in the Psychedelic Sixties</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Southern California, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://kpaulsen.com/">Kris Paulsen</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/half-inch-revolution/">Half Inch Revolution: The Guerilla Video Tape Network</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="http://procom.ryerson.ca/people/carolyn-kane">Carolyn Kane</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00871">The Tragedy of Radical Subjectivity: From Radical Software to Proprietary Subjects</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 47, no. 5 (2014).</li>
	<li><a href="https://collopy.net/">Peter Sachs Collopy</a>, “<a href="https://repository.upenn.edu/edissertations/1665/">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://medienwissenschaft.philhist.unibas.ch/de/personen/ute-holl/">Ute Holl</a>, <cite><a href="http://library.oapen.org/handle/20.500.12657/31337">Cinema, Trance and Cybernetics</a></cite> (Amsterdam University Press, 2017).
</ol>

<h4 id="sound">Sound and Music</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://annenberg.usc.edu/faculty/communication/christina-dunbar-hester">Christina Dunbar-Hester</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243909337116">Listening to Cybernetics: Music, Machines, and Nervous Systems, 1950–1980</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</cite> 35 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sterneworks.org/">Jonathan Sterne</a>, “Nature Builds No Telephones” and “Perceptual Coding and the Domestication of Noise,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mp3-the-meaning-of-a-format/oclc/769429993">MP3: The Meaning of a Format</a></cite> (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/staff/profiles/music/haworth-christopher.aspx">Christopher Haworth</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.461">Music and Cybernetics in Historical Perspective: Introduction to the Special Issue</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://deirdreloughridge.wordpress.com">Deirdre Loughridge</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.503">Daphne Oram: Cyberneticist?</a>” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eamonnbell.com">Eamonn Bell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.523">Cybernetics, Listening, and Sound-Studio Phenomenotechnique in Abraham Moles’s <cite>Théorie de l’information et perception esthétique</cite> (1958)</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.claralatham.com">Clara Latham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.559">The Sound Machine in the Body: Cybernetics and the Theremin</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://music.utexas.edu/about/people/eric-drott">Eric Drott</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.578">Music and the Cybernetic Mundane</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://ted-gordon.net">Theodore Gordon</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07494467.2021.2001939">‘Androgynous Music’: Pauline Oliveros’s Early Cybernetic Improvisation</a>,” <cite>Contemporary Music Review</cite> 40 (2022).</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="computing" /><category term="art" /><category term="war" /><category term="biology" /><category term="video" /><category term="media" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="psychiatry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.]]></summary></entry></feed>