<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/engineering.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-09T12:46:08-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/engineering.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Beckmans at Caltech, 1923–1939</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2025/beckmans/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beckmans at Caltech, 1923–1939" /><published>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2025/beckmans</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2025/beckmans/"><![CDATA[From 1923 to 1939, Arnold Beckman was first a graduate student and then a professor at Caltech. Peter Sachs Collopy, PhD discusses Arnold and Mabel Beckman’s relationships with Caltech and how Caltech changed during this period.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="electronics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From 1923 to 1939, Arnold Beckman was first a graduate student and then a professor at Caltech. Peter Sachs Collopy, PhD discusses Arnold and Mabel Beckman’s relationships with Caltech and how Caltech changed during this period.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/crossing-over/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020" /><published>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/crossing-over</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/crossing-over/"><![CDATA[Science is as much a visual practice as a textual or quantitative one. For centuries, scientists have used microscopes, telescopes, painting, illustration, printing, and photography to perceive nature and communicate what they see in it, often in collaboration with artists. In the twentieth century, scientists also came to view creativity as an essential resource and looked to art to foster it.

*Crossing Over* is an interdisciplinary publication that looks at one prominent university—the California Institute of Technology (Caltech) in Pasadena—as a site for scientific and artistic image production. Uncovering the rich pictorial record embedded in its Archives and Special Collections, a team of visual culture scholars examines Caltech through a series of tightly focused case studies. How, the authors ask, have science and engineering institutions like Caltech used scientific representation, art, and architecture to construct themselves and produce discovery and invention? This book reveals new facets of life and work at Caltech that will be illuminating even to those familiar with the school, showcasing views that informed—and were informed by—the vibrant visual culture of Southern California.

This volume was published to accompany [an exhibition](/exhibits/2024/crossing-over) on view at the California Institute of Technology from September 27 to December 15, 2024. It is a [finalist](https://www.collegeart.org/news/2025/11/13/announcing-the-2026-morey-book-award-and-barr-awards-shortlists/) for the College Art Association’s 2026 Alfred H. Barr Jr. Award for Smaller Museums, Libraries, Collections, and Exhibitions.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="art" /><category term="astronomy" /><category term="biology" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="computing" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="geology" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="media" /><category term="physics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="war" /><category term="California" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Science is as much a visual practice as a textual or quantitative one. For centuries, scientists have used microscopes, telescopes, painting, illustration, printing, and photography to perceive nature and communicate what they see in it, often in collaboration with artists. In the twentieth century, scientists also came to view creativity as an essential resource and looked to art to foster it. Crossing Over is an interdisciplinary publication that looks at one prominent university—the California Institute of Technology (Caltech) in Pasadena—as a site for scientific and artistic image production. Uncovering the rich pictorial record embedded in its Archives and Special Collections, a team of visual culture scholars examines Caltech through a series of tightly focused case studies. How, the authors ask, have science and engineering institutions like Caltech used scientific representation, art, and architecture to construct themselves and produce discovery and invention? This book reveals new facets of life and work at Caltech that will be illuminating even to those familiar with the school, showcasing views that informed—and were informed by—the vibrant visual culture of Southern California. This volume was published to accompany an exhibition on view at the California Institute of Technology from September 27 to December 15, 2024. It is a finalist for the College Art Association’s 2026 Alfred H. Barr Jr. Award for Smaller Museums, Libraries, Collections, and Exhibitions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Passing in the Hallway: Art and Technology at Caltech, 1968–1972</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/passing-in-the-hallway/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Passing in the Hallway: Art and Technology at Caltech, 1968–1972" /><published>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/passing-in-the-hallway</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/passing-in-the-hallway/"><![CDATA[In 1969, Caltech converted seven rooms in its defunct Earhart Plant Research Laboratory into an art studio, hosting artists who worked in the media of plastics and computer animation. In the long 1960s, artists and scientists embraced each others’ professional practices, and universities created new centers for art and technology. Artists and scientists did not come to these new programs with the same motivations and expectations. Many artists were interested in synthesizing art with science and engineering, but most scientists and engineers who engaged in art were seeking a break from their technical work rather than a different mode of it, making genuine collaboration the exception rather than the rule.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="art" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="computing" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="media" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="California" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 1969, Caltech converted seven rooms in its defunct Earhart Plant Research Laboratory into an art studio, hosting artists who worked in the media of plastics and computer animation. In the long 1960s, artists and scientists embraced each others’ professional practices, and universities created new centers for art and technology. Artists and scientists did not come to these new programs with the same motivations and expectations. Many artists were interested in synthesizing art with science and engineering, but most scientists and engineers who engaged in art were seeking a break from their technical work rather than a different mode of it, making genuine collaboration the exception rather than the rule.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020</title><link href="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2024/crossing-over/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crossing Over: Art and Science at Caltech, 1920–2020" /><published>2024-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/exhibits/2024/crossing-over</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2024/crossing-over/"><![CDATA[*Crossing Over* was an expansive public exhibition that wove together the history of science with historical and contemporary art. How, it asked, have scientists and engineers used images and collaborated with artists to discover, invent, and communicate? How have artists been inspired by Caltech science? Spread across six sites at Caltech, the exhibition featured displays of over 200 objects, most drawn from the Caltech Archives and Special Collections, including rare books, paintings, drawings, photographs, scientific instruments, molecular models, and video.

September 27 – December 15, 2024]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="exhibits" /><category term="art" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="science" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="astronomy" /><category term="biology" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="geology" /><category term="physics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="technology" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Crossing Over was an expansive public exhibition that wove together the history of science with historical and contemporary art. How, it asked, have scientists and engineers used images and collaborated with artists to discover, invent, and communicate? How have artists been inspired by Caltech science? Spread across six sites at Caltech, the exhibition featured displays of over 200 objects, most drawn from the Caltech Archives and Special Collections, including rare books, paintings, drawings, photographs, scientific instruments, molecular models, and video. September 27 – December 15, 2024]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Video Is as Powerful as LSD”: Electronics and Psychedelics as Technologies of Consciousness</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2023/video-is-as-powerful-as-lsd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Video Is as Powerful as LSD”: Electronics and Psychedelics as Technologies of Consciousness" /><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2023/video-is-as-powerful-as-lsd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2023/video-is-as-powerful-as-lsd/"><![CDATA[<p>In the middle of the twentieth century, the invention and availability of new psychedelic drugs, and the growing cultural discourse around them, coincided with those of television, videotape, and computing. The technologies of psychedelics and electronics grew up together, and those using or thinking about one often implicated the other. When Sony and other Japanese manufacturers developed new portable videotape recorders in the late 1960s, for example, new communities of artists and tinkerers emerged around them, first in the US and Canada and then in Europe, Asia, North Africa, and Latin America. For the first time, declared these enthusiasts, many people could make their own television, breaking the broadcast oligopoly. In describing the psychological and sociological implications of this new technology, many compared it to psychedelic drugs.<p>

<p class="translation">A mediados del siglo XX, la invención y disponibilidad de nuevas drogas psicodélicas, y el creciente discurso cultural en torno a ellas, coincidieron con los de la televisión, las cintas de vídeo y la informática. Las tecnologías psicodélicas y la electrónica crecieron juntas, y quienes usaban o pensaban en una a menudo implicaban a la otra. Cuando Sony y otros fabricantes japoneses desarrollaron nuevos magnetoscopios portátiles a finales de los años sesenta, por ejemplo, surgieron nuevas comunidades de artistas a su alrededor, primero en Estados Unidos y Canadá, y después en Europa, Asia, el norte de África y América Latina. Por primera vez, declararon estos entusiastas, mucha gente podía hacer su propia televisión, rompiendo el oligopolio de la radiodifusión.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="art" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the middle of the twentieth century, the invention and availability of new psychedelic drugs, and the growing cultural discourse around them, coincided with those of television, videotape, and computing. The technologies of psychedelics and electronics grew up together, and those using or thinking about one often implicated the other. When Sony and other Japanese manufacturers developed new portable videotape recorders in the late 1960s, for example, new communities of artists and tinkerers emerged around them, first in the US and Canada and then in Europe, Asia, North Africa, and Latin America. For the first time, declared these enthusiasts, many people could make their own television, breaking the broadcast oligopoly. In describing the psychological and sociological implications of this new technology, many compared it to psychedelic drugs. A mediados del siglo XX, la invención y disponibilidad de nuevas drogas psicodélicas, y el creciente discurso cultural en torno a ellas, coincidieron con los de la televisión, las cintas de vídeo y la informática. Las tecnologías psicodélicas y la electrónica crecieron juntas, y quienes usaban o pensaban en una a menudo implicaban a la otra. Cuando Sony y otros fabricantes japoneses desarrollaron nuevos magnetoscopios portátiles a finales de los años sesenta, por ejemplo, surgieron nuevas comunidades de artistas a su alrededor, primero en Estados Unidos y Canadá, y después en Europa, Asia, el norte de África y América Latina. Por primera vez, declararon estos entusiastas, mucha gente podía hacer su propia televisión, rompiendo el oligopolio de la radiodifusión.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behind the Book: Escape from Earth</title><link href="https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behind the Book: Escape from Earth" /><published>2022-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="communism" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Iterating Infrastructure from High Volts to X-Rays to Nuclear Physics: Early Caltech Science in the Archives</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2022/iterating-infrastructure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Iterating Infrastructure from High Volts to X-Rays to Nuclear Physics: Early Caltech Science in the Archives" /><published>2022-01-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-01-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2022/iterating-infrastructure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2022/iterating-infrastructure/"><![CDATA[In the 1920s and 1930s, Caltech iteratively developed infrastructure for research on high-voltage electricity, x-rays, and nuclear physics. In 1923, the Institute built the High Voltage Research Laboratory, now the Ronald and Maxine Lind Hall of Mathematics and Physics, with funding from Southern California Edison, which used the unique million-volt high-bay research facility to test high-voltage transmission equipment. Among Caltech's faculty, electrical engineer Royal Sorensen invented the cascade transformer for the facility, and physicist Robert Millikan planned to use its power to dismantle the atom and achieve the alchemists' dream of transmutation of matter. Instead, though, Millikan's student Charles Lauritsen made High Volts a key site for high-voltage x-ray research, including on the uses of radiation therapy for cancer, bringing medical physics to Caltech in the early 1930s. Lauritsen and his students in turn modified their x-ray tubes to conduct research in nuclear physics, realizing Millikan's vision of deconstructing the atom. These three research programs built on each other, repurposing apparatus and thus ultimately the resources of the electricity industry to develop experimental physics in new directions. In this talk, I will use this early history of Caltech physics to think about both how research programs are shaped by the material resources of earlier projects and what we can learn from the collections of the Caltech Archives.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="physics" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="technology" /><category term="science" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the 1920s and 1930s, Caltech iteratively developed infrastructure for research on high-voltage electricity, x-rays, and nuclear physics. In 1923, the Institute built the High Voltage Research Laboratory, now the Ronald and Maxine Lind Hall of Mathematics and Physics, with funding from Southern California Edison, which used the unique million-volt high-bay research facility to test high-voltage transmission equipment. Among Caltech’s faculty, electrical engineer Royal Sorensen invented the cascade transformer for the facility, and physicist Robert Millikan planned to use its power to dismantle the atom and achieve the alchemists’ dream of transmutation of matter. Instead, though, Millikan’s student Charles Lauritsen made High Volts a key site for high-voltage x-ray research, including on the uses of radiation therapy for cancer, bringing medical physics to Caltech in the early 1930s. Lauritsen and his students in turn modified their x-ray tubes to conduct research in nuclear physics, realizing Millikan’s vision of deconstructing the atom. These three research programs built on each other, repurposing apparatus and thus ultimately the resources of the electricity industry to develop experimental physics in new directions. In this talk, I will use this early history of Caltech physics to think about both how research programs are shaped by the material resources of earlier projects and what we can learn from the collections of the Caltech Archives.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Art Do Work</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Art Do Work" /><published>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work/"><![CDATA[In <cite>Making Art Work</cite>, W. Patrick McCray asks why and how American artists and engineers collaborated to produce technological art in the 1960s and 1970s. In our current moment, so obviously marked by the American government’s failure to deploy scientific expertise against a pandemic, and by demonstrations against white supremacy and police brutality larger than those of the 1960s, this book also provokes additional questions. Of what did technological art make people aware? Could it in fact contribute to solving social problems like hunger, homelessness, and war? How did patriarchy and white supremacy shape this art and the awareness it produced? What roles did women and people of color play in constructing and contesting it? Although none of these questions is at the center of McCray’s book, he points toward some of the answers.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="politics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="technopolitics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Making Art Work, W. Patrick McCray asks why and how American artists and engineers collaborated to produce technological art in the 1960s and 1970s. In our current moment, so obviously marked by the American government’s failure to deploy scientific expertise against a pandemic, and by demonstrations against white supremacy and police brutality larger than those of the 1960s, this book also provokes additional questions. Of what did technological art make people aware? Could it in fact contribute to solving social problems like hunger, homelessness, and war? How did patriarchy and white supremacy shape this art and the awareness it produced? What roles did women and people of color play in constructing and contesting it? Although none of these questions is at the center of McCray’s book, he points toward some of the answers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Caltech’s House of Lightning</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/house-of-lightning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Caltech’s House of Lightning" /><published>2020-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/house-of-lightning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/house-of-lightning/"><![CDATA[In 1923, Caltech and Southern California Edison Company built the High Voltage Research Laboratory to test high-voltage equipment and conduct research in physics and electrical engineering. Designed by architect Bertram Goodhue, with sculpture by Lee Lawrie, it became home to electrical demonstrations and research on x-rays and nuclear physics.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="physics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 1923, Caltech and Southern California Edison Company built the High Voltage Research Laboratory to test high-voltage equipment and conduct research in physics and electrical engineering. Designed by architect Bertram Goodhue, with sculpture by Lee Lawrie, it became home to electrical demonstrations and research on x-rays and nuclear physics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed.

Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite>, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite> is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="computing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="fascism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed. Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, IBM and the Holocaust, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, IBM and the Holocaust is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ready, Set, Spark</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/ready-set-spark/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ready, Set, Spark" /><published>2020-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/ready-set-spark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/ready-set-spark/"><![CDATA[When Caltech's former Sloan Lab reopened in January 2019 as the Linde Hall of Mathematics and Physics, staff, faculty, and students encountered a structure with a transformed interior that was originally built 97 years ago. Over the course of a century, it has witnessed many changes, evolving to suit the needs of the disciplines it has served: physics, mathematics, and electrical engineering. In its earliest years, the building was known by several names, including Edison High Tension Laboratory and High Voltage Research Laboratory, but was generally referred to as High Volts. It came into being out of a partnership between Caltech and the Southern California Edison (SCE) company, which contributed money to its construction in exchange for use of it for research. SCE had recently decided to change its transmission lines from 150,000 to 220,000 volts. The lines and associated equipment would need to be able to withstand a massive surge if they were struck by lightning, so SCE wanted to conduct research at a million volts, a higher voltage than could be reliably produced by any existing American laboratory.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="science" /><category term="physics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When Caltech’s former Sloan Lab reopened in January 2019 as the Linde Hall of Mathematics and Physics, staff, faculty, and students encountered a structure with a transformed interior that was originally built 97 years ago. Over the course of a century, it has witnessed many changes, evolving to suit the needs of the disciplines it has served: physics, mathematics, and electrical engineering. In its earliest years, the building was known by several names, including Edison High Tension Laboratory and High Voltage Research Laboratory, but was generally referred to as High Volts. It came into being out of a partnership between Caltech and the Southern California Edison (SCE) company, which contributed money to its construction in exchange for use of it for research. SCE had recently decided to change its transmission lines from 150,000 to 220,000 volts. The lines and associated equipment would need to be able to withstand a massive surge if they were struck by lightning, so SCE wanted to conduct research at a million volts, a higher voltage than could be reliably produced by any existing American laboratory.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From High Volts to High Energy Physics</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/from-high-volts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From High Volts to High Energy Physics" /><published>2020-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/from-high-volts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/from-high-volts/"><![CDATA[Last year, Caltech rededicated a building on its campus following a major renovation. The Alfred P. Sloan Laboratory for Mathematics and Physics became the Ronald and Maxine Linde Hall of Mathematics and Physics. Linde Hall occupies a structure which is now 97 years old and has evolved over that time with the disciplines of physics, mathematics, and electrical engineering.

The building, constructed in 1923, originally had a few names, including Edison High Tension Laboratory, High Voltage Research Laboratory, and High Potential Research Laboratory, but was generally referred to as High Volts. It was the fifth permanent building constructed on Caltech’s campus, after Throop Hall, Gates Laboratory of Chemistry, Culbertson Auditorium, and the Norman Bridge Laboratory of Physics.

Astrophysicist George Ellery Hale, as a Caltech trustee, conceived of the laboratory as part of a strategy of persuading experimentalist Robert Millikan to come to Caltech. Millikan was tortured—his word, not mine—by his decision of whether to come to Caltech or stay at the University of Chicago. Hale’s fellow trustees Henry M. Robinson and Arthur Fleming—both of whom became namesakes of buildings on campus—were also on the board of directors of the local electric company, Southern California Edison.

Hale proposed to them that if the Edison Company bought Caltech a new laboratory, both parties would benefit: “I believe the Company would get its money back in the form of new information regarding insulation and other problems connected with high voltage lines, not to speak of the advertising value.” He was right: The company's interest came from a decision they made around 1920 to change their transmission lines from 150,000 to 220,000 volts. Such lines and associated insulators, transformers, circuit breakers, and other equipment would need to be able to withstand a massive surge if they were struck by lightning, so the Edison Company wanted to conduct research at a million volts, a higher voltage than could be reliably produced by any existing American laboratory. The lab cost $139,915, of which Edison paid $105,000.

The design of High Volts was also a collaboration. Millikan provided specifications, including a requirement that the building have ventilation to allow ozone to escape but also not let in light. The interior was dominated by a single large industrial space packed with high-voltage apparatus, including two key pieces of million-volt equipment. A million-volt surge generator produced rapid impulses of artificial lightning. In addition, Royal Sorensen, who founded electrical engineering at Caltech when he was hired in 1910, invented the cascade transformer in 1922 (an innovation which was simultaneously made by others in Germany) and designed a million-volt model, composed of four 250,000 volt transformers built by Westinghouse which each weighed 22 tons, for High Volts; it stepped an externally-supplied 15,000 volts up to a million volts of continuous current. Edison engineers designed a steel frame, the second constructed in Pasadena, and prominent architect Bertram Goodhue designed the exterior, which used a diamond pattern to provide texture in the absence of windows. The similarly prominent architectural sculptor Lee Lawrie produced a relief over the entry which conveyed the high voltage research performed within.

Sorensen regularly gave a public lecture and demonstration on high voltage electricity, with the latter portion taking place in High Volts. “It proved to have its usual strong draw this year when, on a rainy Friday evening, almost 1000 people stormed East Bridge,” reported *Engineering and Science*, Caltech’s research magazine, in 1949. “Prof. Sorensen obligingly gave his lecture twice, and the lab ran off three demonstrations, while a special police detail coped with the crush.”

In [his oral history](http://resolver.caltech.edu/CaltechOH:OH_Roberts_J), Caltech chemistry professor John Roberts recalls visiting Caltech as a teenager for these demonstrations:

>The High Voltage Lab was a fabulous attraction. What is now the Sloan building then had no windows in it. It was deep down inside—just a great big basement-like room with no upper floors. And they had these big girders up at the top. The floor of this room was filled with all kinds of electrical equipment—enormous transformers, and condensers, and so on, big swooping insulators. It looked like Frankenstein’s laboratory. Great transformers topped with big mushroom rings, you know, they used to shoot sparks off of.… They’d have a “horn gap,” where a pair of wires would be close together at the top of the transformer and far apart at the top of the room. They would start an arc at the bottom and it would grow in length and rise to the ceiling. That was really impressive to watch as the arcs got up to the ceiling, and then crack, and disappear. They’d make this crackling noise as they’d go up. And then they’d charge up the condensers and shoot off big sparks, and blow up some blocks of wood, and stuff like that.

According to the February 1949 issue of *Engineering and Science*, “these facilities have been used to aid Southern California Edison in the development of high voltage transmission lines, to furnish lightning protection of oil storage tanks for the oil industry, to test insulators for numerous utility companies.” The transmission lines tested at High Volts made it possible to transmit electricity to Southern California from the Hoover Dam in Nevada. Among the significant inventions of the lab was a vacuum switch designed by Sorensen and Millikan which was manufactured for aircraft and other industries.

Going back to 1921, though, as Hale saw it in his letter to his fellow trustees, though, High Volts would have an entirely different benefit for the physicist he was trying to recruit. “Millikan,” he wrote, “would also have the advantage of using enormous voltage to bust up some of his atoms. This possibility, which no other laboratory could match, is what excites him.… When a man gets on the trail of the philosopher's stone, even if he isn't after gold, you can accomplish a great deal by offering it to him!”

Millikan's interest did indeed come from his interest in taking apart atoms and discovering what they were made of. He was also seeking, as Hale's reference to the philosopher's stone suggests, to transmute matter from one element to another by reconstructing the nucleus. In 1904, Millikan had already written that “the dreams of the ancient alchemists are true, for the radioactive elements all appear to be slowly but spontaneously transmuting themselves into other elements.” In 1912, he believed he and his student George Winchester produced hydrogen ions from aluminum using high-voltage electricity. In 1919, Ernest Rutherford persuaded more physicists that he had caused nitrogen atoms to eject protons by bombarding them with alpha particles. Several scientists claimed they had turned various metals into gold in the 1920s using electricity—it was a renaissance of alchemy.

Although Millikan submitted a grant proposal for support for this research in 1921, and although he, Hale, and Caltech as an institution occasionally referred to the High Voltage Laboratory as intended for investigations inside the atom, Millikan never published the results of his efforts to transmute matter at Caltech, nor can evidence of it be found in his surviving laboratory notebooks. In his article on the subject, historian Robert Kargon, suggests that “these efforts may have in fact been made but were unsuccessful,” adding that Millikan “preferred to bury quietly unfruitful enterprises; he position as fundraiser for an exciting new research center made such unpublicized interment a practical necessity.” Ultimately, then, the new lab would find other uses.

Charles Lauritsen, who received his PhD from Caltech in 1929 and remained here for the rest of his career, made High Volts a key site for high-voltage X-ray research, building the first million-volt X-ray tube there in about 1930. Lauritsen soon became interested in the medical applications of this device, writing in his patent application that “radiations substantially the frequency of the gamma radiation from radium may be obtained from the tube” and that “such tubes can therefore be employed as the full equivalent of radium in the treatment of disease, or for therapeutic purposes.”

Although Caltech biologists steered clear of medical applications at this time, its physicists did not. Millikan enlisted local physician Seeley G. Mudd, whose mother was already donating a geology building to the Institute in memory of his father, mining tycoon Seeley W. Mudd. That building is now typically called North Mudd, as the younger Mudd later donated an associated building named after himself as well, South Mudd. I for one didn't realize until I was preparing this talk that the two buildings are named after two different men.

To return to our story, Millikan enlisted the younger Mudd in a partnership researching the therapeutic effects of Lauritsen's million-volt x-ray tube compared to lower voltage radiation already available in hospitals, and the Los Angeles County General Hospital began to bring cancer patients to High Volts for radiation therapy. Although he was independently wealthy and didn't receive a salary, and indeed donated money as well as his time to the project, Caltech appointed Mudd became Research Associate in Radiation, and later, in 1935, Professor of X-Ray Therapy. Physician Clyde Emery was made Assistant Professor of X-Ray Therapy at the same time. Caltech's medical physics research was so active that it became one of the main reasons for the Institute to construct a new building, Kellogg Radiation Laboratory, in 1932.

Meanwhile, Lauritsen’s students, funded by their work maintaining x-ray tubes for radiation therapy, began modifying High Volts equipment for nuclear physics, making Millikan's vision of deconstructing the atom there a reality; H. Richard Crane, for example, produced neutrons by ion beam for the first time in the early 1930s. “The transmutation of the elements, now an accomplished fact,” wrote Millikan to their funder, W. K. Kellogg, “plus artificial radioactivity, plus neutron beams—all three effects producible by Lauritsen tubes—plus the manifold uses of ultra-short wireless waves, therapeutic and otherwise, open up endless opportunities.”

As with many research programs, radiation therapy came to an end at Caltech when funders—not only Kellogg but also the National Academy of Sciences’ National Cancer Advisory Council and the Childs Foundation, decided to stop funding it. In the early 1940s, Kellogg was dramatically repurposed for research on rocketry as the US prepared to enter World War II.

High Volts retained its unusual, single-room architecture until 1960, when Caltech renovated it into the Alfred P. Sloan Laboratory of Mathematics and Physics, producing a more conventional internal structure, with windows and five floors of space, including new basements, rather than a single large room. By this point, it had had a storied career contributing to electrical engineering, nuclear physics, radiation therapy, spectacular public demonstrations, and even science we might call alchemy.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="physics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="science" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last year, Caltech rededicated a building on its campus following a major renovation. The Alfred P. Sloan Laboratory for Mathematics and Physics became the Ronald and Maxine Linde Hall of Mathematics and Physics. Linde Hall occupies a structure which is now 97 years old and has evolved over that time with the disciplines of physics, mathematics, and electrical engineering. The building, constructed in 1923, originally had a few names, including Edison High Tension Laboratory, High Voltage Research Laboratory, and High Potential Research Laboratory, but was generally referred to as High Volts. It was the fifth permanent building constructed on Caltech’s campus, after Throop Hall, Gates Laboratory of Chemistry, Culbertson Auditorium, and the Norman Bridge Laboratory of Physics. Astrophysicist George Ellery Hale, as a Caltech trustee, conceived of the laboratory as part of a strategy of persuading experimentalist Robert Millikan to come to Caltech. Millikan was tortured—his word, not mine—by his decision of whether to come to Caltech or stay at the University of Chicago. Hale’s fellow trustees Henry M. Robinson and Arthur Fleming—both of whom became namesakes of buildings on campus—were also on the board of directors of the local electric company, Southern California Edison. Hale proposed to them that if the Edison Company bought Caltech a new laboratory, both parties would benefit: “I believe the Company would get its money back in the form of new information regarding insulation and other problems connected with high voltage lines, not to speak of the advertising value.” He was right: The company’s interest came from a decision they made around 1920 to change their transmission lines from 150,000 to 220,000 volts. Such lines and associated insulators, transformers, circuit breakers, and other equipment would need to be able to withstand a massive surge if they were struck by lightning, so the Edison Company wanted to conduct research at a million volts, a higher voltage than could be reliably produced by any existing American laboratory. The lab cost $139,915, of which Edison paid $105,000. The design of High Volts was also a collaboration. Millikan provided specifications, including a requirement that the building have ventilation to allow ozone to escape but also not let in light. The interior was dominated by a single large industrial space packed with high-voltage apparatus, including two key pieces of million-volt equipment. A million-volt surge generator produced rapid impulses of artificial lightning. In addition, Royal Sorensen, who founded electrical engineering at Caltech when he was hired in 1910, invented the cascade transformer in 1922 (an innovation which was simultaneously made by others in Germany) and designed a million-volt model, composed of four 250,000 volt transformers built by Westinghouse which each weighed 22 tons, for High Volts; it stepped an externally-supplied 15,000 volts up to a million volts of continuous current. Edison engineers designed a steel frame, the second constructed in Pasadena, and prominent architect Bertram Goodhue designed the exterior, which used a diamond pattern to provide texture in the absence of windows. The similarly prominent architectural sculptor Lee Lawrie produced a relief over the entry which conveyed the high voltage research performed within. Sorensen regularly gave a public lecture and demonstration on high voltage electricity, with the latter portion taking place in High Volts. “It proved to have its usual strong draw this year when, on a rainy Friday evening, almost 1000 people stormed East Bridge,” reported Engineering and Science, Caltech’s research magazine, in 1949. “Prof. Sorensen obligingly gave his lecture twice, and the lab ran off three demonstrations, while a special police detail coped with the crush.” In his oral history, Caltech chemistry professor John Roberts recalls visiting Caltech as a teenager for these demonstrations: The High Voltage Lab was a fabulous attraction. What is now the Sloan building then had no windows in it. It was deep down inside—just a great big basement-like room with no upper floors. And they had these big girders up at the top. The floor of this room was filled with all kinds of electrical equipment—enormous transformers, and condensers, and so on, big swooping insulators. It looked like Frankenstein’s laboratory. Great transformers topped with big mushroom rings, you know, they used to shoot sparks off of.… They’d have a “horn gap,” where a pair of wires would be close together at the top of the transformer and far apart at the top of the room. They would start an arc at the bottom and it would grow in length and rise to the ceiling. That was really impressive to watch as the arcs got up to the ceiling, and then crack, and disappear. They’d make this crackling noise as they’d go up. And then they’d charge up the condensers and shoot off big sparks, and blow up some blocks of wood, and stuff like that. According to the February 1949 issue of Engineering and Science, “these facilities have been used to aid Southern California Edison in the development of high voltage transmission lines, to furnish lightning protection of oil storage tanks for the oil industry, to test insulators for numerous utility companies.” The transmission lines tested at High Volts made it possible to transmit electricity to Southern California from the Hoover Dam in Nevada. Among the significant inventions of the lab was a vacuum switch designed by Sorensen and Millikan which was manufactured for aircraft and other industries. Going back to 1921, though, as Hale saw it in his letter to his fellow trustees, though, High Volts would have an entirely different benefit for the physicist he was trying to recruit. “Millikan,” he wrote, “would also have the advantage of using enormous voltage to bust up some of his atoms. This possibility, which no other laboratory could match, is what excites him.… When a man gets on the trail of the philosopher’s stone, even if he isn’t after gold, you can accomplish a great deal by offering it to him!” Millikan’s interest did indeed come from his interest in taking apart atoms and discovering what they were made of. He was also seeking, as Hale’s reference to the philosopher’s stone suggests, to transmute matter from one element to another by reconstructing the nucleus. In 1904, Millikan had already written that “the dreams of the ancient alchemists are true, for the radioactive elements all appear to be slowly but spontaneously transmuting themselves into other elements.” In 1912, he believed he and his student George Winchester produced hydrogen ions from aluminum using high-voltage electricity. In 1919, Ernest Rutherford persuaded more physicists that he had caused nitrogen atoms to eject protons by bombarding them with alpha particles. Several scientists claimed they had turned various metals into gold in the 1920s using electricity—it was a renaissance of alchemy. Although Millikan submitted a grant proposal for support for this research in 1921, and although he, Hale, and Caltech as an institution occasionally referred to the High Voltage Laboratory as intended for investigations inside the atom, Millikan never published the results of his efforts to transmute matter at Caltech, nor can evidence of it be found in his surviving laboratory notebooks. In his article on the subject, historian Robert Kargon, suggests that “these efforts may have in fact been made but were unsuccessful,” adding that Millikan “preferred to bury quietly unfruitful enterprises; he position as fundraiser for an exciting new research center made such unpublicized interment a practical necessity.” Ultimately, then, the new lab would find other uses. Charles Lauritsen, who received his PhD from Caltech in 1929 and remained here for the rest of his career, made High Volts a key site for high-voltage X-ray research, building the first million-volt X-ray tube there in about 1930. Lauritsen soon became interested in the medical applications of this device, writing in his patent application that “radiations substantially the frequency of the gamma radiation from radium may be obtained from the tube” and that “such tubes can therefore be employed as the full equivalent of radium in the treatment of disease, or for therapeutic purposes.” Although Caltech biologists steered clear of medical applications at this time, its physicists did not. Millikan enlisted local physician Seeley G. Mudd, whose mother was already donating a geology building to the Institute in memory of his father, mining tycoon Seeley W. Mudd. That building is now typically called North Mudd, as the younger Mudd later donated an associated building named after himself as well, South Mudd. I for one didn’t realize until I was preparing this talk that the two buildings are named after two different men. To return to our story, Millikan enlisted the younger Mudd in a partnership researching the therapeutic effects of Lauritsen’s million-volt x-ray tube compared to lower voltage radiation already available in hospitals, and the Los Angeles County General Hospital began to bring cancer patients to High Volts for radiation therapy. Although he was independently wealthy and didn’t receive a salary, and indeed donated money as well as his time to the project, Caltech appointed Mudd became Research Associate in Radiation, and later, in 1935, Professor of X-Ray Therapy. Physician Clyde Emery was made Assistant Professor of X-Ray Therapy at the same time. Caltech’s medical physics research was so active that it became one of the main reasons for the Institute to construct a new building, Kellogg Radiation Laboratory, in 1932. Meanwhile, Lauritsen’s students, funded by their work maintaining x-ray tubes for radiation therapy, began modifying High Volts equipment for nuclear physics, making Millikan’s vision of deconstructing the atom there a reality; H. Richard Crane, for example, produced neutrons by ion beam for the first time in the early 1930s. “The transmutation of the elements, now an accomplished fact,” wrote Millikan to their funder, W. K. Kellogg, “plus artificial radioactivity, plus neutron beams—all three effects producible by Lauritsen tubes—plus the manifold uses of ultra-short wireless waves, therapeutic and otherwise, open up endless opportunities.” As with many research programs, radiation therapy came to an end at Caltech when funders—not only Kellogg but also the National Academy of Sciences’ National Cancer Advisory Council and the Childs Foundation, decided to stop funding it. In the early 1940s, Kellogg was dramatically repurposed for research on rocketry as the US prepared to enter World War II. High Volts retained its unusual, single-room architecture until 1960, when Caltech renovated it into the Alfred P. Sloan Laboratory of Mathematics and Physics, producing a more conventional internal structure, with windows and five floors of space, including new basements, rather than a single large room. By this point, it had had a storied career contributing to electrical engineering, nuclear physics, radiation therapy, spectacular public demonstrations, and even science we might call alchemy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Becoming Caltech, 1910–1930: Presentations from the Archives</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/becoming-caltech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Becoming Caltech, 1910–1930: Presentations from the Archives" /><published>2020-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/becoming-caltech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/becoming-caltech/"><![CDATA[A century ago, a small institution called Throop Polytechnic Institute dramatically reinvented itself, transforming from a manual arts academy to an engineering school, then expanding into a research institute. In 1920, it became the California Institute of Technology. In summer 2020, Caltech archivists gave a series of livestreamed presentations on the science, engineering, architecture, and community life of early Caltech.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="geology" /><category term="chemistry" /><category term="physics" /><category term="biology" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="education" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A century ago, a small institution called Throop Polytechnic Institute dramatically reinvented itself, transforming from a manual arts academy to an engineering school, then expanding into a research institute. In 1920, it became the California Institute of Technology. In summer 2020, Caltech archivists gave a series of livestreamed presentations on the science, engineering, architecture, and community life of early Caltech.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Becoming Caltech: Building a Research Community, 1910–1930</title><link href="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2020/becoming-caltech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Becoming Caltech: Building a Research Community, 1910–1930" /><published>2020-02-10T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/exhibits/2020/becoming-caltech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/exhibits/2020/becoming-caltech/"><![CDATA[In the 1910s and 1920s, Caltech dramatically reinvented itself, transforming from a manual arts academy to an engineering school, then expanding into a research institute. The school began building its current campus, recruited renowned faculty, constructed sophisticated laboratories, trained students to become leading researchers, and established new relationships with industry and government. On February 10, 1920, the Institute’s trustees acknowledged this transformation by changing the institution’s name from Throop College of Technology to California Institute of Technology.

A century later, the Caltech Archives presents the exhibition “Becoming Caltech: Building a Research Community, 1910–1930.” It tells the story of Caltech's early growth through historical documents, objects, photographs, and film, organized into three sections. “Becoming” traces Caltech's evolution through the reformation instigated by George Ellery Hale and catalyzed by World War I. “Building Research” chronicles both the history of science, engineering, and the humanities at Caltech—ranging from the core activities of the 1910s (electrical engineering, chemistry, and physics) to the new fields of the 1920s (genetics, seismology, and aeronautics)—and the architecture and construction of the buildings which housed this research. “Community” explores the lives and culture of the students, faculty, and staff who made up the Institute, including athletics, clubs, the Athenaeum, and the big T that students carved out of the forest on the side of Mt. Wilson.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="exhibits" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="laboratories" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="education" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the 1910s and 1920s, Caltech dramatically reinvented itself, transforming from a manual arts academy to an engineering school, then expanding into a research institute. The school began building its current campus, recruited renowned faculty, constructed sophisticated laboratories, trained students to become leading researchers, and established new relationships with industry and government. On February 10, 1920, the Institute’s trustees acknowledged this transformation by changing the institution’s name from Throop College of Technology to California Institute of Technology. A century later, the Caltech Archives presents the exhibition “Becoming Caltech: Building a Research Community, 1910–1930.” It tells the story of Caltech’s early growth through historical documents, objects, photographs, and film, organized into three sections. “Becoming” traces Caltech’s evolution through the reformation instigated by George Ellery Hale and catalyzed by World War I. “Building Research” chronicles both the history of science, engineering, and the humanities at Caltech—ranging from the core activities of the 1910s (electrical engineering, chemistry, and physics) to the new fields of the 1920s (genetics, seismology, and aeronautics)—and the architecture and construction of the buildings which housed this research. “Community” explores the lives and culture of the students, faculty, and staff who made up the Institute, including athletics, clubs, the Athenaeum, and the big T that students carved out of the forest on the side of Mt. Wilson.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cybernetics Moment, or Why We Call Our Age the Information Age</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/cybernetics-moment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cybernetics Moment, or Why We Call Our Age the Information Age" /><published>2019-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2019/cybernetics-moment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/cybernetics-moment/"><![CDATA[The historical literature on cybernetics has ballooned in the last 15 years, as scholars have sought to understand how scientists and engineers studying “control and communication in the animal and the machine” (as Norbert Weiner subtitled his book <cite>Cybernetics</cite>) contributed to Soviet and Chilean computer networks, assistive technologies for the deaf, theories of schizophrenia, and experimental music and cinema, to name just a few of their projects. This range of topics raises anew the question—central to historians’ accounts since the early 1990s—of what exactly cybernetics was. As the first book to integrate the many dimensions of cybernetics into a single narrative, <cite>The Cybernetics Moment</cite> presents a new answer to this crucial question.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="computing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The historical literature on cybernetics has ballooned in the last 15 years, as scholars have sought to understand how scientists and engineers studying “control and communication in the animal and the machine” (as Norbert Weiner subtitled his book Cybernetics) contributed to Soviet and Chilean computer networks, assistive technologies for the deaf, theories of schizophrenia, and experimental music and cinema, to name just a few of their projects. This range of topics raises anew the question—central to historians’ accounts since the early 1990s—of what exactly cybernetics was. As the first book to integrate the many dimensions of cybernetics into a single narrative, The Cybernetics Moment presents a new answer to this crucial question.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">La vidéo et les origines de la photographie électronique</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/photographie-electronique/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La vidéo et les origines de la photographie électronique" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2019/photographie-electronique</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/photographie-electronique/"><![CDATA[<p class="translation">Dans notre imaginaire historique, la récente révolution numérique de la photographie a tendance à occulter une révolution antérieure qui fut moins totale mais plus profonde : la révolution analogique, c’est-à-dire la traduction d’images en signaux électriques et en champs magnétiques variant de façon continue. La photographie analogique électronique a pris la forme de la télévision et de la vidéo, mais aussi de techniques d’enregistrement d’images fixes (par exemple le Videofile d’Ampex dans les années 1960 ; le Mavica de Sony dans les années 1980). Les principaux composants de ces nouvelles technologies, notamment ceux utilisés par les procédés d’enregistrement haute-fidélité et les tubes à vide pour les caméras vidéo, ont d’abord été mis au point à des fins militaires. L’électronique analogique partageait ces éléments et beaucoup d’autres – notamment les supports physiques d’enregistrement – avec les technologies numériques. Peter Sachs Collopy nous montre donc que ce n’est pas la numérisation qui a radicalement transformé la photographie au siècle dernier, mais bien le remplacement de la photochimie par des supports électromagnétiques, à la fois analogiques et numériques.</p>

<p>Our current association of the digital with progress can distract us from the historical fact that the most sophisticated electronic technologies have often been analog ones, processing information as continuous variations in voltage or current and recording it as continuous variations in magnetic fields. The discourse of the digital can also obscure continuities between electronic media, preventing us from seeing how much analog and digital modes of representing information have in common. Rather than thinking of the recent decline of film as a process of digitization, we might just as productively see it as a culmination of the rise of electronic photography, a phenomenon that has introduced into our visual experience not only the digital but also the analog.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dans notre imaginaire historique, la récente révolution numérique de la photographie a tendance à occulter une révolution antérieure qui fut moins totale mais plus profonde : la révolution analogique, c’est-à-dire la traduction d’images en signaux électriques et en champs magnétiques variant de façon continue. La photographie analogique électronique a pris la forme de la télévision et de la vidéo, mais aussi de techniques d’enregistrement d’images fixes (par exemple le Videofile d’Ampex dans les années 1960 ; le Mavica de Sony dans les années 1980). Les principaux composants de ces nouvelles technologies, notamment ceux utilisés par les procédés d’enregistrement haute-fidélité et les tubes à vide pour les caméras vidéo, ont d’abord été mis au point à des fins militaires. L’électronique analogique partageait ces éléments et beaucoup d’autres – notamment les supports physiques d’enregistrement – avec les technologies numériques. Peter Sachs Collopy nous montre donc que ce n’est pas la numérisation qui a radicalement transformé la photographie au siècle dernier, mais bien le remplacement de la photochimie par des supports électromagnétiques, à la fois analogiques et numériques. Our current association of the digital with progress can distract us from the historical fact that the most sophisticated electronic technologies have often been analog ones, processing information as continuous variations in voltage or current and recording it as continuous variations in magnetic fields. The discourse of the digital can also obscure continuities between electronic media, preventing us from seeing how much analog and digital modes of representing information have in common. Rather than thinking of the recent decline of film as a process of digitization, we might just as productively see it as a culmination of the rise of electronic photography, a phenomenon that has introduced into our visual experience not only the digital but also the analog.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Portable Moving Images: A Media History of Storage Formats</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/portable-moving-images/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portable Moving Images: A Media History of Storage Formats" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2019/portable-moving-images</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2019/portable-moving-images/"><![CDATA[Although Ricardo Cedeño Montaña does not frame his project as such, <cite>Portable Moving Images</cite> is perhaps the most ambitious contribution yet to the “format theory” and “general history of compression” proposed by Jonathan Sterne in his <cite>MP3: The Meaning of a Format</cite>. <cite>Portable Moving Images</cite> is an expansive but sometimes frustrating history of the successive “reductions” that transformed first film, then analog video, and finally digital video from complex technologies for professional media production to ubiquitous tools used by amateurs. In each process, Montaña argues, cameras and other equipment became not only smaller but also more automated; reduction in both mass and the complexity of operation facilitated widespread use of new formats. “Portable media,” he writes, “compress the media factory into takeaway apparatuses that are then poured into the streets.”]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="video" /><category term="computing" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Although Ricardo Cedeño Montaña does not frame his project as such, Portable Moving Images is perhaps the most ambitious contribution yet to the “format theory” and “general history of compression” proposed by Jonathan Sterne in his MP3: The Meaning of a Format. Portable Moving Images is an expansive but sometimes frustrating history of the successive “reductions” that transformed first film, then analog video, and finally digital video from complex technologies for professional media production to ubiquitous tools used by amateurs. In each process, Montaña argues, cameras and other equipment became not only smaller but also more automated; reduction in both mass and the complexity of operation facilitated widespread use of new formats. “Portable media,” he writes, “compress the media factory into takeaway apparatuses that are then poured into the streets.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Emergence of Video Processing Tools: Television Becoming Unglued</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/emergence-of-video-processing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Emergence of Video Processing Tools: Television Becoming Unglued" /><published>2015-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/emergence-of-video-processing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/emergence-of-video-processing/"><![CDATA[As artists gained access to the technologies of television production in the 1960s and 1970s, many began to build their own tools for electronically processing analog video signals to produce novel visual effects. For many artists, the construction and use of mixers, keyers, colorizers, and scan processors became the basis for aesthetic and critical engagements with electronic technologies, as well as collaboration with engineers. This expansive book consists of forty-three chapters by thirty-one authors—most of them artists or curators, many of them also participants in this history—on the people and machines that made up video processing in the United States.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="art" /><category term="video" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As artists gained access to the technologies of television production in the 1960s and 1970s, many began to build their own tools for electronically processing analog video signals to produce novel visual effects. For many artists, the construction and use of mixers, keyers, colorizers, and scan processors became the basis for aesthetic and critical engagements with electronic technologies, as well as collaboration with engineers. This expansive book consists of forty-three chapters by thirty-one authors—most of them artists or curators, many of them also participants in this history—on the people and machines that made up video processing in the United States.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="war" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="fascism" /><category term="New York" /><category term="California" /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Video Synthesizers: From Analog Computing to Digital Art</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2014/video-synthesizers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Video Synthesizers: From Analog Computing to Digital Art" /><published>2014-12-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2014-12-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2014/video-synthesizers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2014/video-synthesizers/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, artists and engineers began building increasingly sophisticated video synthesizers, machines that produced abstract or distorted images by electronically manipulating either a video signal or the cathode ray tube on which it was displayed. This article explores how experimental videographers modeled video synthesizers on audio synthesizers, conceptualized them as analog computers, and starting in 1973, interfaced them with digital minicomputers.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="computing" /><category term="video" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, artists and engineers began building increasingly sophisticated video synthesizers, machines that produced abstract or distorted images by electronically manipulating either a video signal or the cathode ray tube on which it was displayed. This article explores how experimental videographers modeled video synthesizers on audio synthesizers, conceptualized them as analog computers, and starting in 1973, interfaced them with digital minicomputers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technology and Society</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology and Society" /><published>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesday evenings, 6:00 to 9:00, from September 2 to December 9 in Williams Hall room 219. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Tuesdays from 5:00 to 6:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>
<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you <a href="reading">read and think about them</a> before each class meeting. Your engaged and insightful participation in discussions will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<p>The other assignments consist of three short papers, of approximately five pages each. I’ll provide more detailed prompts, but in short <a href="politics">the first paper</a> should present an argument about whether and how a particular technology “has politics,” <a href="observing">the second</a> should describe and analyze your observation of people using technology, and <a href="history">the third</a> should present a brief history of a technology of your choice. You will have an opportunity to submit a draft, get my feedback, and revise your paper before I grade it. Each paper will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>The following four books, which we’ll be reading cover-to-cover or nearly so, are available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> is also available online, and other readings will be available through links below.</p>
<ul id="books">
	<li>Lynn White, Jr., <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> (1962).</li>
	<li>Thomas J. Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet: Technology and Culture from the Renaissance to the Present</cite>, second edition (2011, revised from 2004 original).</li>
	<li>Ruth Schwartz Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother: The Ironies of Household Technology from the Open Hearth to the Microwave</cite> (1983).</li>
	<li>David Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old: Technology and Global History since 1900</cite> (2007).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Schedule</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>September 2: Introduction</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 9: Technologies of Feudalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Langdon Winner, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/20024652">Do Artifacts Have Politics?</a>” (1980).</li>
			<li>White, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite>, preface and chapters 1 and 2.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, preface and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 16: Roots of Capitalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lewis Mumford, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01149.0001.001">Technics and Civilization</a></cite> (1934), objectives and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Cynthia Cockburn, <cite>Machinery of Dominance: Women, Men, and Technical Know-How</cite> (1985), introduction and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 2.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 23: Print Culture</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Marshall McLuhan, <cite>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</cite> (1964), chapters 1, 16, and 18.</li>
			<li>Elizabeth Eisenstein, <cite>The Printing Revolution in Early Modern Europe</cite>, second edition (2005, abridged from <cite>The Printing Press as an Agent of Change: Communications and Cultural Transformations in Early-Modern Europe</cite>, 1979), introduction and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li>Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar, <cite>Laboratory Life: The Construction of Scientific Facts</cite>, second edition (1986, revised from 1979 original), pages 43–53.</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule" style="page-break-before: always">
		<h4>September 30: The Industrialization of Manufacturing</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 3.</li>
			<li>Walter Licht, <cite>Industrializing America: The Nineteenth Century</cite> (1995), introduction and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li>Judith A. McGaw, “Gender and Papermaking” (1998, abridged from <cite>Most Wonderful Machine: Mechanization and Social Change in Berkshire Paper Making, 1801–1885</cite>, 1987).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 7: The Industrialization of Time and Space</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 4.</li>
			<li>Wolfgang Schivelbusch, <cite>The Railway Journey: The Industrialization of Time and Space in the 19th Century</cite> (1986), chapters 1–6.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 14: The Industrialization of Housework</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother</cite>, chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 21: Technological Systems</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Thomas P. Hughes, <cite>American Genesis: A Century of Invention and Technological Enthusiasm 1870–1970</cite> (1989), introduction and chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Leo Marx, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2010.0009"><i>Technology</i>: The Emergence of a Hazardous Concept</a>” (2010, revised from 1997 original).</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>October 28: Modern Cities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 6.</li>
			<li>David Nye, <cite>Electrifying America: Social Meanings of a New Technology, 1880–1940</cite> (1990), preface and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 4: Modern Media</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Friedrich A. Kittler, <cite>Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</cite> (1999, translated from 1986 German original), pages 1–37.</li>
			<li>Susan J. Douglas, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01134.0001.001">Inventing American Broadcasting, 1899–1922</a></cite> (1987), introduction and chapter 6.</li>
			<li>Claude S. Fischer, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb00141.0001.001">America Calling: A Social History of the Telephone to 1940</a></cite> (1992), chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 11: Alternative Modernities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5.</li>
			<li>Paul R. Josephson, <cite>Would Trotsky Wear a Bluetooth? Technological Utopianism under Socialism, 1917–1989</cite> (2010), introduction and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 18: The Industrialization of Violence</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 7.</li>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 6 and 7.</li>
			<li>Paul N. Edwards, <cite><a href="http://cognet.mit.edu/book/closed-world">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (1996), pages 1–27.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>November 25: <i>No class</i></h4>
		<ul>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 2: Globalization</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 3, 4, 8 and conclusion.</li>
			<li>Carroll Pursell, <cite>The Machine in America: A Social History of Technology</cite>, second edition (2007, revised from 1994 original), chapter 13.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 9: Technological Systems Revisited</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapters 9 and 10.</li>
			<li>Nathan Ensmenger, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2012.0126">The Digital Construction of Technology: Rethinking the History of Computers in Society</a>” (2012).</li>
			<li>Paolo Pedercini, “<a href="http://www.molleindustria.org/blog/videogames-and-the-spirit-of-capitalism/">Videogames and the Spirit of Capitalism</a>” (2014).</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybernetics of the LRAD</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybernetics of the LRAD" /><published>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/"><![CDATA[<p>
	The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/">marketed</a> to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5369190/lrad-sound-cannon-used-on-pittsburgh-g20-protesters">first deployed in the United States</a> at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/14/chicago_cops_new_weapon/singleton/">will likely again</a> project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.
</p>
<!--more-->
<iframe class="video" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TInNg6QbHXc" title="Video player" frameborder="0" allow="picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen;"></iframe>
<p>
	As Aaron Bady <a href="http://thenewinquiry.com/blogs/hearing-like-an-lrad/">points out</a>, the LRAD brings together violence and speech. “To ask the question of whether an LRAD is designed to hurt people or designed to communicate across long distances with people,” writes Bady, “is to mystify its central design function: It is a technology whose purpose is to FORCE you to listen and obey, and one which is less interested in the difference than you’d think.” The LRAD makes it impossible to think of policing—particularly the iconic “order to disperse” delivered to political demonstrators from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haymarket_affair#Bombing_and_gunfire">Chicago in 1886</a> to Pittsburgh in 2009 (shown above)—as a process in which orders come first and force follows only in the case of disobedience. The medium through which orders are communicated is itself forceful; the LRAD is a <em>weapon</em>, which is why the LRAD Corporation sells it, according to their <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/content/view/323">fact sheet</a>, “only to qualified government agencies and commercial entities that are fully trained in the device’s operation.” Bady concludes, then, that the LRAD demonstrates policing is “simply about power. Communication is a means of making you obey,” and, from the perspective of the LRAD, nothing more.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD conflates communication and force not only conceptually but materially: The same sound serves both purposes. It thus taps into a deep seam in twentieth century science and philosophy that is concerned precisely with the relationship between communication and action. It could be interpreted, for instance, in terms of <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/~kbach/spchacts.html">speech act theory</a>: A loud LRAD order to disperse is both a threatening speech act and itself an act of force.
</p>
<p>
	Since the use of violence to establish control is intrinsic to the LRAD, though, its collapsing of communication and force resonates less with speech acts than the mid-century science of cybernetics. As MIT mathematician Norbert Wiener subtitled <a href="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL14113345M/Cybernetics_or_Control_and_communication_in_the_animal_and_the_machine.">his 1948 book</a> in which he named the discipline, cybernetics involved the study of “control and communication in the animal and machine.” The field developed in the late 1940s through collaborations between scientists interested in understanding minds, societies, and machines in the same terms—collaborations such as the <a href="http://asc-cybernetics.org/foundations/history/MacySummary.htm">Macy Conferences</a>—and cyberneticians conflated control and communication in part to establish parallels between these different entities. This collapsing of categories also owed something, though, to the origins of cybernetics in military research.
</p>
<p>
	Wiener did much of his thinking about analogies between humans and mechanical control systems during World War II while designing an “antiaircraft predictor,” designed to aim a gun in order to shoot down a maneuvering plane. Such a predictor was necessary because during the twenty seconds a shell took to reach its target, the pilot would maneuver, apparently unpredictably. In his article “<a href="http://jerome-segal.de/Galison94.pdf">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” and a <a href="http://cabinetmagazine.org/issues/12/najafi2.php">followup interview</a> in <cite>Cabinet</cite>, historian of science <a href="https://galison.scholar.harvard.edu">Peter Galison</a> argues that Wiener conceived of the enemy pilot as essentially mechanical, and his predictor as a machine that mirrored its behavior. “With no access to anything in the enemy plane,” he says, “Wiener simply treated the pilot-plane assembly as a complex machine—a servomechanism—that once characterized could be simulated in order to predict what it would do. And then it could be blown out of the sky.”
</p>
<p>
	Although Wiener’s work stood in a long tradition of <a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL8396574W/Between_Human_and_Machine">control engineering</a>—since his goal was simply to control a gun—his system also relied on interpreting the plane’s motions as communication to the predictor, which then “learned” its patterns by observing with radar. Even though, “because of the antagonistic relationship between attacker and defender, the anti-aircraft operator was obviously in no position to talk to or even see the pilot,” the latter’s movements still revealed—communicated—his intentions. From Wiener’s perspective as an engineer, though, there was no distinction between control and communication in this system; both were simply messages. There were messages conveyed by the pilot to the plane (through a joystick, say), from the plane to the predictor (through radar), from the predictor to the gun (through a mechanical connection), and from the gun to the plane (through a shell), but each relationship was one of both control and communication, of both force and speech.
</p>
<p>
	The U.S. military also embraced this conflation. During the decades after World War II “command and control,” previously two competing models of military management, became a single practice. <em>Command</em> traditionally involved an officer giving an order which was then interpreted and implemented by those below him in a hierarchy, often as more specific commands to their subordinates. It involved the ambiguity we expect from human communication, if not the dialogue. <em>Control</em>, on the other hand, was direct and (at least ideally) unambiguous. Nuclear weapons, which had to be deployed rapidly and only upon the decision of senior commanders, were subject to control rather than command. This distinction collapsed, though, as nuclear weapons were integrated into conventional military tactics. “By the early 1960s,” writes historian of technology <a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a> in <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2937046W/The_Closed_World">The Closed World</a></cite>, “military parlance treated the two as virtually identical. A decade later, ‘command, control, communications, and information’ (C<sup>3</sup>I) had become a single unified process.”
</p>
<p>
	It is from this postwar military ideology that the LRAD and its inventor Elwood Norris emerged. According to <a href="http://keynotespeakers.com/speaker_detail.php?speakerid=4074">his speaking bio</a>, Norris served in the Air Force as a nuclear weapons specialist in the 1950s before becoming an independent inventor. He was <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2009/03/06/smallbusiness/killer_sounds.fsb/">hired by the Navy</a> to design the LRAD in 2000 after the U.S.S. Cole bombing, and the original purpose of the device was to deter guerrillas from U.S. warships. It has since been used to deter Somali pirates from commercial ships and “to blast a series of Arabic phrases, such as ‘Go away or we will kill you,’” in Baghdad and Fallujah.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD, then, is a military technology that has come home to U.S. soil as a command-and-control system for conveying both orders and force from police to civilians. Its erasure of the distinction between control and communication is not a unique phenomenon that emerges when you build a very loud speaker; rather, its inventor designed a speaker loud enough to “influence behavior and create safety zones” because he and his employers already conflated force and speech.
</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="war" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is marketed to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was first deployed in the United States at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and will likely again project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">History of Cybernetics Bibliography</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="History of Cybernetics Bibliography" /><published>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>If you’ve come here after asking yourself (or Google) what cybernetics is, I recommend starting with Bernard Geoghegan and Benjamin Peters’ entry “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” from the <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite>, and Geoffrey Bowker’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>.” Ronald Kline’s <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment</a></cite> is the synthetic history the field has been waiting for. William Aspray’s “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>” places cybernetics in the context of developments in computing and information theory, while Peter Galison’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” is a classic account of the field’s military origins. The texts listed below survey the many forms cybernetics took in the decades that followed.</p>
	
<p>This bibliography is limited in three ways: It includes only books and articles which focus on cybernetics rather than the related histories of cyborgs and information theory; it includes only texts in English, though there are also substantial French and German literatures on the subject; and it excludes articles and dissertations that have been superseded by books by the same authors. Within these limitations, I welcome references to additional books and articles. I last updated this list on November 26, 2023.</p>

<h3 id="big">The Big Picture <small>(but mostly Anglo-American)</small></h3>
<ol class="start">
	<li>A. A. Verveen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0025-5564(71)90004-6">In Search of Processes: The Early History of Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Mathematical Biosciences</cite> 11 (1971).
	<li>Michael Apter, “Cybernetics: A Case Study of a Scientific Subject-Complex,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sociology-of-science/oclc/591825">The Sociology of Science</a></cite>, edited by Paul Halmos (University of Keele, 1972).</li>
	<li>Robert Lilienfeld, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-systems-theory-an-ideological-analysis/oclc/3275488">The Rise of Systems Theory: An Ideological Analysis</a></cite> (Wiley, 1978).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>,” <cite>Social Studies of Science</cite> 23 (1993).</li>
	<li><a href="http://nkhayles.com/">Katherine Hayles</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-we-became-posthuman-virtual-bodies-in-cybernetics-literature-and-informatics/oclc/39539341">How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in Cybernetics, Literature, and Informatics</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 1999).</li>
	<li>Charles Fran&ccedil;ois, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1099-1743(199905%2F06)16%3A3%3C203%3A%3AAID-SRES210%3E3.0.CO%3B2-1">Systemics and Cybernetics in a Historical Perspective</a>,” <cite>Systems Research and Behavioral Science</cite> 16 (1999).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sonoma.edu/hutchins/faculty/debora-hammond.html">Debora Hammond</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-of-synthesis-exploring-the-social-implications-of-general-systems-theory/oclc/939936819">The Science of Synthesis: Exploring the Social Implications of General Systems Theory</a></cite> (University Press of Colorado, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “The Empty Archive: Cybernetics and the 1960s,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/memory-practices-in-the-sciences/oclc/60776866">Memory Practices in the Sciences</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2008.9">The Historiographic Conceptualization of Information: A Critical Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 30 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://english.emory.edu/home/people/faculty/faculty_pages/johnston.html">John Johnston</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/allure-of-machinic-life-cybernetics-artificial-life-and-the-new-ai/oclc/255975196">The Allure of Machinic Life: Cybernetics, Artificial Life, and the New AI</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2008).</li>
	<li>Philipp Aumann, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2011.78">The Distinctiveness of a Unifying Science: Cybernetics’ Way to West Germany</a>” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 33 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000018">Cybernetic Sense</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/beautiful-data-a-history-of-vision-and-reason-since-1945/oclc/875884461">Beautiful Data: A History of Vision and Reason since 1945</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2014).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment; or, Why We Call Our Age the Information Age</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="http://medientheorie.com/">Claus Pias</a>, “The Age of Cybernetics,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-the-macy-conferences-1946-1953-transactions/oclc/945975579">Cybernetics: The Macy Conferences, 1946–1954; The Complete Transactions</a></cite> (diaphanes, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://ridt.co/">Thomas Rid</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-the-machines-a-cybernetic-history/oclc/921868924">Rise of the Machines: A Cybernetic History</a></cite> (Norton, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a> and <a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite> (2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://elizabethpetrick.com">Elizabeth Petrick</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243919881212">Building the Black Box: Cyberneticians and Complex Systems</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, and Human Values</cite> (2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="origins">Origins</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Otto Mayr, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/origins-of-feedback-control/oclc/102836">The Origins of Feedback Control</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1970).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~bill/">William Aspray</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 7 (1985).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/between-human-and-machine-feedback-control-and-computing-before-cybernetics/oclc/51493422">Between Human and Machine: Feedback, Control, and Computing before Cybernetics</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="us">United States</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20027476">The Americanization of Unity</a>,” <cite>Daedalus</cite> 127 (1998).</li>
	<li>Peter Krieg, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920510581729">The Human Face of Cybernetics: Heinz von Foerster and the History of a Movement That Failed</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 34 (2005).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/">Stuart Umpleby</a>, “<a href="http://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/cybernetics/2005_WAS_History_of_Cybernetics_Movement.doc">A History of the Cybernetics Movement in the United States</a>,” <cite>Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences</cite> 91 (2005).</li>
	<li>Christopher Johnson, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43151893">Analogue Apollo: Cybernetics and the Space Age</a>,” <cite>Paragraph</cite> 31 (2008).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="wiener">Norbert Wiener</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/john-von-neumann-and-norbert-wiener-from-mathematics-to-the-technologies-of-life-and-death/oclc/6304716">John von Neumann and Norbert Wiener: From Mathematics to the Technologies of Life and Death</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1982).</li>
	<li>Pesi Masani, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/norbert-wiener-1894-1964/oclc/19389460">Norbert Wiener, 1894–1964</a></cite> (Birkhauser, 1990).</li>
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 21 (1994).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.unizar.es/sociocybernetics/chen/felix/">Felix Geyer</a> and Johannes van der Zouwen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684929410068334">Norbert Wiener and the Social Sciences</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 23 (1994).
	<li><a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=112">David Jerison</a> and <a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=268">Daniel Stroock</a>, “Norbert Wiener,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://conwayandsiegelman.stillpointpress.net/">Flo Conway and Jim Siegelman</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/dark-hero-of-the-information-age-in-search-of-norbert-wiener-the-father-of-cybernetics/oclc/56656253">Dark Hero of the Information Age: In Search of Norbert Wiener, the Father of Cybernetics</a></cite> (Basic Books, 2004).</li>
	<li><a href="http://maramills.org/">Mara Mills</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-1428852">On Disability and Cybernetics: Helen Keller, Norbert Wiener, and the Hearing Glove</a>,” <cite>differences</cite> 22 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19409419.2013.775544">Toward a Genealogy of a Cold War Communication Science: The Strange Loops of Leo and Norbert Wiener</a>,” <cite>Russian Journal of Communication</cite> 5 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.uni-weimar.de/de/medien/professuren/medienwissenschaft/theorie-medialer-welten/personen/schmidgen/">Henning Schmidgen</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119880662">Cybernetic Times: Norbert Wiener, John Stroud, and the ‘Brain Clock’ Hypothesis</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="ussr">Soviet and Comparative Studies</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/david-holloway">David Holloway</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/284545">Innovation in Science—The Case of Cybernetics in the Soviet Union</a>,” <cite>Science Studies</cite> 4 (1974).</li>
	<li>Peter Elias, “The Rise and Fall of Cybernetics in the US and the USSR,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-newspeak-to-cyberspeak-a-history-of-soviet-cybernetics/oclc/48477582">From Newspeak to Cyberspeak: A History of Soviet Cybernetics</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <a href="http://jerome-segal.de/">J&eacute;r&ocirc;me Segal</a>, and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, “From Communications Engineering to Communications Science: Cybernetics and Information Theory in the United States, France, and the Soviet Union,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-and-ideology-a-comparative-history/oclc/49395331">Science and Ideology: A Comparative History</a></cite>, edited by Mark Walker (Routledge, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="http://ijoc.org/ojs/index.php/ijoc/article/view/212">Betrothal and Betrayal: The Soviet Translation of Norbert Wiener’s Early Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Communications</cite> 2 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-not-to-network-a-nation-the-uneasy-history-of-the-soviet-internet/oclc/927438758">How Not to Network a Nation: The Uneasy History of the Soviet Internet</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://cla.auburn.edu/history/people/faculty/instructors/diana-kurkovsky-west/">Diana Kurkovsky West</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886520">Cybernetics for the Command Economy: Foregrounding Entropy in Late Soviet Planning</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.lafayette.edu/sanbornj/">Joshua Sanborn</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/kri.2022.0044">Cybernetics and Surveillance: The Secret Police Enter the Computer Age</a>,” <cite>Kritika</cite> 23 (2022).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="france">France and “French Theory”</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://socio.umontreal.ca/repertoire-departement/vue/lafontaine-celine/">C&eacute;line Lafontaine</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276407084637">The Cybernetic Matrix of ‘French Theory,’</a>” <cite>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</cite> 24 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~ll2410/">Lydia Liu</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/648527">The Cybernetic Unconscious: Rethinking Lacan, Poe, and French Theory</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 36 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.cornell.edu/jacob-krell">Jacob Krell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886988">What is the ‘Cybernetic’ in the ‘History of Cybernetics’? A French Case, 1968 to the Present</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/en/lehrbereiche-en/general-sociology/team/vincent-august/index">Vincent August</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1368431021991046">Network Concepts in Social Theory: Foucault and Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>European Journal of Social Theory</cite> 24 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1346150607">Code: From Information Theory to French Theory</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2023)</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="chile">Chile</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-revolutionaries-technology-and-politics-in-allendes-chile/oclc/713834502">Cybernetic Revolutionaries: Technology and Politics in Allende’s Chile</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/people/staff/martin-collins">Martin Collins</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2013.776857">introduction to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://usnwc.edu/Faculty-and-Departments/Directory/Michael-Aaron-Dennis">Michael Dennis</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756240">Scientific and Technical Knowledge and the Making of Political Order</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756239">Beyond the Closed World</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://drexel.edu/coas/faculty-research/faculty-directory/TiagoSaraiva/">Tiago Saraiva</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756238">The History of Cybernetics in McOndo</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756237">author response to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="biology">Biology</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-1979-20-206">The Biological Enterprise: Sex, Mind, and Profit from Human Engineering to Sociobiology</a>,” <cite>Radical History Review</cite> no. 20 (1979).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “The High Cost of Information in Post World War II Evolutionary Biology: Ergonomics, Semiotics, and the Sociobiology of Communications Systems,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/philosophical-forum/oclc/1787155">Philosophical Forum</a></cite> 13 (1981–2).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “Signs of Dominance: From a Physiology to a Cybernetics of Primate Society, C.R. Carpenter, 1930–1970,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/studies-in-history-of-biology/oclc/2957828">Studies in History of Biology</a></cite> 6, edited by William Coleman and Camille Limoges (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “A Semiotics of the Naturalistic Field, from C.R. Carpenter to S.A. Altmann, 1930–55,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/primate-visions-gender-race-and-nature-in-the-world-of-modern-science/oclc/19672184">Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</a></cite> (Routledge, 1989).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “The Body of a New Machine: Situating the Organism between Telegraphs and Computers,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/refiguring-life-metaphors-of-twentieth-century-biology/oclc/31606662">Refiguring Life: Metaphors of Twentieth-Century Biology</a></cite> (Columbia University Press, 1995).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/who-wrote-the-book-of-life-a-history-of-the-genetic-code/oclc/41967065">Who Wrote the Book of Life? A History of the Genetic Code</a></cite> (Stanford University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “Taming the Cybernetic Metaphor” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/making-sense-of-life-explaining-biological-development-with-models-metaphors-and-machines/oclc/48100379">Making Sense of Life: Explaining Biological Development with Models, Metaphors, and Machines</a></cite> (Harvard University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sydney.edu.au/arts/history/staff/profiles/warwick.anderson.php">Warwick Anderson</a> and Ian MacKay, “The Science of Self,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/intolerant-bodies-a-short-history-of-autoimmunity/oclc/894511336">Intolerant Bodies: A Short History of Autoimmunity</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="ecology">Ecology</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://faculty.umb.edu/pjt/">Peter Taylor</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4331051">Technocratic Optimism, H.T. Odum, and the Partial Transformation of Ecological Metaphor after World War II</a>,” <cite>Journal of the History of Biology</cite> 21 (1988).</li>
	<li><a href="http://host.jhu.edu/directory/sharon-kingsland/">Sharon Kingsland</a>, “Defining the Ecosystem,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/evolution-of-american-ecology-1890-2000/oclc/56982282">The Evolution of American Ecology, 1890–2000</a></cite> (John Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li>William Bryant, “<a href="http://search.proquest.com/docview/305339541/">Whole System, Whole Earth: The Convergence of Technology and Ecology in Twentieth-Century American Culture</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Iowa, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “Neocybernetics of Gaia: The Emergence of Second-Order Gaia Theory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gaia-in-turmoil-climate-change-biodepletion-and-earth-ethics-in-an-age-of-crisis/oclc/313017382">Gaia in Turmoil: Climate Change, Biodepletion, and Earth Ethics in an Age of Crisis</a></cite>, edited by Eileen Crist and H. Bruce Rinker (MIT Press, 2010).</li>
	<li>Nancy Slack, “Good Friends: Margaret Mead and Gregory Bateson” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/g-evelyn-hutchinson-and-the-invention-of-modern-ecology/oclc/758332328">G. Evelyn Hutchinson and the Invention of Modern Ecology</a></cite> (Yale University Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.usf.edu/arts-sciences/departments/humanities-cultural-studies/faculty/daniel-belgrad.aspx">Daniel Belgrad</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1153210310">The Culture of Feedback: Ecological Thinking in ’70s America</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="social">Social Sciences</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-group/oclc/23047769">Constructing a Social Science for Postwar America: The Cybernetics Group, 1946–1953</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.albany.edu/~gpr/">George Richardson</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-thought-in-social-science-and-systems-theory/oclc/22731896">Feedback Thought in Social Science and Systems Theory</a></cite> (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://emsent.nl/">Esther-Mirjam Sent</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/perspectives_on_science/v008/8.4sent.html">Herbert A. Simon as a Cyborg Scientist</a>,” <cite>Perspectives on Science</cite> 8 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://reilly.nd.edu/people/reilly-fellows/philip-mirowski/">Philip Mirowski</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/machine-dreams-economics-becomes-a-cyborg-science/oclc/45636899">Machine Dreams: Economics Becomes a Cyborg Science</a></cite> (Cambridge University Press, 2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Crowther-Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/herbert-a-simon-the-bounds-of-reason-in-modern-america/oclc/55511492">Herbert A. Simon: The Bounds of Reason in Modern America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/age-of-system-understanding-the-development-of-modern-social-science/oclc/891185841">Age of System: Understanding the Development of Modern Social Science</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.stefanos-geroulanos.com">Stefanos Geroulanos</a> and <a href="https://leifweatherby.org/">Leif Weatherby</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119887098">“Cybernetics and the Human Sciences” special issue introduction</a>, <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119872111">How Disunity Matters to the History of Cybernetics in the Human Sciences in the United States, 1940–80</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li>Poornima Paidipaty, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1463499619899747">‘Tortoises All the Way Down’: Geertz, Cybernetics and ‘Culture’ at the End of the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Anthropological Theory</cite> 20 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="bateson">Gregory Bateson</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://cla.umn.edu/about/directory/profile/lipse001">David Lipset</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gregory-bateson-the-legacy-of-a-scientist/oclc/5894222">Gregory Bateson: The Legacy of a Scientist</a></cite> (Prentice Hall, 1980).</li>
	<li><a href="http://hss.sas.upenn.edu/people/tresch">John Tresch</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2783231">Heredity is an Open System: Gregory Bateson as Descendant and Ancestor</a>,” <cite>Anthropology Today</cite> 14 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.armoniedeldisordine.it/">Leone Montagnini</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777522">Looking for ‘Scientific’ Social Science: The Macy Conferences on Cybernetics in Bateson’s Itinerary</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li>Frank Thomas, Rebekah Waits, and Gail Hartsfield, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777397">The Influence of Gregory Bateson: Legacy or Vestige?</a>” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.northeastern.edu/camd/artdesign/people/william-kaizen/">William Kaizen</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598913">Steps to an Ecology of Communication: <cite>Radical Software</cite>, Dan Graham, and the Legacy of Gregory Bateson</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://history.ua.edu/faculty/erik-peterson/">Erik Peterson</a>, “<a href="http://etd.nd.edu/ETD-db/theses/available/etd-04132010-142514/">Finding Mind, Form, Organism, and Person in a Reductionist Age: The Challenge of Gregory Bateson and C. H. Waddington to Biological and Anthropological Orthodoxy, 1924–1980</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Notre Dame, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="http://sfonline.barnard.edu/feminist-media-theory/schizophrenic-techniques-cybernetics-the-human-sciences-and-the-double-bind/">Schizophrenic Techniques: Cybernetics, the Human Sciences, and the Double Bind</a>,” <cite>S&amp;F Online</cite> 10 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://laps-dept.apps01.yorku.ca/anth/faculty/emeriti/harries.html">Peter Harries-Jones</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/upside-down-gods-gregory-batesons-world-of-difference/oclc/952953457">Upside-Down Gods: Gregory Bateson’s World of Difference</a></cite> (Fordham University Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthonychaney.com/">Anthony Chaney</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/runaway-gregory-bateson-the-double-bind-and-the-rise-of-ecological-consciousness/oclc/1032366653">Runaway: Gregory Bateson, the Double Bind, and the Rise of Ecological Consciousness</a></cite> (University of North Carolina Press, 2017).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="mind">Sciences of Mind</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.sv.uio.no/psi/personer/vit/geirki/">Geir Kirkeb&oslash;en</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/053901895034001002">From a Naked Emperor to Just Clothes: The Rise and Fall of Cybernetic Family Therapy</a>,” <cite>Social Science Information</cite> 34 (1995).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.brown.edu/Departments/CLPS/people/james-anderson">James Anderson</a> and Edward Rosenfeld, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/6626.001.0001">Talking Nets: An Oral History of Neural Networks</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1998).</li>
	<li><a href="https://dlcl.stanford.edu/people/jean-pierre-dupuy">Jean-Pierre Dupuy</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mechanization-of-the-mind-on-the-origins-of-cognitive-science/oclc/44026149">The Mechanization of the Mind: The Origins of Cognitive Science</a></cite>, translated by M. B. DeBevoise (Princeton University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li>Roberto Cordeschi, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/discovery-of-the-artificial-behavior-mind-and-machines-before-and-beyond-cybernetics/oclc/49860160">The Discovery of the Artificial: Behavior, Mind and Machines Before and Beyond Cybernetics</a></cite> (Kluwer Academic Publishers, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1024147708370">From Theory to Data: Representing Neurons in the 1940s</a>,” <cite>Biology and Philosophy</cite> 18 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1162/biot.2006.1.4.418">Cybernetics and Theoretical Approaches in 20th-Century Brain and Behavior Sciences</a>,” <cite>Biological Theory</cite> 1 (2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://socialsciences.exeter.ac.uk/sociology/staff/pickering/">Andrew Pickering</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-brain-sketches-of-another-future/oclc/615626770">The Cybernetic Brain: Sketches of Another Future</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://histsci.fas.harvard.edu/people/rebecca-lemov">Rebecca Lemov</a>, “<a href="http://limn.it/running-amok-in-labyrinthine-systems-the-cyber-behaviorist-origins-of-soft-torture/">Running Amok in Labyrinthine Systems: The Cyber-Behaviorist Origins of Soft Torture</a>,” <cite>Limn</cite> 1 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/dweinste">Deborah Weinstein</a>, “‘Systems Everywhere’: Schizophrenia, Cybernetics, and the Double Bind,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/pathological-family-postwar-america-and-the-rise-of-family-therapy/oclc/800721205">The Pathological Family: Postwar America and the Rise of Family Therapy</a></cite> (Cornell University Press, 2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://mediashiga.net/">John Shiga</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/of-other-networks/">Of Other Networks: Closed-World and Green-World Networks in the Work of John C. Lilly</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://hps.utoronto.ca/staff/chen-pang-yeang/">Chen-Pang Yeang</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/694184">From Modernizing the Chinese Language to Information Science: Chao Yuen Ren’s Route to Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 108 (2017).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthropology.columbia.edu/content/danielle-judith-zola-carr">Danielle Judith Zola Carr</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119874009">‘Ghastly Marionettes’ and the Political Metaphysics of Cognitive Literalism: Anti-Behaviourism, Language, and the Origins of Totalitarianism</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.christinavagt.com">Christina Vagt</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119882883">Design as Aesthetic Education: On the Politics and Aesthetics of Learning Environments</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.princeton.edu/people/katja-guenther">Katja Guenther</a>, “The Dancing Robot: Grey Walter’s Cybernetic Mirror,” in <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1345590894">The Mirror and the Mind: A History of Self-Recognition in the Human Sciences</a></cite> (Princeton University Press, 2022).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="mcculloch">Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://ngp.usc.edu/faculty/profile/?fid=16">Michael Arbib</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0001">Warren McCulloch’s Search for the Logic of the Nervous System</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.psych.uic.edu/department-of-psychiatry-faculty-list/154-about-us/directory/faculty/234-neil-r-smalheiser-md-phd">Neil Smalheiser</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0009">Walter Pitts</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0269889701000266">From Logical Neurons to Poetic Embodiments of Mind: Warren S. McCulloch’s Project in Neuroscience</a>,” <cite>Science in Context</cite> 14 (2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0160-9327(03)00017-6">Integrating Mind and Brain: Warren S. McCulloch, Cerebral Localization, and Experimental Epistemology</a>,” <cite>Endeavour</cite> 27 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/kenaizawa/">Kenneth Aizawa</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000017">Warren McCulloch’s Turn to Cybernetics: What Walter Pitts Contributed</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~philh/">Phil Husbands</a> and <a href="http://cswww.essex.ac.uk/staff/owen/">Owen Holland</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000019">Warren McCulloch and the British Cyberneticians</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/psychology/contact-and-getting-here/people/alan-collins">Alan Collins</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000020">An Asymmetric Relationship: The Spirit of Kenneth Craik and the Work of Warren McCulloch</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, <cite><a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/rebel-genius">Rebel Genius: Warren S. McCulloch’s Transdisciplinary Life in Science</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="politics">Politics and Planning</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/closed-world-computers-and-the-politics-of-discourse-in-cold-war-america/oclc/42636403">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1996).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-warfare-to-welfare-defense-intellectuals-and-urban-problems-in-cold-war-america/oclc/51924188">From Warfare to Welfare: Defense Intellectuals and Urban Problems in Cold War America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.0.0007">Taking Games Seriously</a>,” <cite>Technology and Culture</cite> 49 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bbk.ac.uk/politics/our-staff/academic/antoine-bousquet">Antoine Bousquet</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14682740701791359">Cyberneticizing the American War Machine: Science and Computers in the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Cold War History</cite> 8 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.egs.edu/faculty/brian-holmes/">Brian Holmes</a>, <cite><a href="https://brianholmes.wordpress.com/2009/01/19/book-materials/">Escape the Overcode: Activist Art in the Control Society</a></cite> (Van Abbemuseum, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://geography.utoronto.ca/matt-farish-home-page/">Matthew Ferish</a>, “The Cybernetic Continent: North America as Defense Laboratory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/contours-of-americas-cold-war/oclc/698116870">The Contours of America’s Cold War</a></cite> (University of Minnesota Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://democracycollaborative.org/content/john-duda">John Duda</a>, “<a href="https://www.lwbooks.co.uk/anarchist-studies/21-1/cybernetics-anarchism-and-self-organisation">Cybernetics, Anarchism and Self-Organisation</a>,” <cite>Anarchist Studies</cite> 21 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://rhetoric.berkeley.edu/people/david-bates/">David Bates</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864237">The Political Theology of Entropy: A Katechon for the Cybernetic Age</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eui.eu/DepartmentsAndCentres/HistoryAndCivilization/People/Professors/Guilhot">Nicolas Guilhot</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864244">Automatic Leviathan: Cybernetics and Politics in Carl Schmitt’s Postwar Writings</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.hf.uio.no/ikos/english/people/aca/middle-east-studies/temporary/joakimp/">Joakim Parslow</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0020743821001033">The Mechanical Atatürk: Cybernetics and State Violence in the Second Turkish Republic</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Middle East Studies</cite> 53 (2021).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="popular">Popular Culture and Counterculture</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://homepages.rpi.edu/~eglash/eglash.htm">Ron Eglash</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/095023898335474">Cybernetics in American Youth Subculture</a>,” <cite>Cultural Studies</cite> 12 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://fredturner.stanford.edu/">Fred Turner</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-counterculture-to-cyberculture-stewart-brand-the-whole-earth-network-and-the-rise-of-digital-utopianism/oclc/62533774">From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “<a href="http://www.univie.ac.at/constructivism/journal/7/3/196.clarke">From Information to Cognition: The Systems Counterculture, Heinz von Foerster’s Pedagogy, and Second-Order Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Constructivist Foundations</cite> 7 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.dubberly.com/about">Hugh Dubberly</a> and <a href="http://pangaro.com">Paul Pangaro</a>, “<a href="http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html">How Cybernetics Connects Computing, Counterculture, and Design</a>,” in <cite>Hippie Modernism: The Struggle for Utopia</cite>, edited by Andrew Blauvelt (2015).</li>
	<!--Felicity Scott?-->
</ol>

<h3 id="art">Art</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://daniels.utoronto.ca/people/lobsingerm">Mary Louise Lobsinger</a>, “Cybernetic Theory and the Architecture of Performance: Cedric Price’s Fun Palace,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/anxious-modernisms-experimentation-in-postwar-architectural-culture/oclc/46929153">Anxious Modernisms: Experimentation in Postwar Architectural Culture</a></cite> (Canadian Center for Architecture, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://artexetra.wordpress.com">Edward Shanken</a>, “<a href="http://artexetra.com/CyberneticsArtCultConv.pdf">Cybernetics and Art: Cultural Convergence in the 1960s</a>,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-energy-to-information-representation-in-science-and-technology-art-and-literature/oclc/49821329">From Energy to Information</a></cite>, edited by Bruce Clarke and Linda Henderson (Stanford University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/leonardo/v041/41.2.fernandez.html">Gordon Pask: Cybernetic Polymath</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 41 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598908">Detached from HiStory: Jasia Reichardt and Cybernetic Serendipity</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li>Etan J. Ilfeld, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00326">Contemporary Art and Cybernetics: Waves of Cybernetic Discourse within Conceptual, Video and New Media Art</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 45 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://etiennebenson.com/">Etienne Benson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.7275/R5HT2M7T">Environment between System and Nature: Alan Sonfist and the Art of the Cybernetic Environment</a>,” <cite>communication +1</cite> 3 (2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="film">Film and Video</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.gc.cuny.edu/Page-Elements/Academics-Research-Centers-Initiatives/Doctoral-Programs/Art-History/Faculty-Bios/David-Joselit">David Joselit</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-television-against-democracy/oclc/71322293">Feedback: Television Against Democracy</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://art.stonybrook.edu/faculty/zabet-patterson/">Zabet Patterson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/grey.2009.1.36.36">From the Gun Controller to the Mandala: The Cybernetic Cinema of John and James Whitney</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite> no. 36 (2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://film.fsu.edu/People/Administration/Dr.-Andrew-Syder">Andrew Syder</a>, “<a href="http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15799coll127/id/220820/">“Shaken Out of the Ruts of Ordinary Perception”: Vision, Culture and Technology in the Psychedelic Sixties</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Southern California, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://kpaulsen.com/">Kris Paulsen</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/half-inch-revolution/">Half Inch Revolution: The Guerilla Video Tape Network</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="http://procom.ryerson.ca/people/carolyn-kane">Carolyn Kane</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00871">The Tragedy of Radical Subjectivity: From Radical Software to Proprietary Subjects</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 47, no. 5 (2014).</li>
	<li><a href="https://collopy.net/">Peter Sachs Collopy</a>, “<a href="https://repository.upenn.edu/edissertations/1665/">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://medienwissenschaft.philhist.unibas.ch/de/personen/ute-holl/">Ute Holl</a>, <cite><a href="http://library.oapen.org/handle/20.500.12657/31337">Cinema, Trance and Cybernetics</a></cite> (Amsterdam University Press, 2017).
</ol>

<h4 id="sound">Sound and Music</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://annenberg.usc.edu/faculty/communication/christina-dunbar-hester">Christina Dunbar-Hester</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243909337116">Listening to Cybernetics: Music, Machines, and Nervous Systems, 1950–1980</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</cite> 35 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sterneworks.org/">Jonathan Sterne</a>, “Nature Builds No Telephones” and “Perceptual Coding and the Domestication of Noise,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mp3-the-meaning-of-a-format/oclc/769429993">MP3: The Meaning of a Format</a></cite> (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/staff/profiles/music/haworth-christopher.aspx">Christopher Haworth</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.461">Music and Cybernetics in Historical Perspective: Introduction to the Special Issue</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://deirdreloughridge.wordpress.com">Deirdre Loughridge</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.503">Daphne Oram: Cyberneticist?</a>” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eamonnbell.com">Eamonn Bell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.523">Cybernetics, Listening, and Sound-Studio Phenomenotechnique in Abraham Moles’s <cite>Théorie de l’information et perception esthétique</cite> (1958)</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.claralatham.com">Clara Latham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.559">The Sound Machine in the Body: Cybernetics and the Theremin</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://music.utexas.edu/about/people/eric-drott">Eric Drott</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.578">Music and the Cybernetic Mundane</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://ted-gordon.net">Theodore Gordon</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07494467.2021.2001939">‘Androgynous Music’: Pauline Oliveros’s Early Cybernetic Improvisation</a>,” <cite>Contemporary Music Review</cite> 40 (2022).</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="computing" /><category term="art" /><category term="war" /><category term="biology" /><category term="video" /><category term="media" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="psychiatry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.]]></summary></entry></feed>