<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/politics.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-09T13:32:01-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/politics.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Electrifying Los Angeles</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2026/electrifying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Electrifying Los Angeles" /><published>2026-01-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2026-01-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2026/electrifying</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2026/electrifying/"><![CDATA[<p>This term we will be exploring the meteoric rise of modern Los Angeles through two lenses: the history of its energy infrastructure and of our own institution, Caltech. These two histories intertwine in multiple ways, in the form of big personalities, grand ambitions, and feats of technical bravado. But innumerable smaller, less-visible parts of Caltech and Southern California history also play vital roles in the shaping of this region and our home institution. To trace these stories, large and small, we will be turning to the Caltech Archives and the digital collections of The Huntington Library. You will be learning how to research and communicate the history of archival objects, culminating in a final “group exhibition” of your curated pieces.</p>
<!--more-->


<h3>Schedule of Class Topics and Readings</h3>

<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>January 8: Caltech and Its Archives</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Mike Davis, <cite>City of Quartz: Excavating the Future in Los Angeles</cite> (Verso, 1990), 54–62.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>January 15: Thinking Critically About Infrastructure</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Langdon Winner, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20024652">Do Artifacts Have Politics?</a>” <cite>Daedelus</cite> 190 (1980): 121–136.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>January 22: Electrifying America</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>David E. Nye, <cite>Electrifying America: Social Meanings of a New Technology, 1880–1940</cite> (MIT Press, 1992), 85–137.</li>
			<li>Explore the <a href="https://hdl.huntington.org/digital/collection/p16003coll2/search/order/date/ad/asc">Southern California Edison Photographs and Negatives</a> via the Huntington Digital Library. Spend at least 30 minutes exploring images, and select one to share with the group via Ed. In your post, provide a link to your chosen and describe what interests you about it.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>January 29: Big Creek and the High Voltage Research Laboratory</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Donald C. Jackson, <cite>Building the Ultimate Dam: John S. Eastman and the Control of Water in the West</cite> (University Press of Kansas, 1995), 59–83.</li>
			<li>Etienne Benson, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/22011919-3615916">Generating Infrastructural Invisibility: Insulation, Interconnection, and Avian Excrement in the Southern California Power Grid</a>,” <cite>Environmental Humanities</cite> 6 (2015): 103–130.</li> 
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>February 5: Gordon Kaufmann at Caltech</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Helen Lefkowitz Horowitz, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/3639569">Designing for the Genders: Curricula and Architecture at Scripps College and the California Institute of Technology</a>,” <cite>Pacific Historical Review</cite> 54 (1985): 439–461.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>February 12: Hoover Dam and the Technological Sublime</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Joan Didion, “At the Dam” (1970), in <cite>The White Album</cite> (Simon & Schuster, 1979).</li>
			<li>David E. Nye, <cite>American Technological Sublime</cite> (MIT Press, 1994), 133–142.</li>
			<li>Donald Worster, <cite>Under Western Skies: Nature and History in the American West</cite> (Oxford University Press, 1992), 64–78.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>February 19: Electric Los Angeles</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Daniel L. Wuebben, <cite>Power Lined: Electricity, Landscape, and the American Mind</cite> (University of Nebraska Press, 2019), 87–129.</li>
			<li>Visit from Prof. Brian Jacobson.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>February 26</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>No class: independent Archives visits</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>March 4: <cite>Chinatown</cite> screening</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>March 5: River Futures</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Ellie Robins, “<a href="https://ellie-robins1.medium.com/the-los-angeles-river-is-your-brain-e53e6be10dc2">The Los Angeles River is Your Brain</a>” (2021).</li>
			<li>Visit from Dr. Nick Earhart.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="science" /><category term="physics" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="technology" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="politics" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This term we will be exploring the meteoric rise of modern Los Angeles through two lenses: the history of its energy infrastructure and of our own institution, Caltech. These two histories intertwine in multiple ways, in the form of big personalities, grand ambitions, and feats of technical bravado. But innumerable smaller, less-visible parts of Caltech and Southern California history also play vital roles in the shaping of this region and our home institution. To trace these stories, large and small, we will be turning to the Caltech Archives and the digital collections of The Huntington Library. You will be learning how to research and communicate the history of archival objects, culminating in a final “group exhibition” of your curated pieces.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy" /><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="art" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behind the Book: Escape from Earth</title><link href="https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behind the Book: Escape from Earth" /><published>2022-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="communism" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Robert Millikan, Eugenics, and Justice in the Laboratory and the Archives</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2022/robert-millikan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robert Millikan, Eugenics, and Justice in the Laboratory and the Archives" /><published>2022-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2022/robert-millikan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2022/robert-millikan/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="eugenics" /><category term="physics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="politics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="white supremacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Archiving Communities of Resilience and Resistance in Caltech’s Present &amp;amp; Past</title><link href="https://collopy.net/discussions/2021/archiving-communities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Archiving Communities of Resilience and Resistance in Caltech’s Present &amp;amp; Past" /><published>2021-04-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/discussions/2021/archiving-communities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/discussions/2021/archiving-communities/"><![CDATA[The legacy of Caltech is marked by stories of injustice. It is also marked by the communities forged in the face of that injustice, exclusion, and bigotry. In this virtual event hosted on April 27, 2021, a panel of current and former members of Caltech’s staff, faculty, and student body (Rochelle Diamond, Dr. Melany Hunt, and Dr. Edray Goins) offered reflections on their personal histories of organizing, agitating, and advocating on campus.

In doing so, we consider the ways that remembering those histories - through practices of archiving and other forms of memory work - can inform, ground, and inspire present and future activism at Caltech.

The event also included remarks from Dr. Peter Collopy, Caltech’s University Archivist, and was facilitated by Nivetha (Niv) Karthikeyan as part of her 2020 Milton and Rosalind Chang Prize project, “Intersections: Building Solidarity Through Community Archives.”

This event was hosted by Athena Castro and Greg Fletcher in the Caltech Y.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The legacy of Caltech is marked by stories of injustice. It is also marked by the communities forged in the face of that injustice, exclusion, and bigotry. In this virtual event hosted on April 27, 2021, a panel of current and former members of Caltech’s staff, faculty, and student body (Rochelle Diamond, Dr. Melany Hunt, and Dr. Edray Goins) offered reflections on their personal histories of organizing, agitating, and advocating on campus. In doing so, we consider the ways that remembering those histories - through practices of archiving and other forms of memory work - can inform, ground, and inspire present and future activism at Caltech. The event also included remarks from Dr. Peter Collopy, Caltech’s University Archivist, and was facilitated by Nivetha (Niv) Karthikeyan as part of her 2020 Milton and Rosalind Chang Prize project, “Intersections: Building Solidarity Through Community Archives.” This event was hosted by Athena Castro and Greg Fletcher in the Caltech Y.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Art Do Work</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Art Do Work" /><published>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work/"><![CDATA[In <cite>Making Art Work</cite>, W. Patrick McCray asks why and how American artists and engineers collaborated to produce technological art in the 1960s and 1970s. In our current moment, so obviously marked by the American government’s failure to deploy scientific expertise against a pandemic, and by demonstrations against white supremacy and police brutality larger than those of the 1960s, this book also provokes additional questions. Of what did technological art make people aware? Could it in fact contribute to solving social problems like hunger, homelessness, and war? How did patriarchy and white supremacy shape this art and the awareness it produced? What roles did women and people of color play in constructing and contesting it? Although none of these questions is at the center of McCray’s book, he points toward some of the answers.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="politics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="technopolitics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Making Art Work, W. Patrick McCray asks why and how American artists and engineers collaborated to produce technological art in the 1960s and 1970s. In our current moment, so obviously marked by the American government’s failure to deploy scientific expertise against a pandemic, and by demonstrations against white supremacy and police brutality larger than those of the 1960s, this book also provokes additional questions. Of what did technological art make people aware? Could it in fact contribute to solving social problems like hunger, homelessness, and war? How did patriarchy and white supremacy shape this art and the awareness it produced? What roles did women and people of color play in constructing and contesting it? Although none of these questions is at the center of McCray’s book, he points toward some of the answers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sitting Down with Uncomfortable Things in the Caltech Archives</title><link href="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/uncomfortable-things/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sitting Down with Uncomfortable Things in the Caltech Archives" /><published>2020-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/uncomfortable-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/presentations/2020/uncomfortable-things/"><![CDATA[In this event, members of the Caltech community presented their reflections on a collection of digitized materials curated from the Caltech Archives. The “uncomfortable things” selected for this discussion were artifacts of experiences of exclusion, inequality, discrimination, and bigotry in the history of Caltech. In this session, we acknowledged that the legacy of Caltech is intertwined with stories of injustice. By asking participants to personally reflect on that legacy, this event highlighted how there is no single solution or perspective sufficient to answer the multitude of questions and concerns that our community has about its history.

This event took place on October 2, 2020 as part of the series “Critical Intersections: Conversations on History, Race, and Science,” sponsored by the Caltech Division of the Humanities and Social Sciences.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="presentations" /><category term="eugenics" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="politics" /><category term="science" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="education" /><category term="white supremacy" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this event, members of the Caltech community presented their reflections on a collection of digitized materials curated from the Caltech Archives. The “uncomfortable things” selected for this discussion were artifacts of experiences of exclusion, inequality, discrimination, and bigotry in the history of Caltech. In this session, we acknowledged that the legacy of Caltech is intertwined with stories of injustice. By asking participants to personally reflect on that legacy, this event highlighted how there is no single solution or perspective sufficient to answer the multitude of questions and concerns that our community has about its history. This event took place on October 2, 2020 as part of the series “Critical Intersections: Conversations on History, Race, and Science,” sponsored by the Caltech Division of the Humanities and Social Sciences.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed.

Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite>, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite> is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="computing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="fascism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed. Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, IBM and the Holocaust, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, IBM and the Holocaust is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Evolution Debates</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution Debates" /><published>2017-01-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-01-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2017/evolution/"><![CDATA[<p>As the evolution of life generally and humanity in particular became scientific orthodoxy in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, scientists and other intellectuals debated what this meant. Some conceptions of God were compatible with evolution and others were not, for example, but the inverse was also true: certain conceptions of evolution were compatible with God and others were not. And at the same time, some conceptions of evolution emphasized cooperation and suggested humans would achieve the happiest lives through socialism, while others emphasized the roles of competition and “survival of the fittest” and suggested that capitalism was a better system for human achievement. Some theories of human evolution justified white supremacy, while others suggested racial equality. As a result, debates about biology were often also debates about religion and politics, and the three fields were repeatedly re-formed together.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>This is a syllabus for The Evolution Debates, a course offered for four units of credit in spring 2017 as HIST 255g at the University of Southern California. This course will explore the history of ideas about evolution and human origins from about 1800 to the present. We’ll focus on debates and controversies, both within biology and geology and at intersections of science, religion, and politics, as well as famous incidents like Charles Darwin’s voyage on the Beagle and the Scopes Monkey Trial. More broadly, we’ll study the development of evolutionary theory, the histories of creationism and theistic evolutionism, and the roles of debates about human evolution’s political consequences in the histories of eugenics and scientific racism.</p>

<p>This is a General Education course in the category of Humanistic Inquiry. We’ll use the history of evolutionary thought to understand how scientists, theologians, and others have thought about what it means to be human and to live together in organized societies—and about how we became such social animals. In the process, we’ll interpret not only scientific texts for both professional and popular audiences, but also novels, visual art, film, and works of philosophy and theology. We’ll read carefully in order both to understand how arguments work and how the ideas of evolutionary thinkers have been shaped by the particular times, places, and experiences in which they lived, as well as by changing media and systems of publishing and scientific communication.</p>

<p>The course will meet for lectures on Monday, Wednesday, and Friday mornings, 9 to 9:50, from January 9 to April 28, in Von Kleinsmid Center room 102. I will be available for office hours on Mondays from 10:00 to 12:00 in Social Sciences Building room 281, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>

<p>This course is organized around substantial reading assignments of primary sources, which is to say texts written by biologists, geologists, philosophers, theologians, and other participants in the evolution debates. We’ll discuss readings during <!--both lecture and discussion sections-->every class, so please read everything assigned before the class meeting it’s listed under. Each week I will expect you post a short reaction to the reading by Sunday (or by Tuesday on weeks when the class doesn’t meet on Monday) using Blackboard’s blog feature. You can use this as an opportunity to raise questions, to comment on arguments you found particularly surprising or compelling, or to suggest ways the reading might relate to previous readings or forthcoming assignments.</p>

<p>You are required to buy two books, both of which are also available at the USC Bookstore. Please buy these specific editions, so we can refer to the same page numbers and editor’s notes:</p>
<ul>
	<li><cite><a href="http://greenlion.com/books/Darwin_GC.html">Selections from Darwin’s Origin of Species: The Shape of the Argument</a></cite>, edited by Nicholas Maistrellis, Green Cat Books edition (2009).</li>
	<li>H.G. Wells, <cite><a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/9780393927948">The Time Machine</a></cite>, edited by Stephen Arata, Norton Critical Edition (2008).</li>
</ul>

<p>All other required readings for the course will be available online; for the first half of the semester, we’ll mostly be reading texts available through the web repository <a href="https://www.hathitrust.org/">HathiTrust</a> (and linked to below). When we get to more recent texts, I’ll make scanned copies of the excerpts we’re reading available to you.</p>

<p>My lectures will provide historical context for these readings, introduce you to debates between historians about their significance, and describe the roles of historical figures beyond those whose work you’re reading. You’re therefore not required to read a textbook for the course, but if you’d like one to refer to or to follow along in for an additional perspective on this history, I’ve included page numbers below for relevant sections of Peter J. Bowler, <cite><a href="https://www.ucpress.edu/books/evolution-2/paper">Evolution: The History of an Idea</a></cite>, third edition (2003), which is available from the USC Bookstore and on reserve at Leavey Library’s circulation desk, and listed with them some other books for further reading or as sources for writing papers. Two other useful reference sources will be the <cite>Dictionary of Scientific Biography</cite> and the <cite><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</a></cite>, each of which is useful for finding introductory information on particular scientists and philosophers and citations for books and articles that provide more detailed information.</p>

<p>Your first substantial writing assignment, due February 10, will be a paper approximately five pages long in which you develop <a href="review">your own analysis of a review of <cite>The Origin of Species</cite></a>, contextualizing it in the life of its author, with attention to their other scientific, religious, political, and philosophical interests and commitments, and in the editorial agenda of the publication in which it appears. We’ll spend some time in class looking at different ways you might find such reviews and research their authors and publications.</p>

<p>Your second writing assignment, due April 7, will be an <a href="book">online exhibit on a particular book in the evolution debates as a material text</a>. In this exhibit, you’ll demonstrate what you can learn from looking at a physical book about its intended audience and how it was meant to be read. We’ll spend some time in class in advance of this assignment thinking about books in precisely this way, and will visit the USC Libraries’ Special Collections to look at original editions of books on evolution including some of those we’ve read ourselves. You’ll also have an opportunity to present the book you’re thinking about to the class on March 3.</p>

<p>Your last essay assignment, of approximately five pages and due April 28, will be to analyze what was at stake in a particular controversy about evolution. What did the people involved care about? What did they want to persuade others of? How did they use the idea of evolution to do so?</p>

<p>Additionally, there will be a midterm exam during class on March 10 and a final exam on May 5. These exams may involve short answer questions, longer essay questions, or a combination. In any case, the purpose will be more to evaluate your understanding of how ideas about evolution and its scientific, social, and religious consequences have changed over time, and less to test your memory of specific names or dates.</p>

<p>Your grade for the course will be based 15% on each of the two essays, 15% on the online exhibit, 15% on each of the two exams, 10% on reading responses, and 15% on your engaged and insightful participation in class.</p>


<h3 id="schedule">Schedule of Class Topics and Readings</h3>

<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 9: What Are the Evolution Debates?</h5>
		<ul>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Peter J. Bowler, <cite>Evolution: The History of an Idea</cite>, third edition (2003), 1–26.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="stable">Is Nature Stable or Changing?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, January 11: The Great Chain of Being and the System of Nature <!--(29 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Charles Bonnet, <cite>The Contemplation of Nature</cite> (1764), translated and abridged in John Wesley, <cite>A Survey of the Wisdom of God in the Creation</cite> (1777), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc2.ark:/13960/t83j3c60t">volume 4</a>, 49–51, 58–62, 87–96.</li>
			<li>Carl Linnaeus, <cite>A General System of Nature</cite> (1735–1768), revised by Johann Friedrich Gmelin (1788–1793) and translated by William Turton (1800), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=ncs1.ark:/13960/t1fj2zn1z">volume 1</a>, 1–11.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 48–71; Arthur O. Lovejoy, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.05488.0001.001">The Great Chain of Being: A Study of the History of an Idea</a></cite> (1936); Michel Foucault, <cite>The Order of Things: An Archeology of the Human Sciences</cite> (1966; 1970); Londa Schiebinger, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2166840">Why Mammals Are Called Mammals: Gender Politics in Eighteenth-Century Natural History</a>” (1993).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, January 13: Evolution in an Age of Revolutions <!--(32 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Jean-Baptiste Lamarck, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044066262601">Zoological Philosophy</a></cite> (1809), translated by Hugh Elliot (1914), 1–8, 35–46, 68–70, 106–114.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 71–95; Adrian Desmond, <cite>The Politics of Evolution: Morphology, Medicine, and Reform in Radical London</cite> (1989).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 16: <i>No class for Martin Luther King, Jr. Day</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, January 18: <i>No class</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, January 20: Natural Theology <!--(62 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Thomas Malthus, <cite><a href="https://archive.org/details/essayonprinciple00malt_1">An Essay on the Principle of Population</a></cite> (1798), 11–17, 356–371.</li>
			<li>William Paley, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uva.x001197535">Natural Theology</a></cite> (1802), 1–21, 454–459, 467–469, 473–481.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 96–106.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 23: Catastrophe and Uniformity <!--(39 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Georges Cuvier, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015032031943">Essay on the Theory of the Earth</a></cite> (1813), translated by Robert Kerr (1815), 5–17.</li>
			<li>Charles Lyell, <cite>Principles of Geology</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433066370341">volume 1</a> (1830), 1–4; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044103125563">volume 2</a> (1832), 18–32; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433066370366">volume 3</a> (1833), 1–7.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 106–134; Charles Coulston Gillespie, <cite>Genesis and Geology: A Study in the Relations of Scientific Thought, Natural Theology, and Social Opinion in Great Britain, 1790–1850</cite> (1951); Martin S. Rudwick, <cite>Bursting the Limits of Time: The Reconstruction of Geohistory in the Age of Revolution</cite> (2005) and <cite>Worlds Before Adam: The Reconstruction of Geohistory in the Age of Reform</a></cite> (2008).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, January 25: Popular Evolutionism <!--(48 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Robert Chambers, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044107245359">The Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</a></cite> (1844), 113–119, 145–147, 153–161, 174–178, and 268–291.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 134–140; James Secord, <cite>Victorian Sensation: The Extraordinary Publication, Reception, and Secret Authorship of <cite>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</cite></cite> (2000).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="darwin">Darwin and Wallace’s Answers</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, January 27: The Voyages of Charles Darwin and Alfred Russell Wallace <!--(10 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Charles Darwin, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015074623516">Journal and Remarks</a></cite> (1839), 453–457, 461–465.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 141–155; Janet Browne, <cite>Charles Darwin: Voyaging</cite> (1995).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, January 30: “One Long Argument” <!--(65 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Charles Darwin, <cite>On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection</cite> (1859), edited by Nicholas Maistrellis, Green Cat Books edition (2009), 5–7, 13–26, 31–42, 47–65, 71–77, 83–94, 99–105.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 155–176; Piers Hale, <cite>Political Descent: Malthus, Mutualism, and the Politics of Evolution in Victorian England</cite> (2014), 1–65; Janet Browne, <cite>Charles Darwin: The Power of Place</cite> (2002).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 1: The Reception of Darwinism</h5>
		<ul>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 177–202; Alvar Ellegård, <cite>Darwin and the General Reader: The Reception of Darwin’s Theory of Evolution in the British Periodical Press, 1859–1872</cite> (1958); David L. Hull, <cite>Darwin and His Critics: The Reception of Darwin’s Theory of Evolution by the Scientific Community</cite> (1973); <cite>The Comparative Reception of Darwinism</cite>, edited by Thomas F. Glick (1974); <cite>Disseminating Darwinism: The Role of Place, Race, Religion, and Gender</cite>, edited by Ronald L. Numbers and John Stenhouse (1999); <cite>The Reception of Charles Darwin in Europe</cite>, edited by Eve-Marie Engels and Thomas F. Glick (2008).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 3: <i>Introduction to Special Collections</i></h5>
		<ul>	
			<li><i>Meet in <a href="https://libraries.usc.edu/locations/special-collections">USC Special Collections</a>, Doheny Memorial Library room 206.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="atheistic">Is Darwinism Atheistic?</h4>
<ul>
	<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 202–207; James Moore, <cite>The Post-Darwinian Controversies: A Study of the Protestant Struggle to Come to Terms with Darwin in Great Britain and America, 1870–1900</cite> (1979); Jon H. Roberts, <cite>Darwinism and the Divine in America: Protestant Intellectuals and Organic Evolution, 1859–1900</cite> (1988).</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 6: Anti-Evolutionism <!--(24 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>	
			<li>Charles Hodge, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044019200393">What Is Darwinism?</a></cite> (1874), 1–2, 40–48, 52–53, 168–178.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 8: Christian Darwinism <!--(29 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>George Frederick Wright, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015074659486;seq=371">Concerning the True Doctrine of Final Cause or Design in Nature</a>,” <cite>Bibliotheca Sacra</cite> 34 (1877): 357–385.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 10: <i>The Evolution Debates in Special Collections</i></h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Meet in USC Special Collections.</i></li>
			<li><i>Paper due <a href="review">contextualizing a review of <cite>The Origin of Species</cite></a>.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="humans">How Did Humans Evolve?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 13: Monogenism and Polygenism <!--(36 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Louis Agassiz, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=nyp.33433081670469;seq=118">The Diversity of Origin of the Human Races</a>,” <cite>Christian Examiner</cite> 49 (1850): 110–113, 126–128, 136–138, 141–145.</li>
			<li>Frederick Douglass, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.69015000002739">The Claims of the Negro, Ethnologically Considered</a></cite> (1854), 9–10, 12–18, 34–35.</li>
			<li>Charles Darwin, <cite>The Descent of Man, and Selection in Relation to Sex</cite> (1871), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=osu.32435064734387">volume 1</a>, 9–10, 220–227.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 207–216, 292–297.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 15: Sexual Selection <!--(31 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Darwin, <cite>Descent of Man</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=osu.32435064734387">volume 1</a>, 245–251, 263–266; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hw2p3s">volume 2</a>, 301–302, 310–314.</li>
			<li>Eliza Burt Gamble, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.rslxyf">The Evolution of Woman</a></cite> (1894), 19–31.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 313–315; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 106–154; Cynthia Eagle Russett, <cite>Sexual Science: The Victorian Construction of Womanhood</cite> (1989); Kimberly A. Hamlin, <cite>From Eve to Evolution: Darwin, Science, and Women’s Rights in Gilded Age America</cite> (2014).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 17: Herbert Spencer’s Universal Evolutionism <!--(29 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044014674535">First Principles</a></cite> (1862), 146–174. (An earlier version of this chapter, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.31158008177155;seq=254">Progress: Its Law and Cause</a>,” <cite>Westminster Review</cite> 67 (1857), is also available.)</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 220–223; Mark Francis, <cite>Herbert Spencer and the Invention of Modern Life</cite> (2007); <cite>Global Spencerism: The Communication and Appropriation of a British Evolutionist</cite>, edited by Bernard Lightman (2015).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 20: <i>No class for Presidents Day</i></h5>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="politics">The Politics of Evolution: Competitive or Cooperative?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, February 22: Individualism <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044011566569">Social Statics</a></cite> (1851), 16–38.</li>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite>The Principles of Biology</cite> (1864), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044009912734">volume 1</a>, 443–445.</li>
			<li>Herbert Spencer, <cite>The Principles of Sociology</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.ah5dvt">volume 3</a> (1896), 608–611.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 274–277, 298–302; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 66–105.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, February 24: Liberalism <!--(20 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Thomas Henry Huxley, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101065273508;seq=171">The Struggle for Existence: A Programme</a>,” <cite>Nineteenth Century</cite>, February 1888, 161–180.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 216–220; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 155–221.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, February 27: Socialism <!--(25 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Peter Kropotkin, “Mutual Aid Among Animals,” <cite>Nineteenth Century</cite>, <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101065273474;seq=351">September 1890</a>, 337–349, 354; <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101065273474;seq=712">November 1890</a>, 709–719.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 305–307, 315–317; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 222–251; Daniel Todes, <cite>Darwin Without Malthus: The Struggle for Existence in Russian Evolutionary Thought</cite> (1989).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 1: Communism <!--(26 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Lewis Henry Morgan, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044011479847">Ancient Society</a></cite> (1877), 3–18, 551–554.</li>
			<li>Frederick Engels, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015024944756">The Origin of the Family, Private Property and the State</a></cite> (1884), translated by Ernest Untermann (1902), 102–103, 116–119.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 284–292.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 3: <i>Presentations on Special Collections</i></h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Meet in USC Special Collections.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="eclipse">The Eclipse of Darwinism: What Are the Mechanisms of Evolution?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, March 6: Neo-Darwinism and Neo-Lamarckism <!--(27 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Ernst Haeckel, <cite>The History of Creation</cite> (1868), translated by Edwin Ray Lankester (1876), <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=inu.30000041570254">volume 1</a>, 280–292.</li>
			<li>Edwin Ray Lankester, <cite>Degeneration: A Chapter in Darwinism</cite> (1880), excerpted in H.G. Wells, <cite>The Time Machine</cite> (1895), edited by Stephen Arata, Norton Critical Edition (2008), 160–163.</li>
			<li>H.G. Wells, “Zoological Retrogression” (1891), excerpted in Wells, <cite>Time Machine</cite>, 133–135.</li>
			<li>August Weismann, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hc4pef">The Germ-Plasm: A Theory of Heredity</a></cite> (1892), translated by W. Newton Parker and Harriet R&ouml;nnfeldt (1893), ix–xv.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 224–256; Hale, <cite>Political Descent</cite>, 252–353; Peter J. Bowler, <cite>The Eclipse of Darwinism: Anti-Darwinian Evolution Theories in the Decades around 1900</cite> (1983).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 8: “The Deathbed of Darwinism”? <!--(36 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Alexander Patterson, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015028720707">The Other Side of Evolution</a></cite> (1903), vii–xix, 120–136.</li>
			<li>Vernon Kellogg, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.$b572418">Darwinism To-Day</a></cite> (1907), 1–7.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Ronald L. Numbers, <cite>The Creationists: From Scientific Creationism to Intelligent Design</cite> (1992; 2006).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 10: <i>Midterm exam</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>March 12–19: <i>No class for spring break</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, March 20: Evolutionary Fiction <!--(71 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>H.G. Wells, <cite>Time Machine</cite> (1895), 1–71.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 22: Genetics and Eugenics <!--(27 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Francis Galton, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.$b676997;view=2up;seq=168">Hereditary Talent and Character</a>,” <cite>Macmillan’s Magazine</cite>, June 1865, 157–166.</li>
			<li>William Bateson, “<a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=umn.31951d00400715m;seq=64">Problems of Heredity as a Subject for Horticultural Investigation</a>,” <cite>Journal of the Royal Horticultural Society</cite> 25 (1900): 54–61.</li>
			<li>Charles Davenport, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.hc19hh">Heredity in Relation to Eugenics</a></cite> (1911), iii–vi, 1–5.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 256–273, 307–313; Diane Paul, <cite>Controlling Human Heredity, 1865 to the Present</cite> (1995).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 24: <i>No class</i></h5>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, March 27: Creative Evolution <!--(55 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Henri Bergson, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=hvd.32044021581178">Creative Evolution</a></cite> (1907), translated by Arthur Mitchell (1911), ix–xv, 84–97, 163–165, 176–185, 251–271.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 317–322; R. C. Grogin, <cite>The Bergsonian Controversy in France, 1900–1914</cite> (1988).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, March 29: The Scopes Monkey Trial and the Revival of Creationism <!--(27 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>William Jennings Bryan, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015026299282">In His Image</a></cite> (1922), 86–94, 102–109, 122–127, 132–135.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 375–381; Numbers, <cite>Creationists</cite>; Edward J. Larson, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.00666.0001.001">Summer for the Gods: The Scopes Trial and America’s Continuing Debate over Science and Religion</a></cite> (1997); Adam R. Shapiro, <cite>Trying Biology: The Scopes Trial, Textbooks, and the Antievolution Movement in American Schools</cite> (2013).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="synthesis">The Evolutionary Synthesis: Is Evolution Progressive?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, March 31: Population Genetics and the Modern Synthesis <!--(17 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>R.A. Fisher, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.27468">The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection</a></cite> (1930), vii–x, 256–258.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, <cite>Genetics and the Origin of Species</cite> (1937), 3–12.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 325–340; Vassiliki Betty Smokovitis, <cite>Unifying Biology: The Evolutionary Synthesis and Evolutionary Biology</cite> (1996); Robert D. Kohler, <cite>Lords of the Fly: Drosophila Genetics and the Experimental Life</cite> (1994).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 3: Evolutionary Progress <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Julian Huxley, <cite>Evolution: The Modern Synthesis</cite> (1942), 556–569, 575–578.</li> <!--Pages missing from scan-->
			<li>George Gaylord Simpson, <cite>The Meaning of Evolution</cite> (1949), 240–246.</li>
			<li>George Gaylord Simpson, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/40970168">The Concept of Progress in Organic Evolution</a>,” <cite>Social Research</cite> 41 (1974): 46–51.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 340–346; Michael Ruse, <cite>Monad to Man: The Concept of Progress in Evolutionary Biology</cite> (1996).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 5: The Teilhardian Synthesis <!--(68 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, <cite>The Phenomenon of Man</cite> (1938/1955), translated by Bernard Wall (1959), 11–14, 27–28, 180–184, 237–245, 257–272, 291–299.</li>
			<li>Peter Medawar, <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2252158">review of <cite>The Phenomenon of Man</cite></a>, <cite>Mind</cite> 70 (1961): 99–106.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, <cite>The Biology of Ultimate Concern</cite> (1967), 114–122, 133–137.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 7: <i>No class</i></h5>
		<ul>
			<li><i>Online exhibit due <a href="book">on an evolutionary book as a material text</a>.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 10: Scientific Creationism <!--(22 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>John C. Whitcomb and Henry M. Morris, <cite>The Genesis Flood</cite> (1961), xix–xxii, xxv–xxix, 63–70.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4444260">Nothing in Biology Makes Sense Except in the Light of Evolution</a>,” <cite>American Biology Teacher</cite> 35 (1973): 125–129.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Numbers, <cite>Creationists</cite>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 12: The Evolution of Human Race <!--(34 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Carleton Putnam, <cite><a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=uc1.b3365886">Race and Reason: A Yankee View</a></cite> (1961), vii–viii, 1, 36–37, 40–41.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a107063">A Bogus ‘Science’ of Race Prejudice</a>,” <cite>Journal of Heredity</cite> 52 (1961): 189–190.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, <cite>Mankind Evolving: The Evolution of the Human Species</cite> (1962), 253–257, 266–271, 285–286.</li>
			<li>Theodosius Dobzhansky, “A Debatable Account of the Origin of Races,” <cite>Scientific American</cite>, February 1963, 169–170, 172.</li>
			<li>Richard Lewontin, “The Apportionment of Human Diversity,” <cite>Evolutionary Biology</cite> 6 (1972): 381–387, 396–397.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 278–284, 302–305, 353–356; Lee D. Baker, <cite>From Savage to Negro: Anthropology and the Construction of Race, 1896–1954</cite> (1998); John P. Jackson, Jr., <cite>Science for Segregation: Race, Law, and the Case against Brown v. Board of Education</cite> (2005).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 14: Periodic Extinctions and Punctuated Equilibria <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Niles Eldridge, “‘A Battle of Words,’” in <cite>The Third Culture</cite>, edited by John Brockman (1995), 120–125.</li>
			<li>Niles Eldridge and Stephen Jay Gould, “<a href="http://www.blackwellpublishing.com/ridley/classictexts/eldredge.pdf">Punctuated Equilibria: An Alternative to Phyletic Gradualism</a>,” in <cite>Models in Paleobiology</cite>, edited by Thomas J.M. Schopf (1972), 83–98, 108–115.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 347–353; David Sepkoski, <cite>Rereading the Fossil Record: The Growth of Paleobiology as an Evolutionary Discipline</cite> (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="adaptationism">Adaptationism: Does Natural Selection Explain All Traits?</h4>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 17: Biology as an Information Science <!--(32 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>George C. Williams, “‘A Package of Information,’” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 39–47.</li>
			<li>Richard Dawkins, <cite>The Selfish Gene</cite> (1976), 1–11.</li>
			<li>Richard Dawkins, “‘A Survival Machine,’” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 75–86.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 356–361.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 19: Sociobiology <!--(22 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>E.O. Wilson, <cite>Sociobiology</cite> (1975), 3–6, 547–551, 559–565, 574–575.</li>
			<li>Sociobiology Study Group of Science for the People, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1297246">Sociobiology: Another Biological Determinism</a>,” <cite>BioScience</cite> 26 (1976): 182, 184–186.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 21: The Descent of Woman <!--(39 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Elaine Morgan, <cite>The Descent of Woman</cite> (1972), 1–13, 26–33.</li>
			<li>Sarah Blaffer Hrdy, <cite>The Woman That Never Evolved</cite> (1981), 1–15, 189–191.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Donna Haraway, <cite>Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</cite> (1989); Erika Lorraine Milam, <cite>Looking for a Few Good Males: Female Choice in Evolutionary Biology</cite> (2010).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Monday, April 24: Critiques of Adaptationism <!--(30 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Stephen Jay Gould, “‘The Pattern of Life’s History,’” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 52–64.</li>
			<li>Stephen Jay Gould and Richard C. Lewontin, “<a href="http://www.blackwellpublishing.com/ridley/classictexts/gould.pdf">The Spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian Paradigm</a>,” <cite>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London</cite> 205 (1979): 581–597.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Bowler, <cite>Evolution</cite>, 361–374.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Wednesday, April 26: The Revival of Natural Theology <!--(47 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Richard Dawkins, <cite>The Blind Watchmaker</cite> (1986), 1–9.</li>
			<li>William A. Dembski, “The Logical Underpinnings of Intelligent Design,” in <cite>Debating Design: From Darwin to DNA</cite>, edited by William A. Dembski and Michael Ruse (2004), 311–329.</li>
			<li>Michael J. Behe, “Irreducible Complexity: Obstacle to Darwinian Evolution,” in Dembski and Ruse, <cite>Debating Design</cite>, 352–355.</li>
			<li>Kenneth R. Miller, “The Flagellum Unspun: The Collapse of ‘Irreducible Complexity,’” in Dembski and Ruse, <cite>Debating Design</cite>, 81–95.</li>
			<li class="reference">Reference: Numbers, <cite>Creationists</cite>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, April 28: Symbiogenesis <!--(41 pages)--></h5>
		<ul>
			<li>Lynn Margulis, “‘Gaia Is a Tough Bitch,’” in Brockman, <cite>Third Culture</cite>, 130–140.</li>
			<li>Lynn Margulis and Dorion Sagan, <cite>Acquiring Genomes: A Theory of the Origin of Species</cite> (2002), xi–xvi, 11–23, 51–56, 201–205.</li>
			<li><i>Paper due analyzing the stakes of a particular evolution controversy.</i></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h5>Friday, May 5: <i>Final exam from 8:00 to 10:00</i></h5>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="biology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="science" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="geology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="white supremacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the evolution of life generally and humanity in particular became scientific orthodoxy in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, scientists and other intellectuals debated what this meant. Some conceptions of God were compatible with evolution and others were not, for example, but the inverse was also true: certain conceptions of evolution were compatible with God and others were not. And at the same time, some conceptions of evolution emphasized cooperation and suggested humans would achieve the happiest lives through socialism, while others emphasized the roles of competition and “survival of the fittest” and suggested that capitalism was a better system for human achievement. Some theories of human evolution justified white supremacy, while others suggested racial equality. As a result, debates about biology were often also debates about religion and politics, and the three fields were repeatedly re-formed together.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">America and the Cold War World, 1945–1991</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2016/coldwar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="America and the Cold War World, 1945–1991" /><published>2016-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2016/coldwar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2016/coldwar/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for America in the Cold War World, 1945–1991, a course offered in fall 2016 as HIST 465 at the University of Southern California. This is a course on the political and cultural history of the United States in its global context. We’ll seek to understand how the rivalry between the United States and the Soviet Union shaped how Americans lived their lives and exercised power, paying particular attention to American science, technology, media, popular culture, and family life, as well as to Americans’ engagements with the rest of the world.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Thursday afternoons, 2:00 to 4:50, from August 25 to December 1 in Verna and Peter Dauterive Hall room 107. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours on Wednesdays from 3:00 to 5:00 in Social Sciences Building room 281, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>

<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you read and think about them before each class meeting. Each week I will expect you post a short reaction to the reading the day before class using Blackboard’s blog feature. You can use this as an opportunity to raise questions, to comment on arguments you found particularly surprising or compelling, or to suggest ways the reading might relate to previous readings or forthcoming assignments.</p>

<p>Your first larger assignment will be to develop your own analysis of <a href="film">a film</a> in the context of the Cold War, and to present it in a short paper of about five pages. Your second assignment will be a contribution to an online exhibit on America in the Cold War that we’ll produce together as a class. A final assignment will require you to develop your own historical analysis of an event, person, or cultural or political phenomenon, and to present an argument about how your subject shaped, and was shaped by, America in the Cold War world. That final project, which may build on your work for either of the earlier two assignments, may take the form of a traditional research paper of 15–20 pages, or you may speak with me about presenting it in another medium; in either case, you will have the opportunities to get feedback on a short proposal and a brief presentation as you work on your project. Your grade for the course will be based 20% on your film analysis, 20% on your contribution to the online guide, 30% on your final project, and 30% on your reading responses and engaged and insightful participation in discussions.</p>

<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>Please purchase the following three books, or plan to borrow them from Leavey Library’s circulation desk, where they will be on reserve. The first two are available at the <a href="https://uscbookstore.com/">USC Bookstores</a>; <cite>The Culture of the Cold War</cite> is out of print, so please seek out a used or library copy.</p>

<ul>
	<li>Robert J. McMahon, <cite>The Cold War: A Very Short Introduction</cite> (2003).</li>
	<li>Jeremi Suri, <cite>Power and Protest: Global Revolution and the Rise of Detente</cite> (2003).</li>
	<li>Stephen J. Whitfield, <cite>The Culture of the Cold War</cite>, second edition (1996, revised from 1991 original).</li>
</ul>

<p>All other readings will be available through links below. If you prefer print to reading off a screen, though, you may still want to buy or borrow a few more books. The ones we’ll be reading substantial chunks of, which will also be available on reserve at Leavey, include:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Thomas Borstelmann, <cite>The Cold War and the Color Line: American Race Relations in the Global Arena</cite> (2001).</li>
	<li>Michael D. Gordin, <cite>Five Days in August: How World War II Became a Nuclear War</cite> (2007).</li>
	<li>Van Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left: An Interpretive History</a></cite> (2005).</li>
	<li>Elaine Tyler May, <cite>Homeward Bound: American Families in the Cold War Era</cite>, revised edition (2008, revised from 1988 original).</li>
	<li>Lisa McGirr, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.02237.0001.001">Suburban Warriors: The Origins of the New American Right</a></cite> (2002).</li>
	<li>Odd Arne Westad, <cite>The Global Cold War: Third World Interventions and the Making of Our Times</cite> (2005).</li>
</ul>

<p class="box">Boxes like this one contain suggestions for additional reading. You might want to read beyond the assigned reading based on your curiosity, as research for an assignment, or ideally for both reasons, as you use an assignment to pursue your own interests.</p>


<h3>Schedule</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>August 25: Introduction</h4>
		<ul>
			<li><i>In class:</i> George Orwell, “<a href="http://orwell.ru/library/articles/ABomb/english/e_abomb">You and the Atomic Bomb</a>” (1945), Harry Truman, “<a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/features/truman-hiroshima/">Statement by the President of the United States</a>” (1945), and Stanley Kubrick, <cite>Dr. Strangelove or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb</cite> (1964).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 1: The Atomic Age <!--(148 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Eric Schlosser, “<a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/almost-everything-in-dr-strangelove-was-true">Almost Everything in <cite>Dr. Strangelove</cite> Was True</a>,” <cite>New Yorker</cite> (2014).</li>
			<li>Michael D. Gordin, <cite><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt163tcm5">Five Days in August: How World War II Became a Nuclear War</a></cite> (2007), chapters 1, 3, and 6–7.</li>
			<li>Naomi Oreskes, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qf6k8.5">Science in the Origins of the Cold War</a>,” in <cite>Science and Technology in the Global Cold War</cite>, edited by Naomi Oreskes and John Krige (2014).</li>
			<li>Paul Boyer, <cite>By the Bomb’s Early Light: American Thought and Culture at the Dawn of the Atomic Age</cite> (1985), chapters 1 and 26–27, and epilogue.</li>
			<li class="box">For more on Cold War science, see Audra J. Wolfe, <cite>Competing with the Soviets: Science, Technology, and the State in Cold War America</cite> (2013) and its bibliography. On nuclear weapons in the context of the U.S. military, see Eric Schlosser, <cite>Command and Control: Nuclear Weapons, the Damascus Accident, and the Illusion of Safety</cite> (2013), and Alex Wellerstein’s blog <a href="http://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/">Restricted Data</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 8: Soviet and American Systems <!--(129 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Robert J. McMahon, <cite>The Cold War: A Very Short Introduction</cite> (2003), chapters 1–2.</li>
			<li>Odd Arne Westad, <cite>The Global Cold War: Third World Interventions and the Making of Our Times</cite> (2005), introduction and chapters 1–2.</li>
			<li>Raymond Williams, “Capitalism,” “Communism,” “Democracy,” “Imperialism,” “Liberal,” and “Socialist,” in <cite>Keywords: A Vocabulary for Culture and Society</cite>, revised edition (1983, revised from 1976 original).</li>
			<li>David F. Ruccio, “<a href="http://search.credoreference.com/content/entry/nyupacs/capitalism/">Capitalism</a>,” in <cite>Keywords for American Cultural Studies</cite>, edited by Bruce Burgett and Glenn Hendler (2014).</li>
			<li>Nikhil Pal Singh, “<a href="http://search.credoreference.com/content/entry/nyupacs/liberalism/">Liberalism</a>,” in Burgett and Hendler, <cite>Keywords for American Cultural Studies</cite>.</li>
            <li class="box">John Lewis Gaddis, <cite>The Cold War: A New History</cite> (2005) is a standard history of the Cold War as a bipolar conflict. <cite><a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/series/cambridge-history-of-the-cold-war/DEFB061DD8FD3DA500549912A13F03CE">The Cambridge History of the Cold War</a></cite>, edited by Melvyn P. Leffler and Odd Arne Westad (2010), is an extensive, three-volume collection of essays. For more on the cultural Cold War, see Audra J. Wolfe’s <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160314004755/http://backlist.cc/lists/cultural-cold-war">introductory bibliography</a>.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 15: Anticommunism and the Domestic Cold War <!--(150 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Stephen J. Whitfield, <cite>The Culture of the Cold War</cite>, second edition (1996, revised from 1991 original), chapters 1–2, 4, 6, and 8–9.</li>
			<li class="box">Starting places for additional reading include Ellen Schrecker, <cite>Many Are the Crimes: McCarthyism in America</cite> (1998); Thomas Doherty, <cite>Cold War, Cool Medium: Television, McCarthyism, and American Culture</cite> (2003); and David K. Johnson, <cite>The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government</cite> (2004).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 22: Nuclear Families <!--(144 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Kenneth T. Jackson, <cite>Crabgrass Frontier: The Suburbanization of the United States</cite> (1985), chapters 13–14.</li>
			<li>Elaine Tyler May, <cite>Homeward Bound: American Families in the Cold War Era</cite>, revised edition (2008, revised from 1988 original), introduction and chapters 1, 4, and 6–7.</li>
			<li class="box">For more on redlining and segregation, see chapter 11 of <cite>Crabgrass Frontier</cite> and Ta-Nehisi Coates, “<a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2014/06/the-case-for-reparations/361631/">The Case for Reparations</a>” (2014). Ta-Nehisi Coates, “<a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2014/06/home-is-where-the-hatred-is/373510/">Home is Where the Hatred Is</a>” (2014) is a bibliography. On how experts changed cities during the Cold War, see Jennifer S. Light, <cite>From Warfare to Welfare: Defense Intellectuals and Urban Problems in Cold War America</cite> (2003).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>September 29: The Global Cold War <!--(149 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McMahon, <cite>Cold War</cite>, chapters 3–5.</li>
			<li>Westad, <cite>Global Cold War</cite>, chapter 3.</li>
			<li>Greg Grandin, <cite>The Last Colonial Massacre: Latin America in the Cold War</cite> (2004), preface and introduction.</li>
			<li>Jacob Darwin Hamblin, <cite>Arming Mother Nature: The Birth of Catastrophic Environmentalism</cite> (2013), chapter 6.</li>
			<li class="box">There are many directions to go for additional reading, but for samples of recent essays see <cite>Environmental Histories of the Cold War</cite>, edited by J. R. McNeill and Corinna R. Unger (2010), and <cite>The Cold War in the Third World</cite>, edited by Robert J. McMahon (2013). The Korean War is conspicuously absent from cultural histories of the Cold War, but for diplomatic and military history see Bruce Cumings, <cite>The Korean War: A History</cite> (2010); Wada Haruki, <cite>The Korean War: An International History</cite>, translated by Frank Baldwin (2014); and Allan R. Millett, <cite>The Korean War</cite>, The Essential Bibliography Series (2007).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>Monday, October 3: Paper due <a href="film">contextualizing a film</a></h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 6: Black Liberation Movements I <!--(136 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Thomas Borstelmann, <cite>The Cold War and the Color Line: American Race Relations in the Global Arena</cite> (2001), prologue and chapters 2–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 13: Black Liberation Movements II <!--(147 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Borstelmann, <cite>Cold War and the Color Line</cite>, chapters 5–6, and epilogue.</li>
			<li>Van Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left: An Interpretive History</a></cite> (2005), chapter 9.</li>
			<li>Ryan J. Kirkby, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/crv.2011.0001">‘The Revolution Will Not Be Televised’: Community Activism and the Black Panther Party, 1966–1971</a>,” <cite>Canadian Review of American Studies</cite> (2011).</li>
			<li class="box">Chapters 4 and 9 of <a href="http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/bbm%3A978-1-4039-8014-4%2F1.pdf">the bibliography of <cite>Rethinking the New Left</cite></a> are important starting points for further reading, as is the <a href="http://www.aaihs.org/blackpanthersyllabus/">#blackpanthersyllabus</a>, compiled by Keisha N. Blain, Ashley Farmer, and Dara Vance (2016). Joshua Bloom and Waldo E. Martin, Jr., <cite>Black Against Empire: The History and Politics of the Black Panther Party</cite> (2012) is a detailed narrative history of the BPP.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4 class="newpage">October 20: The Vietnam War <!--(154 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Jeremi Suri, <cite>Power and Protest: Global Revolution and the Rise of Detente</cite> (2003), introduction and chapters 4–5.</li>
			<li>Christian G. Appy, <cite>American Reckoning: The Vietnam War and Our National Identity</cite> (2015), introduction and chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left</a></cite>, chapter 8.</li>
			<li class="box">Even without leaving campus you can find hundreds of books on the Vietnam War, as you can see for yourself by browsing DS557 to DS559 in Doheny Library. Starting places for further reading include the rest of <cite>American Reckoning</cite>; Mark Atwood Lawrence, <cite>The Vietnam War: A Concise International History</cite> (2008); and <cite>A Vietnam War Reader: A Documentary History from American and Vietnamese Perspectives</cite>, edited by Michael H. Hunt (2010).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 27: Detente and New Radicalisms <!--(154 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McMahon, <cite>Cold War</cite>, chapter 7.</li>
			<li>Suri, <cite>Power and Protest</cite>, chapter 6 and conclusion.</li>
			<li>Gosse, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4039-8014-4">Rethinking the New Left</a></cite>, chapters 10–13.</li>
			<li class="box">Again, <a href="http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/bbm%3A978-1-4039-8014-4%2F1.pdf">the bibliography of <cite>Rethinking the New Left</cite></a> is a good starting point for further reading.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>Monday, October 31: Contribution due to <a href="http://coldwar.collopy.net/exhibits/show/assignment/assignment1">online exhibit</a></h4>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>November 3: New Conservatisms I <!--(150 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lisa McGirr, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.02237.0001.001">Suburban Warriors: The Origins of the New American Right</a></cite> (2002), introduction and chapters 2–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 10: New Conservatisms II <!--(142 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McGirr, <cite><a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.02237.0001.001">Suburban Warriors</a></cite>, chapters 5–6, and epilogue.</li>
			<li>Corey Robin, <cite>The Reactionary Mind: Conservatism from Edmund Burke to Sarah Palin</cite> (2011), pages 3–17.</li>
			<li>Daniel T. Rodgers, <cite>Age of Fracture</cite> (2011), prologue and chapter 1.</li>
			<li class="box">Other starting places for reading on Cold War conservatism include Rick Perlstein’s trilogy <cite>Before the Storm: Barry Goldwater and the Unmaking of the American Consensus</cite> (2001), <cite>Nixonland: The Rise of a President and the Fracturing of America</cite> (2008), and <cite>The Invisible Bridge: The Fall of Nixon and the Rise of Reagan</cite> (2014), as well as <a href="http://www.publicbooks.org/feature/trump-syllabus-20">Trump Syllabus 2.0</a>, compiled by N. D. B. Connolly and Keisha N. Blain (2016), and Sean Wilentz, <cite>The Age of Reagan: A History, 1974–2008</cite> (2008).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>Monday, November 14: Final project proposal due</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 17: Ends of the Cold War and Beyond <!--(139 pages)--></h4>
		<ul>
			<li>McMahon, <cite>Cold War</cite>, chapter 8.</li>
			<li>Francis Fukuyama, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24027184">The End of History?</a>” <cite>National Interest</cite>, Summer 1989.</li>
			<li>John Lewis Gaddis, <cite>We Now Know: Rethinking Cold War History</cite> (1997), chapter 10.</li>
			<li>Jon Wiener, <cite>How We Forgot the Cold War: A Historical Journey across America</cite> (2012), introduction, chapters 1 and 21, conclusion, and epilogue.</li>
			<li>Appy, <cite>American Reckoning</cite>, chapter 11.</li>
			<li class="box">Few historians have yet written extensively about the 1980s and beyond, though <cite>Age of Fracture</cite> and <cite>The Age of Reagan</cite> are important exceptions. For more historiography of the Cold War, see <cite>Cold War Triumphalism: The Misuse of History after the Fall of Communism</cite>, edited by Ellen Schrecker (2004), and <cite>Uncertain Empire: American History and the Idea of the Cold War</cite>, edited by Joel Isaac and Duncan Bell (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 24: <i>No class for Thanksgiving</i></h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 1: Final project presentations</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 8: Final project due</h4>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="war" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="liberalism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="white supremacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for America in the Cold War World, 1945–1991, a course offered in fall 2016 as HIST 465 at the University of Southern California. This is a course on the political and cultural history of the United States in its global context. We’ll seek to understand how the rivalry between the United States and the Soviet Union shaped how Americans lived their lives and exercised power, paying particular attention to American science, technology, media, popular culture, and family life, as well as to Americans’ engagements with the rest of the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="war" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="fascism" /><category term="New York" /><category term="California" /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Race Relationships: Collegiality and Demarcation in Physical Anthropology</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/race-relationships/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Race Relationships: Collegiality and Demarcation in Physical Anthropology" /><published>2015-05-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-05-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/race-relationships</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/race-relationships/"><![CDATA[In 1962, anthropologist Carleton Coon argued in <cite>The Origin of Races</cite> that some human races had evolved further than others. Among his most vocal critics were geneticist Theodosius Dobzhansky and anthropologist Ashley Montagu, each of whom had known Coon for decades. I use this episode, and the long relationships between scientists that preceded it, to argue that scientific research on race was intertwined not only with political projects to conserve or reform race relations, but also with the relationships scientists shared as colleagues. Demarcation between science and pseudoscience, between legitimate research and scientific racism, involved emotional as well as intellectual labor.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="science" /><category term="biology" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="liberalism" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="white supremacy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 1962, anthropologist Carleton Coon argued in The Origin of Races that some human races had evolved further than others. Among his most vocal critics were geneticist Theodosius Dobzhansky and anthropologist Ashley Montagu, each of whom had known Coon for decades. I use this episode, and the long relationships between scientists that preceded it, to argue that scientific research on race was intertwined not only with political projects to conserve or reform race relations, but also with the relationships scientists shared as colleagues. Demarcation between science and pseudoscience, between legitimate research and scientific racism, involved emotional as well as intellectual labor.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technology and Society</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology and Society" /><published>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesday evenings, 6:00 to 9:00, from September 2 to December 9 in Williams Hall room 219. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Tuesdays from 5:00 to 6:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>
<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you <a href="reading">read and think about them</a> before each class meeting. Your engaged and insightful participation in discussions will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<p>The other assignments consist of three short papers, of approximately five pages each. I’ll provide more detailed prompts, but in short <a href="politics">the first paper</a> should present an argument about whether and how a particular technology “has politics,” <a href="observing">the second</a> should describe and analyze your observation of people using technology, and <a href="history">the third</a> should present a brief history of a technology of your choice. You will have an opportunity to submit a draft, get my feedback, and revise your paper before I grade it. Each paper will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>The following four books, which we’ll be reading cover-to-cover or nearly so, are available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> is also available online, and other readings will be available through links below.</p>
<ul id="books">
	<li>Lynn White, Jr., <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> (1962).</li>
	<li>Thomas J. Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet: Technology and Culture from the Renaissance to the Present</cite>, second edition (2011, revised from 2004 original).</li>
	<li>Ruth Schwartz Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother: The Ironies of Household Technology from the Open Hearth to the Microwave</cite> (1983).</li>
	<li>David Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old: Technology and Global History since 1900</cite> (2007).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Schedule</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>September 2: Introduction</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 9: Technologies of Feudalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Langdon Winner, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/20024652">Do Artifacts Have Politics?</a>” (1980).</li>
			<li>White, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite>, preface and chapters 1 and 2.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, preface and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 16: Roots of Capitalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lewis Mumford, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01149.0001.001">Technics and Civilization</a></cite> (1934), objectives and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Cynthia Cockburn, <cite>Machinery of Dominance: Women, Men, and Technical Know-How</cite> (1985), introduction and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 2.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 23: Print Culture</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Marshall McLuhan, <cite>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</cite> (1964), chapters 1, 16, and 18.</li>
			<li>Elizabeth Eisenstein, <cite>The Printing Revolution in Early Modern Europe</cite>, second edition (2005, abridged from <cite>The Printing Press as an Agent of Change: Communications and Cultural Transformations in Early-Modern Europe</cite>, 1979), introduction and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li>Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar, <cite>Laboratory Life: The Construction of Scientific Facts</cite>, second edition (1986, revised from 1979 original), pages 43–53.</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule" style="page-break-before: always">
		<h4>September 30: The Industrialization of Manufacturing</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 3.</li>
			<li>Walter Licht, <cite>Industrializing America: The Nineteenth Century</cite> (1995), introduction and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li>Judith A. McGaw, “Gender and Papermaking” (1998, abridged from <cite>Most Wonderful Machine: Mechanization and Social Change in Berkshire Paper Making, 1801–1885</cite>, 1987).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 7: The Industrialization of Time and Space</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 4.</li>
			<li>Wolfgang Schivelbusch, <cite>The Railway Journey: The Industrialization of Time and Space in the 19th Century</cite> (1986), chapters 1–6.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 14: The Industrialization of Housework</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother</cite>, chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 21: Technological Systems</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Thomas P. Hughes, <cite>American Genesis: A Century of Invention and Technological Enthusiasm 1870–1970</cite> (1989), introduction and chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Leo Marx, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2010.0009"><i>Technology</i>: The Emergence of a Hazardous Concept</a>” (2010, revised from 1997 original).</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>October 28: Modern Cities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 6.</li>
			<li>David Nye, <cite>Electrifying America: Social Meanings of a New Technology, 1880–1940</cite> (1990), preface and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 4: Modern Media</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Friedrich A. Kittler, <cite>Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</cite> (1999, translated from 1986 German original), pages 1–37.</li>
			<li>Susan J. Douglas, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01134.0001.001">Inventing American Broadcasting, 1899–1922</a></cite> (1987), introduction and chapter 6.</li>
			<li>Claude S. Fischer, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb00141.0001.001">America Calling: A Social History of the Telephone to 1940</a></cite> (1992), chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 11: Alternative Modernities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5.</li>
			<li>Paul R. Josephson, <cite>Would Trotsky Wear a Bluetooth? Technological Utopianism under Socialism, 1917–1989</cite> (2010), introduction and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 18: The Industrialization of Violence</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 7.</li>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 6 and 7.</li>
			<li>Paul N. Edwards, <cite><a href="http://cognet.mit.edu/book/closed-world">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (1996), pages 1–27.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>November 25: <i>No class</i></h4>
		<ul>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 2: Globalization</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 3, 4, 8 and conclusion.</li>
			<li>Carroll Pursell, <cite>The Machine in America: A Social History of Technology</cite>, second edition (2007, revised from 1994 original), chapter 13.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 9: Technological Systems Revisited</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapters 9 and 10.</li>
			<li>Nathan Ensmenger, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2012.0126">The Digital Construction of Technology: Rethinking the History of Computers in Society</a>” (2012).</li>
			<li>Paolo Pedercini, “<a href="http://www.molleindustria.org/blog/videogames-and-the-spirit-of-capitalism/">Videogames and the Spirit of Capitalism</a>” (2014).</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MIT, Ethics, and the Prosecution of Aaron Swartz</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/aaron-swartz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MIT, Ethics, and the Prosecution of Aaron Swartz" /><published>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2013/aaron-swartz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/aaron-swartz/"><![CDATA[<p>
	On January 11, autodidact, hacker, and activist <a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/">Aaron Swartz</a> committed suicide in the midst of a draconian prosecution for using guest access to MIT’s network to download millions of articles from JSTOR. I’d only had a few brief conversations with Aaron on Twitter, but I read his blog for almost a decade, making his projects and ideas a steady presence in my life. In the words of Grace Llewellyn’s <a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2674846W/The_Teenage_Liberation_Handbook"><cite>Teenage Liberation Handbook</cite></a>, for which Aaron and I <a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/productivity">shared an affection</a> as unschoolers, Aaron was a “glorious generalist,” someone who has deep interests but, rather than obsessing, searches for connections between them and everything else. The world needs such people. I was crushed by Aaron’s death.
</p>
<!--more-->
<p>
	On Tuesday, MIT released its review panel’s report on “<a href="http://swartz-report.mit.edu/docs/report-to-the-president.pdf">MIT and the Prosecution of Aaron Swartz</a>.” Those of us interested in the case have been anticipating this report, particularly given the respect many of us have for computer scientist <a href="http://groups.csail.mit.edu/mac/users/hal/">Hal Abelson</a>, who was charged by MIT’s president with writing it. Personally, I learned how to program when I was about ten from <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/books/logo-macintosh">a book by Abelson and his daughter</a>, and still appreciate his approach to computer science pedagogy and work with foundations like <a href="http://creativecommons.org/">Creative Commons</a> and the <a href="http://fsf.org/">Free Software Foundation</a>.
</p>
<p>
	The Abelson report effectively depicts an MIT administration telling itself it was neutral in the case while cooperating with the prosecution, particularly by allowing prosecutors to repeatedly meet with witnesses without an MIT lawyer present once MIT had granted them initial permission, a courtesy they did not extend to the defense. It depicts an MIT that didn’t see itself as Aaron’s victim, but also never recognized its own role as legislator given the use of the <a href="http://ist.mit.edu/network/rules">MITNet Rules of Use</a> to support a claim, under the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Fraud_and_Abuse_Act">Computer Fraud and Abuse Act</a>, that Aaron exceeded authorized access to MIT’s network. Within MIT, only incoming Media Lab director <a href="http://joi.ito.com/">Joi Ito</a> suggested that MIT question the premise of the prosecution, writing to MIT’s lawyers that “since it is a criminal case and the prosecutor needs to prove beyond reasonable doubt that it was unauthorized, I think MIT is in the position to ‘cast doubt’ if it desires.” As defense attorneys asked MIT to speak out against the prosecution with increasing urgency, the Institute’s main reason for not doing so seems to have been that they believed it might actually hurt Aaron’s case, that they believed—as Aaron’s friend <a href="http://lessig.tumblr.com/post/40347463044/prosecutor-as-bully">Lawrence Lessig wrote</a> immediately after Aaron’s death—that prosecutor <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Heymann">Stephen Heymann</a> was a bully who interpreted opposition as a personal attack on his authority and responded by escalating.
</p>
<p>
	The report is nonetheless a disappointment. I don’t think I saw until now MIT President L. Rafael Reif’s formal letter to Abelson requesting the report, and I certainly hadn’t realized that Abelson’s charge was limited to fact-finding and “identify[ing] the issues that warrant further analysis in order to learn from these events.” Since Abelson and his colleagues on the review panel, economist <a href="http://economics.mit.edu/faculty/pdiamond">Peter Diamond</a> and lawyer <a href="http://grossolaw.com/grosso.htm">Andrew Grosso</a>, didn’t discover any shocking malfeasance on the part of MIT, their recommendations (which take the form of questions to avoid exceeding their charge) are rather mundane, including reforming MIT’s data retention policies and holding “a series of campus-wide deliberations around issues raised by this report.” The most critical, perhaps, is that MIT “develop additional on-campus expertise for handling potential computer crime incidents” in order to avoid reliance on outside police, reliance that in Aaron’s case inadvertently (from MIT’s perspective) involved the Secret Service.
</p>
<p>
	This limited charge proscribed the review panel from asserting outright that MIT should have behaved differently. The two quotations from their interviews which they include in their conclusion, though, say a lot. One administrator told the review panel, “MIT didn’t do anything wrong, but we didn’t do ourselves proud.” And a friend of Aaron’s pointed out that “neutrality on these cases is an incoherent stance. It’s not the right choice for a tough leader or a moral leader.”
</p>
<div style="text-align: center; font-weight: bold">. . .</div>
<p>
	Early this summer, I taught <a href="/teaching/2013/cyberculture/">a course</a> on the history and culture of the internet. In our discussion of Lessig’s book <a href="http://codev2.cc/"><cite>Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace</cite></a>, I suggested to students that it, like most political writing, was written in the genre of advice for those in power. Its central point is that “cyberspace requires choices” in how it is built, both by programmers and by legislators. Lessig’s message to these influential people was that although their decisions might seem merely technical, they are in fact deeply ethical. Although he was quite pessimistic that those in power would rise to the occasion—“we urgently need to make fundamental choices about values,” wrote Lessig, “but… the government we have now is a failure”—he wrote a book about how governance on the internet ought to function in America.
</p>
<p>
	I also showed my class Aaron’s 2012 Freedom to Connect keynote speech, “<a href="http://www.democracynow.org/2013/1/14/freedom_to_connect_aaron_swartz_1986">How We Stopped SOPA</a>,” and noted a difference in perspective between these two political documents. Aaron’s intended audience was those who are not in power. His message was that they too should seek to influence internet policy, and indeed that this is the way out of Lessig’s trap. “We won this fight because everyone made themselves the hero of their own story,” concluded Aaron. “Everyone took it as their job to save this crucial freedom. They threw themselves into it. They did whatever they could think of to do. They didn’t stop to ask anyone for permission.… The internet really is out of control.”
</p>
<p>
	Internet censorship was an issue on which Swartz and Lessig generally agreed, but their rhetoric appealed to different audiences: to caricature a bit, Lessig’s was technocratic while Swartz’s was rabble-rousing. The lesson I suggested to my students was not that Aaron’s perspective was more productive than Lessig’s; I love Lessig’s critical edge, and since I teach at the University of Pennsylvania, I expect that some of my students will become influential politicians and programmers who may build the internet more humanely under Lessig’s influence. Rather, I suggested that, in considering any political issue, it’s worth thinking through both perspectives. What could you do to improve the world in a particular way if you were in a position of authority? What could you do if you were not? We need to be able to think in both ways because most of us move back and forth between these situations over the course of our lives and even over the course of our days. I, for example, have no more influence than my neighbors in electoral politics, but make hiring and firing decisions as a board member of our local food co-op. In either context, though, I want to act ethically.</p>
<p>
	Because they were not in the role of either prosecutor or defendant, and because Aaron was not formally affiliated with the Institute, MIT’s lawyers and administrators imagined themselves to be neutral, without any ethical interest in the prosecution. The Abelson report reveals that they acted properly, for the most part, with regard to their professional and legal responsibilities. Their largest sins of commission were relatively minor, permitting the prosecutors greater access to witnesses than the defense team and acting on a subpoena which had apparently expired. It also reveals, though, that they failed—“<a href="http://tarensk.tumblr.com/post/56881327662/mit-report-is-a-whitewash-my-statement-in-response">reprehensibly</a>,” as Aaron’s partner Taren Stinebrickner-Kauffman writes, “<a href="https://archives.lessig.org/index6f09.html">more than negligent[ly]</a>,” as Lessig writes—to act on their deeper ethical responsibilities, in particular by not asserting that Aaron hadn’t actually violated their Rules of Use. In short, MIT believed that as long as they played their narrow role in the drama everything would turn out fine; they did not “take it as their job,” as Aaron would have counseled, to consider whether the prosecutor was behaving ethically and how they could influence him. Given that the case concerned not only the use of MIT property, and not only issues of intellectual and practical interest to many MIT students and faculty, but the eminent possibility of a ruined life, this was a grave ethical failure.
</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On January 11, autodidact, hacker, and activist Aaron Swartz committed suicide in the midst of a draconian prosecution for using guest access to MIT’s network to download millions of articles from JSTOR. I’d only had a few brief conversations with Aaron on Twitter, but I read his blog for almost a decade, making his projects and ideas a steady presence in my life. In the words of Grace Llewellyn’s Teenage Liberation Handbook, for which Aaron and I shared an affection as unschoolers, Aaron was a “glorious generalist,” someone who has deep interests but, rather than obsessing, searches for connections between them and everything else. The world needs such people. I was crushed by Aaron’s death.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyberculture</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyberculture" /><published>2013-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Cyberculture (STSC/SOCI 260), a course on histories and cultures of the internet offered in summer 2013 at the University of Pennsylvania. The course might also be called “Several Ways of Looking at the Internet,” “Histories and Cultures of the Internet,” or “Introduction to Internet Studies.” In this course, we will explore how people use the internet to develop new conceptions of identity, build virtual communities, and affect political change. Each class we’ll study an aspect of the history and culture of the internet, covering topics such as hackers, virtuality, sovereignty, and algorithms. We’ll read books, articles, and blogs about historical and contemporary cultures of computing, from Spacewar players and phone phreaks in the 1970s to Google, Facebook, World of Warcraft, WikiLeaks, and Anonymous today. In addition, we’ll explore some of these online communities and projects ourselves, and develop our own analyses of them.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesdays and Thursdays, 1:00 to 4:10, from May 21 to June 27 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 392. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Thursdays from 12:00 to 1:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you read and think about them before each class meeting.</p>

<p>The main component of this course other than discussions is a final project, which will involve developing your own analysis of an online community or phenomenon incorporating some ways of looking at the internet from the course. Such a project could take the form of a traditional research paper of 10–15 pages or an online presentation involving a similar amount of research and analysis; possibilities range from videos and webcomics to Twitter or Tumblr experiments and beyond. Although you are not required to make your project publicly available online, I can suggest from my own experience that it can be more exciting to produce for an audience beyond your instructor and would be happy to talk with you about appropriate online venues for sharing your project.</p>

<p>In order to help you progress toward completing your project over the course of the semester, I will ask that you meet with me to discuss your ideas for your project on May 28 or 30, submit a short (one to three page) proposal by June 6, present a progress report to the class June 11 or 13, submit a draft to me by June 20, and submit the final project on June 27, the last day of class. I will provide feedback at each of these stages. Your grade for the course will be based 20% on your proposal, 20% on your presentation, 30% on your final project, and 30% on your engaged and insightful participation in discussions.</p>

<h3>News</h3>
<p>One of the things we’ll do in this course is use recent history to find ways to think about current events. Accordingly, you may find it interesting or useful for your project to follow some news. <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/"><cite>The Atlantic</cite>’s technology channel</a> is among the best sources. <a href="http://www.wired.com/"><cite>Wired</cite></a> has many sections and blogs of varying quality, and their security blog <a href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/">Threat Level</a> is particularly good.</p>

	<p>The best source for cyberculture news might be Twitter, though, provided you follow the right people. My account is <a href="http://twitter.com/collopy">@collopy</a>, and I’ve made a list of <a href="http://twitter.com/collopy/cyberculture/">some Twitter users relevant to this course</a> that you can subscribe to, including the authors of texts on this syllabus. If you find anything online you’d like to share with the class, please tweet it using the (admittedly silly) hashtag <a href="http://twitter.com/search/realtime?q=%23cyberpenn">#cyberpenn</a>.</p>

<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>Please find a list of required readings below. Many readings are freely available online (and linked here), and I will make most of the others available to students. The exception is <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture</cite> by Fred Turner, the one book we’ll be reading in its entirety, which is available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. Other books are also available at the Penn Book Center for those who would like to own them.</p>

<h3 style="page-break-before: always">Foundations</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>May 21: Introduction</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Mitchell Kapor and John Perry Barlow, “<a href="http://w2.eff.org/Misc/Publications/John_Perry_Barlow/HTML/eff.html">Across the Electronic Frontier</a>” (1990).</li>
			<li>John Perry Barlow, “<a href="http://w2.eff.org/Censorship/Internet_censorship_bills/barlow_0296.declaration">A Declaration of the Independence of Cyberspace</a>” (1996).</li>
			<li>Bruce Schneier, “<a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2013/01/power_and_the_i.html">Power and the Internet</a>” (2013).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>May 23: Hackers</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Steven Levy, <cite>Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution</cite> (1984), <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/729/pg729.html">chapters 1 and 2</a>.</li>
			<li>Adrian Johns, <cite>Piracy: The Intellectual Property Wars from Gutenberg to Gates</cite> (2009), chapter 16.</li>
			<li>Stewart Brand, “<a href="http://wheels.org/spacewar/stone/rolling_stone.html">Spacewar: Fanatic Life and Symbolic Death Among the Computer Bums</a>” (originally in <cite>Rolling Stone</cite>, 1972).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>May 28: Cybernetics</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Fred Turner, <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</cite> (2006), introduction and chapters 1–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
			<h4>May 30: Networks (“The New Economy”)</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Turner, <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture</cite>, chapters 5–8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h3>Virtual Community</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>June 4: Virtuality</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Julian Dibbell, “<a href="http://juliandibbell.com/texts/bungle_vv.html">A Rape in Cyberspace: How an Evil Clown, a Haitian Trickster Spirit, Two Wizards, and a Cast of Dozens Turned a Database Into a Society</a>” (originally in <cite>The Village Voice</cite>, 1993).</li>
		    <li>Sherry Turkle, <cite>Life on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet</cite> (1995), chapters 7–9.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 6: Identity</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lisa Nakamura, <cite>Cybertypes: Race, Ethnicity, and Identity on the Internet</cite> (2002), introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 11: Play</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Bonnie Nardi, <cite><a href="http://doi.org/10.3998/toi.8008655.0001.001">My Life as a Night Elf Priest: An Anthropological Account of World of Warcraft</a></cite> (2010), prologue, chapters 1, 2, and 6–9, and coda.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 13: Networks (Social Network Sites)</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>danah boyd, “<a href="http://www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf">Why Youth (Heart) Social Network Sites: The Role of Networked Publics in Teenage Social Life</a>” (2007).</li>
		    <li>danah boyd, “<a href="http://www.danah.org/papers/2011/WhiteFlight.pdf">White Flight in Networked Publics? How Race and Class Shaped American Teen Engagement with MySpace and Facebook</a>” (2011).</li>
		    <li>Nathan Jurgenson, “<a href="http://mdpi.com/1999-5903/4/1/83/pdf">When Atoms Meet Bits: Social Media, the Mobile Web and Augmented Revolution</a>” (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h3>Politics</h3>
<ul>
		<li>
			<h4>June 18: Sovereignty</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Lawrence Lessig, <cite><a href="http://codev2.cc/download+remix/Lessig-Codev2.pdf">Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace, Version 2.0</a></cite> (2006, revised from 1999), prefaces and chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 20: Resistance</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Andy Greenberg, <cite>This Machine Kills Secrets: How WikiLeakers, Cypherpunks, and Hacktivists Aim to Free the World’s Information</cite> (2012), prologue and chapters 1, 3, and 4.</li>
		    <li>Gabriella Coleman, “<a href="http://canopycanopycanopy.com/15/our_weirdness_is_free">Our Weirdness Is Free</a>” (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 25: Algorithms</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Tarleton Gillespie, “<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Gillespie_2014_The-Relevance-of-Algorithms.pdf">The Relevance of Algorithms</a>” (2012).</li>
		    <li>Eli Pariser, <cite>The Filter Bubble: How the New Personalized Web Is Changing What We Read and How We Think</cite> (2011), introduction and chapters 1, 4, and 6.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
			<h4>June 27: Networks (Infrastructure)</h4>
	    <ul>
	        <li>Andrew Blum, <cite>Tubes: A Journey to the Center of the Internet</cite> (2012), prologue and chapters 1, 2, and 7.</li>
	    </ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Cyberculture (STSC/SOCI 260), a course on histories and cultures of the internet offered in summer 2013 at the University of Pennsylvania. The course might also be called “Several Ways of Looking at the Internet,” “Histories and Cultures of the Internet,” or “Introduction to Internet Studies.” In this course, we will explore how people use the internet to develop new conceptions of identity, build virtual communities, and affect political change. Each class we’ll study an aspect of the history and culture of the internet, covering topics such as hackers, virtuality, sovereignty, and algorithms. We’ll read books, articles, and blogs about historical and contemporary cultures of computing, from Spacewar players and phone phreaks in the 1970s to Google, Facebook, World of Warcraft, WikiLeaks, and Anonymous today. In addition, we’ll explore some of these online communities and projects ourselves, and develop our own analyses of them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taking Over the NRA</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/taking-over-nra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking Over the NRA" /><published>2013-02-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2013-02-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2013/taking-over-nra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/taking-over-nra/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s an episode of <cite>The West Wing</cite>—“<a href="http://westwing.wikia.com/wiki/The_Portland_Trip">The Portland Trip</a>”—in which Republican congressman Matt Skinner quips to presidential aide Josh Lyman, “I never understood why you gun control people don’t all join the NRA. They’ve got two million members, you bring three million to the next meeting, call a vote. ‘All those in favor of tossing guns?’ Bam. Move on.”</p>
<!--more-->

<p>Skinner isn’t exactly proposing direct action, but the president’s staff on <cite>The West Wing</cite> clearly consider this sort of activist politics beneath them. Josh is dismissive not, it seems to me, because it’s a bad idea, but simply because it’s not the way establishment liberals do things. “It’s a heck of a strategy, Matt,” he says. “I’ll bring that up at a meeting.”</p>

<p>As American started talking seriously about gun control in the weeks after December’s shooting at Sandy Hook Elementary School, this scene played over and over in my head. What if a lobbying organization like the National Rifle Association could be made responsive to the public—or at least to those who care enough about its issue to join whether they agree with its current political stances or not? At the very least, this fictional congressman had a more creative approach to gun control activism than the ineffective assault weapons bans championed by many Democratic legislators.</p>

<p>If the NRA is any kind of democracy, it’s representative rather than direct, so I started looking into how the NRA’s Board of Directors is elected. While the Association’s policies regarding elections aren’t available online, you can find blogs where members gripe about the system’s shortcomings and occasionally describe it in some detail. I was intrigued enough to write to the NRA and ask for a copy of their bylaws, which they were kind enough to mail me.</p>

<img style="display: block; margin: auto;" title="Envelope from the NRA" src="/images/envelope.gif" width="357" height="243">

<p>My conclusion is that Skinner’s idea wouldn’t work. Even if you could persuade three million—or five million, or ten million—progressives to join the NRA, the organization’s bylaws ensure they couldn’t take it over. Aaron Sorkin frequently says <a href="http://www.vulture.com/2012/06/aaron-sorkin-newsroom-interview.html">in interviews</a> he can “write about people who are smarter than I am and know more than I do, and I am able to do that simply by being tutored almost phonetically, sometimes.” Much of what passes for intelligence among his characters is merely cleverness. It would not be difficult for an actual Republican congressman to understand that the NRA can resist conquest by “gun control people.” For the rest of us, however, here’s how it works:</p>

<img title="The National Rifle Association of America Bylaws" src="/images/bylaws.gif" style="display: block; float: right; margin: 10px;" width="175" height="375">

<p>In addition to a fairly typical clause offering membership only to those “who subscribe… to the objectives and purposes of the Association,” the bylaws bar new members from voting unless they purchase a “Life Membership,” <a href="https://membership.nrahq.org/forms/signup.asp">currently available for $1000</a>. Article III, section 6, item e, part 1 states that only “lifetime members and annual members with five or more consecutive years of membership… who have attained the age of 18 years and who are citizens of the United States of American shall be entitled to a vote” when electing Directors.</p>

<p>The bylaws also prescribe the process by which aspiring Directors of the NRA get their names on the ballot. Most are nominated by a Nominating Committee (on which <cite>Mother Jones</cite> journalist Frank Smyth has <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2013/01/nra-board-newtown-bushmaster">some interesting reporting</a>) appointed by the Board of Directors and thus unlikely to rock the boat. Alternately, a candidate may be placed on the ballot by a petition of a mere 250 signatures of members eligible to vote.</p>

<p><a href="http://firearmscoalition.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;id=599">According to NRA member Jeff Knox</a>, this petition process was instituted in 1977 as part of “a major member revolt at the annual meeting in Cincinnati [in which] a more politically aggressive faction grabbed the reigns of the organization.” <a href="http://www.thenation.com/blog/172125/how-nra-became-organization-aspiring-vigilantes-part-2">As Rick Perlstein writes</a>, it was in this coup that the NRA became more concerned with opposing gun control than with outdoor sports. Making the NRA more democratic by introducing petitions was a way to keep it accountable to a politically involved membership.</p>

<p>Now, though, the NRA’s membership is in favor of substantially more gun control than their leadership, even if it isn’t flooded with three million “gun control people”; <a href="http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp1300512">74% of NRA members support background checks for all gun purchases</a>. There are a number of reasons why the NRA’s leadership doesn’t reflect membership opinion, but among them is surely that, according to Knox and other members, only 7% of eligible members vote. (This number is probably low, since <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/mojo/2013/01/nra-membership-numbers">it’s likely that many of the NRA’s Life Members are dead</a>, but it’s still probable that only a minority of eligible members vote.) The shortest path to the NRA becoming a more moderate organization might be simply for moderates to run for the Board of Directors—by petition if necessary—and for other moderates to vote for them. The “hardliners” who made the NRA what it is today may have also left a way out.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="conservatism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s an episode of The West Wing—“The Portland Trip”—in which Republican congressman Matt Skinner quips to presidential aide Josh Lyman, “I never understood why you gun control people don’t all join the NRA. They’ve got two million members, you bring three million to the next meeting, call a vote. ‘All those in favor of tossing guns?’ Bam. Move on.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyber-Utopianism Before the Internet</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cyber-utopianism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyber-Utopianism Before the Internet" /><published>2012-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cyber-utopianism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cyber-utopianism/"><![CDATA[<p>In his 2011 book <cite><a href="http://netdelusion.com/">The Net Delusion: The Dark Side of Internet Freedom</a></cite>, <a href="http://evgenymorozov.com/">Evgeny Morozov</a> defines <em>cyber-utopianism</em> as “a naîve belief in the emancipatory nature of online communication that rests on a stubborn refusal to acknowledge its downside.” This belief, he writes, has entered U.S. foreign policy through the State Department’s internet freedom agenda. Its effects can also be seen in the media, as in misplaced enthusiasm about the role of Twitter in the Iranian uprising of 2009. Foundational to Morozov’s portrayal is Andrew Sullivan’s <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/daily-dish/archive/2009/06/the-revolution-will-be-twittered/200478/">announcement on his blog</a> that Iranians began communicating using Twitter after the government shut down the cell phone network. “That a new information technology could be improvised for this purpose so swiftly is a sign of the times,” wrote Sullivan. “You cannot stop people any longer. You cannot control them any longer. They can bypass your established media; they can broadcast to one another; they can organize as never before.”</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Intriguingly, Morozov traces cyber-utopianism to “former hippies’” attempts “to prove that the Internet could deliver what the 1960s couldn’t: boost democratic participation, trigger a renaissance of moribund communities, strengthen associational life, and serve as a bridge from bowling alone to blogging together.” Morozov is right that the counterculture had some influence on the cyber-utopianism of today, but it’s perhaps deeper than he acknowledges. Hippies did not wait for the emergence of the internet to embrace the vision of a networked society; rather, the countercultural politics of the 1960s already incorporated a belief in the democratizing power of decentralized, electronic media. Indeed, despite Sullivan’s suggestion that the people’s power is unprecedented, one can find rhetoric virtually identical to his decades earlier.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" title="Portapak" src="/images/portapak.jpg" alt="" width="370" height="250"/></p>
<p>The focus of this earlier cyber-utopianism was on breaking the oligopoly of broadcast television with cable television, satellites, and other new electronic technologies. Central to this vision was a portable device designed, like the cell phone, for an individual user: Sony’s VideoRover II, released in 1968. This portapak, as users called it, was much lighter and less imposing than traditional television cameras. From the beginning, users interpreted it as a new medium for artistic and political expression. In his 1972 memoir <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL4116949W/The_Stoned_Apocalypse">The Stoned Apocalypse</a></cite>, spiritual seeker and prolific erotica writer Marco Vassi anticipated Sullivan by 37 years: “The enthusiasm for videotape,” he wrote, “came from the evenings we spent using the equipment with each other, to create portraits, and modes of psychological insight, and sheer technological art. I suppose we all had our first flashes of power through those sessions, the realization that if one had access to the technology, he had as strong a voice in shaping the destiny of the world as the politicians and generals.” Many also saw video as an inherently democratic technology that would distribute this power to be heard more equitably.</p>
<p>This ideology was most fully elaborated by the video collective <a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/e/history.html">Raindance</a>, particularly in Michael Shamberg’s 1971 book <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL7098564W/Guerrilla_television">Guerrilla Television</a></cite>. Shamberg, who went on to become a Hollywood producer, presented television itself as a revolutionary technology which had already created a new “electronic environment,” “Media-America.” He was a technological determinist who believed that society was structured by its media; politics was mere superstructure which would follow automatically. “It’s nostalgia,” he wrote, “to think that… balance can be restored politically when politics are a function of Media-America, not vice-versa. Only through a radical re-design of its information structures to incorporate two-way, decentralized inputs can Media-America optimize the feedback it needs to come back to its senses.”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" title="Media-America" src="/images/media-america.jpg" alt="" width="386" height="250"/></p>
<p>Shamberg’s influences are evident even in this short quotation. Foremost among them was media theorist <a href="http://marshallmcluhan.com/biography/">Marshall McLuhan</a>, who proposed that electronic media were creating a new social environment for humanity, a highly participatory “global village.” McLuhan&#8217;s research assistant <a href="http://earthscore.org/about.html">Paul Ryan</a> (no relation to the politician) was an experimental videographer who associated with Raindance; it was Ryan who developed the metaphor Shamberg employed of videography as guerrilla warfare in <a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/volume1nr3/pdf/VOLUME1NR3_art01.pdf">an article</a> in Raindance’s magazine <cite><a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/e/">Radical Software</a></cite>. Both McLuhan and Ryan were in turn deeply influenced by the Jesuit paleontologist and mystic <a href="http://teilharddechardin.org/biography.html">Pierre Teilhard de Chardin</a>, particularly his interpretation of human communication as constituting a global mind or “noosphere.” A more effective noosphere—a “videophere,” in art critic <a href="http://geneyoungblood.com/">Gene Youngblood</a>’s terminology—became the political ideal of experimental videography.</p>
<p>More concretely, Shamberg believed that video would revolutionize particular social relations. “Going out to the suburbs with video cameras and taping commuters,” for example, could show them “how wasted they look from buying the suburban myth.” Being videotaped could sensitize police and prevent brutality. Shamberg’s technological optimism focused specifically on communication technology, as he saw new forms of television and other media as both the sources of social change and the proper replacements for an obsolete political sphere.</p>
<p>There were also those who warned against seeing video as a source of social change, though. Among them was Vassi, himself a founding member of Raindance. “There is some talk, and there will be more, in so-called underground tape circles about the revolutionary impact of tape,” <a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/volume1nr1/pdf/VOLUME1NR1_0020.pdf">wrote Vassi</a> in <cite>Radical Software</cite>. “I think it’s too late for all that. Every innovation in technology brought about by heads will be used by the power-trip neanderthals to furnish a more sophisticated 1984.… I think the thing to watch out for is this: That there be as little talking about all this as possible, not to keep the enemy from overhearing or any of that nonsense, but to guard against coming to believe one’s own rhetoric.”</p>
<p>All of which brings us back to the recent past. In January 2010, a few months after the Iranian uprising, Secretary of State Hillary Clinton delivered a speech, “<a href="http://www.state.gov/secretary/rm/2010/01/135519.htm">Remarks on Internet Freedom</a>,” at the Newseum in Washington. “The spread of information networks is forming a new nervous system for our planet,” she told her audience. “When something happens in Haiti or Hunan, the rest of us learn about it in real time—from real people.” Clinton invoked the same emphasis on direct communication—media without mediation—which Shamberg celebrated in video and Sullivan in Twitter, and the same notion of a global mind which McLuhan and Ryan found in Teilhard. ”Now, in many respects, information has never been so free,” Clinton continued, agreeing with countercultural entrepreneur <a href="http://sb.longnow.org/SB_homepage/">Stewart Brand</a>, who declared in 1984 that “information wants to be free.”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" title="Hillary Clinson" src="/images/clinton.jpg" alt="" width="355" height="200"/></p>
<p>Clinton’s optimism was tempered, though. “We must also recognize that these technologies are not an unmitigated blessing,” she continued. “These tools are also being exploited to undermine human progress and political rights.” Beyond that, we should heed Vassi’s warning and recognize the threat that we will be seduced by our tools and their false but persistent promise of revolutionary change without our active political effort. These information technologies can contribute to the success of political movements, but not if their users see them as replacements for political life.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="video" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="liberalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his 2011 book The Net Delusion: The Dark Side of Internet Freedom, Evgeny Morozov defines cyber-utopianism as “a naîve belief in the emancipatory nature of online communication that rests on a stubborn refusal to acknowledge its downside.” This belief, he writes, has entered U.S. foreign policy through the State Department’s internet freedom agenda. Its effects can also be seen in the media, as in misplaced enthusiasm about the role of Twitter in the Iranian uprising of 2009. Foundational to Morozov’s portrayal is Andrew Sullivan’s announcement on his blog that Iranians began communicating using Twitter after the government shut down the cell phone network. “That a new information technology could be improvised for this purpose so swiftly is a sign of the times,” wrote Sullivan. “You cannot stop people any longer. You cannot control them any longer. They can bypass your established media; they can broadcast to one another; they can organize as never before.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Brainwashing of the Cleveland 5</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cleveland-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Brainwashing of the Cleveland 5" /><published>2012-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cleveland-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cleveland-5/"><![CDATA[<p>On April 30, the FBI arrested five men affiliated with Occupy Cleveland. According to <a href="http://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/352006/bridge-bomb-plot-new-charges.pdf">Special Agent Ryan M. Taylor’s affidavit</a>, Brandon Baxter, Anthony Hayne, Joshua Stafford, Connor Stevens, and Douglas Wright were apprehended “after placing two inert IEDs at the base of the Brecksville-Northfield High Level Bridge and attempting repeatedly to detonate those IEDs.” They did so by dialing a phone number to trigger the devices—a phone number provided by the undercover FBI agent who also sold them the fake explosives.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The <a href="http://cleveland5justice.org/">Cleveland 5</a> face life in prison on three charges, to which they’ve pled not guilty: attempted use of a weapon of mass destruction to destroy property used in interstate commerce, conspiracy to use a weapon of mass destruction to destroy property used in interstate commerce, and attempted use of an explosive device to damage or destroy real property used in interstate commerce. Judge David Dowd, Jr. <a href="http://www.cleveland.com/metro/index.ssf/2012/05/judges_proposal_of_sept_11_tri.html">initially proposed</a> a trial date of September 11, then settled on September 17 after defense attorneys protested.</p>
<p>This was the first time FBI strategies of infiltration and escalation resulted in charges against participants in the Occupy movement. In this case, the agency may be responsible not only for entrapment but for even more egregious malfeasance which amounts to brainwashing.</p>
<p>On April 29—the day before the Cleveland arrests—<cite>The New York Times</cite> published an opinion piece by journalist David K. Shipler under the headline “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/29/opinion/sunday/terrorist-plots-helped-along-by-the-fbi.html?pagewanted=all">Terrorist Plots, Hatched by the F.B.I.</a>” Shipler described an increasingly utilized FBI tactic of fostering terrorist plots in order to catch potential criminals. “Typically,” writes Shipler, “the stings initially target suspects for pure speech—comments to an informer outside a mosque, angry posting on websites, emails with radicals overseas—then woo them into relationships with informers, who are often convicted felons working in exchange for leniency.” Those subjected to this tactic lack the knowledge, connections, and materials necessary to commit a crime, so the FBI supplies them. James Cromitie, for example, was convicted of attempting to bomb synagogues and shoot down military aircraft. “Only the government could have made a ‘terrorist’ out of Mr. Cromitie, whose buffoonery is positively Shakespearean in its scope,” said Judge Colleen McMahon, although she nonetheless sentenced him to 25 years in prison. “Of the 22 most frightening plans for attacks since 9/11 on American soil,” Shipler concluded, “14 were developed in sting operations.”</p>
<p>As in their entrapment of Muslims, the FBI seems to have picked low-hanging fruit in Cleveland: naive young men seeking to make a difference in the world. Even Taylor’s affidavit makes it clear these alleged conspirators were coached extensively by felon <a href="http://www.thesmokinggun.com/documents/fbi-informant-shaquille-azir-756123">Shaquille Azir</a>, an FBI informant similar to those described by Shipler. <a href="http://www.greenisthenewred.com/blog/fbi-anarchist-terrorists-may-day-ohio/5988/">Will Potter writes</a> that “what’s troubling is that the government has had a heavy hand in creating the very plot it thwarted. And on top of that, the defendants, by the admission of the FBI, said repeatedly that they had no intention of harming anyone.” Potter compares the case to that of environmentalist <a href="http://supporteric.org/">Eric McDavid</a>, who was also provided with plans, supplies, and encouragement by an FBI infiltrator.</p>
<p>Azir supplied more than encouragement and fake explosives, however. Based on interviews with friends and family members of the Cleveland 5, <a href="http://www.alternet.org/story/155581/has_the_fbi_launched_a_war_of_entrapment_against_the_occupy_movement?page=entire">Arun Gupta concludes</a> that Azir “provided the five with jobs, money, a place to live, a friendly ear, beer, pot, the prescription stimulant Adderall, and most significant, the ideas and means to carry out a plot conceived by the Bureau itself.” Similarly, <a href="http://www.counterpunch.org/2012/05/21/police-entrapment-of-nonviolent-movements/">Jake Olzen writes</a>, based on an interview with Cleveland activist Richard Schulte, that “Azir would give them a case of beer in the morning,… have them work outside on houses all day, and then give them a case of beer at night. He gave them marijuana and would wear them down by keeping them up late into the night with drinking and conversation—all the while urging them to break away from other groups, keep their arrangement secret and not to trust other activists.”</p>
<p>This treatment was brainwashing—or, as it is sometimes termed, coercive persuasion. The new social environment Azir created meets several of the conditions psychologist Margaret Singer associates with such thought-reform in her book <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL3264926W/Cults_in_Our_Midst">Cults in Our Midst</a></cite>: Azir separated the alleged conspirators from their support networks by suggesting outsiders couldn’t be trusted (a tactic Schulte provocatively describes as using “<a href="http://security.resist.ca/personal/culture.shtml">security culture</a> against activists”), controlled their time by providing them with long days of work, and kept them unaware they were being manipulated by presenting himself as a friend and mentor. According to Gupta, friends described Stafford and Baxter as “highly impressionable,” and Azir took advantage of their vulnerability. Sociologist Richard Ofshe (quoted in <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL6025390W/Brainwash">Brainwash</a></cite> by Dominic Streatfeild) explains that people subjected to such manipulation “make bad decisions because they find themselves in situations that are built to get them to make those decisions.”</p>
<p>In addition to controlling their social environment, Azir manipulated the group physiologically to make them more suggestible. Fatigue obviously helped, and marijuana may have as well: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Cmd=Retrieve&amp;list_uids=417375">Researchers in the 1970s found</a> that “the drug caused an increase in suggestibility similar to that produced by the induction of hypnosis.” Similarly, the National Commission on Marihuana and Drug Abuse’s 1972 report, “Marijuana: A Signal of Misunderstanding,” <a href="http://www.druglibrary.org/schaffer/Library/studies/nc/nc1g_8.htm">stated</a> that “cannabis intoxication produces a heightened suggestibility.” I don’t know if this phenomenon has been exploited by the FBI before. According to John Marks’ classic <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL4097029W/The_search_for_the_Manchurian_candidate">The Search for the “Manchurian Candidate,”</a></cite> though, the Office of Strategic Services used cannabis as a truth drug during World War II. The CIA, its successor agency, later experimented more extensively.</p>
<p>It is not clear whether Azir decided to brainwash the alleged conspirators himself or was instructed to do so by his FBI handlers, particularly since <a href="http://tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com/2012/05/fbi_says_it_isnt_investigating_occupy_cleveland_as.php">the agency denies</a> telling him to hire them for construction work. If Azir provided the group with drugs without FBI authorization, though, his illegal activity would represent egregious loss of control over an informant; according to <a href="https://www.fas.org/irp/agency/doj/fbi/chs-guidelines.pdf">guidelines from 2006</a>, informants may distribute controlled substances only with written authorization from both the Special Agent in Charge and a Chief Federal Prosecutor.</p>
<p>At least one of the Cleveland 5 resisted Azir’s attempt to recruit him: On April 29, according to Taylor’s affidavit, “Stevens advised he did not want to be part of the project, but still wanted to work on [Azir’s] houses. [Azir] told Wright to have Stevens call him,” and apparently persuaded him to participate.</p>
<p>That the alleged conspirators required such persuasion undermines the FBI’s claim that they are dangerous criminals. Specifically, it demonstrates that they were not predisposed to commit the crime, and thus that the case against them constitutes entrapment even under the <a href="http://www.justice.gov/usao/eousa/foia_reading_room/usam/title9/crm00645.htm">narrow definition</a> prevailing in case law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i>Two disclaimers: First, this essay represents a historian’s analysis, not legal advice, and certainly not the opinions of the Cleveland 5 or their lawyers. Second, the Cleveland 5 include friends of friends of mine. As <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/01/fbi_heorically_locks_up_ridiculous_anarchists_on_may_day/singleton/">Alex Pareene writes</a>	of this case, “Someday all Americans, regardless of creed or color, will have their circle of friends secretly infiltrated by a paid informant.”</i></p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="politics" /><category term="drugs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On April 30, the FBI arrested five men affiliated with Occupy Cleveland. According to Special Agent Ryan M. Taylor’s affidavit, Brandon Baxter, Anthony Hayne, Joshua Stafford, Connor Stevens, and Douglas Wright were apprehended “after placing two inert IEDs at the base of the Brecksville-Northfield High Level Bridge and attempting repeatedly to detonate those IEDs.” They did so by dialing a phone number to trigger the devices—a phone number provided by the undercover FBI agent who also sold them the fake explosives.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybernetics of the LRAD</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybernetics of the LRAD" /><published>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/"><![CDATA[<p>
	The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/">marketed</a> to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5369190/lrad-sound-cannon-used-on-pittsburgh-g20-protesters">first deployed in the United States</a> at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/14/chicago_cops_new_weapon/singleton/">will likely again</a> project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.
</p>
<!--more-->
<iframe class="video" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TInNg6QbHXc" title="Video player" frameborder="0" allow="picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen;"></iframe>
<p>
	As Aaron Bady <a href="http://thenewinquiry.com/blogs/hearing-like-an-lrad/">points out</a>, the LRAD brings together violence and speech. “To ask the question of whether an LRAD is designed to hurt people or designed to communicate across long distances with people,” writes Bady, “is to mystify its central design function: It is a technology whose purpose is to FORCE you to listen and obey, and one which is less interested in the difference than you’d think.” The LRAD makes it impossible to think of policing—particularly the iconic “order to disperse” delivered to political demonstrators from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haymarket_affair#Bombing_and_gunfire">Chicago in 1886</a> to Pittsburgh in 2009 (shown above)—as a process in which orders come first and force follows only in the case of disobedience. The medium through which orders are communicated is itself forceful; the LRAD is a <em>weapon</em>, which is why the LRAD Corporation sells it, according to their <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/content/view/323">fact sheet</a>, “only to qualified government agencies and commercial entities that are fully trained in the device’s operation.” Bady concludes, then, that the LRAD demonstrates policing is “simply about power. Communication is a means of making you obey,” and, from the perspective of the LRAD, nothing more.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD conflates communication and force not only conceptually but materially: The same sound serves both purposes. It thus taps into a deep seam in twentieth century science and philosophy that is concerned precisely with the relationship between communication and action. It could be interpreted, for instance, in terms of <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/~kbach/spchacts.html">speech act theory</a>: A loud LRAD order to disperse is both a threatening speech act and itself an act of force.
</p>
<p>
	Since the use of violence to establish control is intrinsic to the LRAD, though, its collapsing of communication and force resonates less with speech acts than the mid-century science of cybernetics. As MIT mathematician Norbert Wiener subtitled <a href="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL14113345M/Cybernetics_or_Control_and_communication_in_the_animal_and_the_machine.">his 1948 book</a> in which he named the discipline, cybernetics involved the study of “control and communication in the animal and machine.” The field developed in the late 1940s through collaborations between scientists interested in understanding minds, societies, and machines in the same terms—collaborations such as the <a href="http://asc-cybernetics.org/foundations/history/MacySummary.htm">Macy Conferences</a>—and cyberneticians conflated control and communication in part to establish parallels between these different entities. This collapsing of categories also owed something, though, to the origins of cybernetics in military research.
</p>
<p>
	Wiener did much of his thinking about analogies between humans and mechanical control systems during World War II while designing an “antiaircraft predictor,” designed to aim a gun in order to shoot down a maneuvering plane. Such a predictor was necessary because during the twenty seconds a shell took to reach its target, the pilot would maneuver, apparently unpredictably. In his article “<a href="http://jerome-segal.de/Galison94.pdf">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” and a <a href="http://cabinetmagazine.org/issues/12/najafi2.php">followup interview</a> in <cite>Cabinet</cite>, historian of science <a href="https://galison.scholar.harvard.edu">Peter Galison</a> argues that Wiener conceived of the enemy pilot as essentially mechanical, and his predictor as a machine that mirrored its behavior. “With no access to anything in the enemy plane,” he says, “Wiener simply treated the pilot-plane assembly as a complex machine—a servomechanism—that once characterized could be simulated in order to predict what it would do. And then it could be blown out of the sky.”
</p>
<p>
	Although Wiener’s work stood in a long tradition of <a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL8396574W/Between_Human_and_Machine">control engineering</a>—since his goal was simply to control a gun—his system also relied on interpreting the plane’s motions as communication to the predictor, which then “learned” its patterns by observing with radar. Even though, “because of the antagonistic relationship between attacker and defender, the anti-aircraft operator was obviously in no position to talk to or even see the pilot,” the latter’s movements still revealed—communicated—his intentions. From Wiener’s perspective as an engineer, though, there was no distinction between control and communication in this system; both were simply messages. There were messages conveyed by the pilot to the plane (through a joystick, say), from the plane to the predictor (through radar), from the predictor to the gun (through a mechanical connection), and from the gun to the plane (through a shell), but each relationship was one of both control and communication, of both force and speech.
</p>
<p>
	The U.S. military also embraced this conflation. During the decades after World War II “command and control,” previously two competing models of military management, became a single practice. <em>Command</em> traditionally involved an officer giving an order which was then interpreted and implemented by those below him in a hierarchy, often as more specific commands to their subordinates. It involved the ambiguity we expect from human communication, if not the dialogue. <em>Control</em>, on the other hand, was direct and (at least ideally) unambiguous. Nuclear weapons, which had to be deployed rapidly and only upon the decision of senior commanders, were subject to control rather than command. This distinction collapsed, though, as nuclear weapons were integrated into conventional military tactics. “By the early 1960s,” writes historian of technology <a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a> in <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2937046W/The_Closed_World">The Closed World</a></cite>, “military parlance treated the two as virtually identical. A decade later, ‘command, control, communications, and information’ (C<sup>3</sup>I) had become a single unified process.”
</p>
<p>
	It is from this postwar military ideology that the LRAD and its inventor Elwood Norris emerged. According to <a href="http://keynotespeakers.com/speaker_detail.php?speakerid=4074">his speaking bio</a>, Norris served in the Air Force as a nuclear weapons specialist in the 1950s before becoming an independent inventor. He was <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2009/03/06/smallbusiness/killer_sounds.fsb/">hired by the Navy</a> to design the LRAD in 2000 after the U.S.S. Cole bombing, and the original purpose of the device was to deter guerrillas from U.S. warships. It has since been used to deter Somali pirates from commercial ships and “to blast a series of Arabic phrases, such as ‘Go away or we will kill you,’” in Baghdad and Fallujah.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD, then, is a military technology that has come home to U.S. soil as a command-and-control system for conveying both orders and force from police to civilians. Its erasure of the distinction between control and communication is not a unique phenomenon that emerges when you build a very loud speaker; rather, its inventor designed a speaker loud enough to “influence behavior and create safety zones” because he and his employers already conflated force and speech.
</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="war" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is marketed to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was first deployed in the United States at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and will likely again project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">History of Cybernetics Bibliography</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="History of Cybernetics Bibliography" /><published>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>If you’ve come here after asking yourself (or Google) what cybernetics is, I recommend starting with Bernard Geoghegan and Benjamin Peters’ entry “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” from the <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite>, and Geoffrey Bowker’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>.” Ronald Kline’s <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment</a></cite> is the synthetic history the field has been waiting for. William Aspray’s “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>” places cybernetics in the context of developments in computing and information theory, while Peter Galison’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” is a classic account of the field’s military origins. The texts listed below survey the many forms cybernetics took in the decades that followed.</p>
	
<p>This bibliography is limited in three ways: It includes only books and articles which focus on cybernetics rather than the related histories of cyborgs and information theory; it includes only texts in English, though there are also substantial French and German literatures on the subject; and it excludes articles and dissertations that have been superseded by books by the same authors. Within these limitations, I welcome references to additional books and articles. I last updated this list on November 26, 2023.</p>

<h3 id="big">The Big Picture <small>(but mostly Anglo-American)</small></h3>
<ol class="start">
	<li>A. A. Verveen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0025-5564(71)90004-6">In Search of Processes: The Early History of Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Mathematical Biosciences</cite> 11 (1971).
	<li>Michael Apter, “Cybernetics: A Case Study of a Scientific Subject-Complex,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sociology-of-science/oclc/591825">The Sociology of Science</a></cite>, edited by Paul Halmos (University of Keele, 1972).</li>
	<li>Robert Lilienfeld, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-systems-theory-an-ideological-analysis/oclc/3275488">The Rise of Systems Theory: An Ideological Analysis</a></cite> (Wiley, 1978).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>,” <cite>Social Studies of Science</cite> 23 (1993).</li>
	<li><a href="http://nkhayles.com/">Katherine Hayles</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-we-became-posthuman-virtual-bodies-in-cybernetics-literature-and-informatics/oclc/39539341">How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in Cybernetics, Literature, and Informatics</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 1999).</li>
	<li>Charles Fran&ccedil;ois, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1099-1743(199905%2F06)16%3A3%3C203%3A%3AAID-SRES210%3E3.0.CO%3B2-1">Systemics and Cybernetics in a Historical Perspective</a>,” <cite>Systems Research and Behavioral Science</cite> 16 (1999).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sonoma.edu/hutchins/faculty/debora-hammond.html">Debora Hammond</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-of-synthesis-exploring-the-social-implications-of-general-systems-theory/oclc/939936819">The Science of Synthesis: Exploring the Social Implications of General Systems Theory</a></cite> (University Press of Colorado, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “The Empty Archive: Cybernetics and the 1960s,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/memory-practices-in-the-sciences/oclc/60776866">Memory Practices in the Sciences</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2008.9">The Historiographic Conceptualization of Information: A Critical Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 30 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://english.emory.edu/home/people/faculty/faculty_pages/johnston.html">John Johnston</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/allure-of-machinic-life-cybernetics-artificial-life-and-the-new-ai/oclc/255975196">The Allure of Machinic Life: Cybernetics, Artificial Life, and the New AI</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2008).</li>
	<li>Philipp Aumann, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2011.78">The Distinctiveness of a Unifying Science: Cybernetics’ Way to West Germany</a>” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 33 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000018">Cybernetic Sense</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/beautiful-data-a-history-of-vision-and-reason-since-1945/oclc/875884461">Beautiful Data: A History of Vision and Reason since 1945</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2014).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment; or, Why We Call Our Age the Information Age</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="http://medientheorie.com/">Claus Pias</a>, “The Age of Cybernetics,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-the-macy-conferences-1946-1953-transactions/oclc/945975579">Cybernetics: The Macy Conferences, 1946–1954; The Complete Transactions</a></cite> (diaphanes, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://ridt.co/">Thomas Rid</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-the-machines-a-cybernetic-history/oclc/921868924">Rise of the Machines: A Cybernetic History</a></cite> (Norton, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a> and <a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite> (2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://elizabethpetrick.com">Elizabeth Petrick</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243919881212">Building the Black Box: Cyberneticians and Complex Systems</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, and Human Values</cite> (2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="origins">Origins</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Otto Mayr, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/origins-of-feedback-control/oclc/102836">The Origins of Feedback Control</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1970).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~bill/">William Aspray</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 7 (1985).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/between-human-and-machine-feedback-control-and-computing-before-cybernetics/oclc/51493422">Between Human and Machine: Feedback, Control, and Computing before Cybernetics</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="us">United States</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20027476">The Americanization of Unity</a>,” <cite>Daedalus</cite> 127 (1998).</li>
	<li>Peter Krieg, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920510581729">The Human Face of Cybernetics: Heinz von Foerster and the History of a Movement That Failed</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 34 (2005).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/">Stuart Umpleby</a>, “<a href="http://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/cybernetics/2005_WAS_History_of_Cybernetics_Movement.doc">A History of the Cybernetics Movement in the United States</a>,” <cite>Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences</cite> 91 (2005).</li>
	<li>Christopher Johnson, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43151893">Analogue Apollo: Cybernetics and the Space Age</a>,” <cite>Paragraph</cite> 31 (2008).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="wiener">Norbert Wiener</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/john-von-neumann-and-norbert-wiener-from-mathematics-to-the-technologies-of-life-and-death/oclc/6304716">John von Neumann and Norbert Wiener: From Mathematics to the Technologies of Life and Death</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1982).</li>
	<li>Pesi Masani, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/norbert-wiener-1894-1964/oclc/19389460">Norbert Wiener, 1894–1964</a></cite> (Birkhauser, 1990).</li>
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 21 (1994).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.unizar.es/sociocybernetics/chen/felix/">Felix Geyer</a> and Johannes van der Zouwen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684929410068334">Norbert Wiener and the Social Sciences</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 23 (1994).
	<li><a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=112">David Jerison</a> and <a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=268">Daniel Stroock</a>, “Norbert Wiener,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://conwayandsiegelman.stillpointpress.net/">Flo Conway and Jim Siegelman</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/dark-hero-of-the-information-age-in-search-of-norbert-wiener-the-father-of-cybernetics/oclc/56656253">Dark Hero of the Information Age: In Search of Norbert Wiener, the Father of Cybernetics</a></cite> (Basic Books, 2004).</li>
	<li><a href="http://maramills.org/">Mara Mills</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-1428852">On Disability and Cybernetics: Helen Keller, Norbert Wiener, and the Hearing Glove</a>,” <cite>differences</cite> 22 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19409419.2013.775544">Toward a Genealogy of a Cold War Communication Science: The Strange Loops of Leo and Norbert Wiener</a>,” <cite>Russian Journal of Communication</cite> 5 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.uni-weimar.de/de/medien/professuren/medienwissenschaft/theorie-medialer-welten/personen/schmidgen/">Henning Schmidgen</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119880662">Cybernetic Times: Norbert Wiener, John Stroud, and the ‘Brain Clock’ Hypothesis</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="ussr">Soviet and Comparative Studies</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/david-holloway">David Holloway</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/284545">Innovation in Science—The Case of Cybernetics in the Soviet Union</a>,” <cite>Science Studies</cite> 4 (1974).</li>
	<li>Peter Elias, “The Rise and Fall of Cybernetics in the US and the USSR,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-newspeak-to-cyberspeak-a-history-of-soviet-cybernetics/oclc/48477582">From Newspeak to Cyberspeak: A History of Soviet Cybernetics</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <a href="http://jerome-segal.de/">J&eacute;r&ocirc;me Segal</a>, and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, “From Communications Engineering to Communications Science: Cybernetics and Information Theory in the United States, France, and the Soviet Union,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-and-ideology-a-comparative-history/oclc/49395331">Science and Ideology: A Comparative History</a></cite>, edited by Mark Walker (Routledge, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="http://ijoc.org/ojs/index.php/ijoc/article/view/212">Betrothal and Betrayal: The Soviet Translation of Norbert Wiener’s Early Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Communications</cite> 2 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-not-to-network-a-nation-the-uneasy-history-of-the-soviet-internet/oclc/927438758">How Not to Network a Nation: The Uneasy History of the Soviet Internet</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://cla.auburn.edu/history/people/faculty/instructors/diana-kurkovsky-west/">Diana Kurkovsky West</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886520">Cybernetics for the Command Economy: Foregrounding Entropy in Late Soviet Planning</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.lafayette.edu/sanbornj/">Joshua Sanborn</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/kri.2022.0044">Cybernetics and Surveillance: The Secret Police Enter the Computer Age</a>,” <cite>Kritika</cite> 23 (2022).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="france">France and “French Theory”</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://socio.umontreal.ca/repertoire-departement/vue/lafontaine-celine/">C&eacute;line Lafontaine</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276407084637">The Cybernetic Matrix of ‘French Theory,’</a>” <cite>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</cite> 24 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~ll2410/">Lydia Liu</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/648527">The Cybernetic Unconscious: Rethinking Lacan, Poe, and French Theory</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 36 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.cornell.edu/jacob-krell">Jacob Krell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886988">What is the ‘Cybernetic’ in the ‘History of Cybernetics’? A French Case, 1968 to the Present</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/en/lehrbereiche-en/general-sociology/team/vincent-august/index">Vincent August</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1368431021991046">Network Concepts in Social Theory: Foucault and Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>European Journal of Social Theory</cite> 24 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1346150607">Code: From Information Theory to French Theory</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2023)</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="chile">Chile</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-revolutionaries-technology-and-politics-in-allendes-chile/oclc/713834502">Cybernetic Revolutionaries: Technology and Politics in Allende’s Chile</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/people/staff/martin-collins">Martin Collins</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2013.776857">introduction to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://usnwc.edu/Faculty-and-Departments/Directory/Michael-Aaron-Dennis">Michael Dennis</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756240">Scientific and Technical Knowledge and the Making of Political Order</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756239">Beyond the Closed World</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://drexel.edu/coas/faculty-research/faculty-directory/TiagoSaraiva/">Tiago Saraiva</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756238">The History of Cybernetics in McOndo</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756237">author response to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="biology">Biology</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-1979-20-206">The Biological Enterprise: Sex, Mind, and Profit from Human Engineering to Sociobiology</a>,” <cite>Radical History Review</cite> no. 20 (1979).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “The High Cost of Information in Post World War II Evolutionary Biology: Ergonomics, Semiotics, and the Sociobiology of Communications Systems,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/philosophical-forum/oclc/1787155">Philosophical Forum</a></cite> 13 (1981–2).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “Signs of Dominance: From a Physiology to a Cybernetics of Primate Society, C.R. Carpenter, 1930–1970,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/studies-in-history-of-biology/oclc/2957828">Studies in History of Biology</a></cite> 6, edited by William Coleman and Camille Limoges (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “A Semiotics of the Naturalistic Field, from C.R. Carpenter to S.A. Altmann, 1930–55,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/primate-visions-gender-race-and-nature-in-the-world-of-modern-science/oclc/19672184">Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</a></cite> (Routledge, 1989).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “The Body of a New Machine: Situating the Organism between Telegraphs and Computers,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/refiguring-life-metaphors-of-twentieth-century-biology/oclc/31606662">Refiguring Life: Metaphors of Twentieth-Century Biology</a></cite> (Columbia University Press, 1995).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/who-wrote-the-book-of-life-a-history-of-the-genetic-code/oclc/41967065">Who Wrote the Book of Life? A History of the Genetic Code</a></cite> (Stanford University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “Taming the Cybernetic Metaphor” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/making-sense-of-life-explaining-biological-development-with-models-metaphors-and-machines/oclc/48100379">Making Sense of Life: Explaining Biological Development with Models, Metaphors, and Machines</a></cite> (Harvard University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sydney.edu.au/arts/history/staff/profiles/warwick.anderson.php">Warwick Anderson</a> and Ian MacKay, “The Science of Self,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/intolerant-bodies-a-short-history-of-autoimmunity/oclc/894511336">Intolerant Bodies: A Short History of Autoimmunity</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="ecology">Ecology</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://faculty.umb.edu/pjt/">Peter Taylor</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4331051">Technocratic Optimism, H.T. Odum, and the Partial Transformation of Ecological Metaphor after World War II</a>,” <cite>Journal of the History of Biology</cite> 21 (1988).</li>
	<li><a href="http://host.jhu.edu/directory/sharon-kingsland/">Sharon Kingsland</a>, “Defining the Ecosystem,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/evolution-of-american-ecology-1890-2000/oclc/56982282">The Evolution of American Ecology, 1890–2000</a></cite> (John Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li>William Bryant, “<a href="http://search.proquest.com/docview/305339541/">Whole System, Whole Earth: The Convergence of Technology and Ecology in Twentieth-Century American Culture</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Iowa, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “Neocybernetics of Gaia: The Emergence of Second-Order Gaia Theory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gaia-in-turmoil-climate-change-biodepletion-and-earth-ethics-in-an-age-of-crisis/oclc/313017382">Gaia in Turmoil: Climate Change, Biodepletion, and Earth Ethics in an Age of Crisis</a></cite>, edited by Eileen Crist and H. Bruce Rinker (MIT Press, 2010).</li>
	<li>Nancy Slack, “Good Friends: Margaret Mead and Gregory Bateson” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/g-evelyn-hutchinson-and-the-invention-of-modern-ecology/oclc/758332328">G. Evelyn Hutchinson and the Invention of Modern Ecology</a></cite> (Yale University Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.usf.edu/arts-sciences/departments/humanities-cultural-studies/faculty/daniel-belgrad.aspx">Daniel Belgrad</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1153210310">The Culture of Feedback: Ecological Thinking in ’70s America</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="social">Social Sciences</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-group/oclc/23047769">Constructing a Social Science for Postwar America: The Cybernetics Group, 1946–1953</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.albany.edu/~gpr/">George Richardson</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-thought-in-social-science-and-systems-theory/oclc/22731896">Feedback Thought in Social Science and Systems Theory</a></cite> (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://emsent.nl/">Esther-Mirjam Sent</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/perspectives_on_science/v008/8.4sent.html">Herbert A. Simon as a Cyborg Scientist</a>,” <cite>Perspectives on Science</cite> 8 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://reilly.nd.edu/people/reilly-fellows/philip-mirowski/">Philip Mirowski</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/machine-dreams-economics-becomes-a-cyborg-science/oclc/45636899">Machine Dreams: Economics Becomes a Cyborg Science</a></cite> (Cambridge University Press, 2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Crowther-Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/herbert-a-simon-the-bounds-of-reason-in-modern-america/oclc/55511492">Herbert A. Simon: The Bounds of Reason in Modern America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/age-of-system-understanding-the-development-of-modern-social-science/oclc/891185841">Age of System: Understanding the Development of Modern Social Science</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.stefanos-geroulanos.com">Stefanos Geroulanos</a> and <a href="https://leifweatherby.org/">Leif Weatherby</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119887098">“Cybernetics and the Human Sciences” special issue introduction</a>, <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119872111">How Disunity Matters to the History of Cybernetics in the Human Sciences in the United States, 1940–80</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li>Poornima Paidipaty, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1463499619899747">‘Tortoises All the Way Down’: Geertz, Cybernetics and ‘Culture’ at the End of the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Anthropological Theory</cite> 20 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="bateson">Gregory Bateson</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://cla.umn.edu/about/directory/profile/lipse001">David Lipset</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gregory-bateson-the-legacy-of-a-scientist/oclc/5894222">Gregory Bateson: The Legacy of a Scientist</a></cite> (Prentice Hall, 1980).</li>
	<li><a href="http://hss.sas.upenn.edu/people/tresch">John Tresch</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2783231">Heredity is an Open System: Gregory Bateson as Descendant and Ancestor</a>,” <cite>Anthropology Today</cite> 14 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.armoniedeldisordine.it/">Leone Montagnini</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777522">Looking for ‘Scientific’ Social Science: The Macy Conferences on Cybernetics in Bateson’s Itinerary</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li>Frank Thomas, Rebekah Waits, and Gail Hartsfield, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777397">The Influence of Gregory Bateson: Legacy or Vestige?</a>” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.northeastern.edu/camd/artdesign/people/william-kaizen/">William Kaizen</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598913">Steps to an Ecology of Communication: <cite>Radical Software</cite>, Dan Graham, and the Legacy of Gregory Bateson</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://history.ua.edu/faculty/erik-peterson/">Erik Peterson</a>, “<a href="http://etd.nd.edu/ETD-db/theses/available/etd-04132010-142514/">Finding Mind, Form, Organism, and Person in a Reductionist Age: The Challenge of Gregory Bateson and C. H. Waddington to Biological and Anthropological Orthodoxy, 1924–1980</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Notre Dame, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="http://sfonline.barnard.edu/feminist-media-theory/schizophrenic-techniques-cybernetics-the-human-sciences-and-the-double-bind/">Schizophrenic Techniques: Cybernetics, the Human Sciences, and the Double Bind</a>,” <cite>S&amp;F Online</cite> 10 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://laps-dept.apps01.yorku.ca/anth/faculty/emeriti/harries.html">Peter Harries-Jones</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/upside-down-gods-gregory-batesons-world-of-difference/oclc/952953457">Upside-Down Gods: Gregory Bateson’s World of Difference</a></cite> (Fordham University Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthonychaney.com/">Anthony Chaney</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/runaway-gregory-bateson-the-double-bind-and-the-rise-of-ecological-consciousness/oclc/1032366653">Runaway: Gregory Bateson, the Double Bind, and the Rise of Ecological Consciousness</a></cite> (University of North Carolina Press, 2017).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="mind">Sciences of Mind</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.sv.uio.no/psi/personer/vit/geirki/">Geir Kirkeb&oslash;en</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/053901895034001002">From a Naked Emperor to Just Clothes: The Rise and Fall of Cybernetic Family Therapy</a>,” <cite>Social Science Information</cite> 34 (1995).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.brown.edu/Departments/CLPS/people/james-anderson">James Anderson</a> and Edward Rosenfeld, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/6626.001.0001">Talking Nets: An Oral History of Neural Networks</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1998).</li>
	<li><a href="https://dlcl.stanford.edu/people/jean-pierre-dupuy">Jean-Pierre Dupuy</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mechanization-of-the-mind-on-the-origins-of-cognitive-science/oclc/44026149">The Mechanization of the Mind: The Origins of Cognitive Science</a></cite>, translated by M. B. DeBevoise (Princeton University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li>Roberto Cordeschi, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/discovery-of-the-artificial-behavior-mind-and-machines-before-and-beyond-cybernetics/oclc/49860160">The Discovery of the Artificial: Behavior, Mind and Machines Before and Beyond Cybernetics</a></cite> (Kluwer Academic Publishers, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1024147708370">From Theory to Data: Representing Neurons in the 1940s</a>,” <cite>Biology and Philosophy</cite> 18 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1162/biot.2006.1.4.418">Cybernetics and Theoretical Approaches in 20th-Century Brain and Behavior Sciences</a>,” <cite>Biological Theory</cite> 1 (2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://socialsciences.exeter.ac.uk/sociology/staff/pickering/">Andrew Pickering</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-brain-sketches-of-another-future/oclc/615626770">The Cybernetic Brain: Sketches of Another Future</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://histsci.fas.harvard.edu/people/rebecca-lemov">Rebecca Lemov</a>, “<a href="http://limn.it/running-amok-in-labyrinthine-systems-the-cyber-behaviorist-origins-of-soft-torture/">Running Amok in Labyrinthine Systems: The Cyber-Behaviorist Origins of Soft Torture</a>,” <cite>Limn</cite> 1 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/dweinste">Deborah Weinstein</a>, “‘Systems Everywhere’: Schizophrenia, Cybernetics, and the Double Bind,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/pathological-family-postwar-america-and-the-rise-of-family-therapy/oclc/800721205">The Pathological Family: Postwar America and the Rise of Family Therapy</a></cite> (Cornell University Press, 2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://mediashiga.net/">John Shiga</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/of-other-networks/">Of Other Networks: Closed-World and Green-World Networks in the Work of John C. Lilly</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://hps.utoronto.ca/staff/chen-pang-yeang/">Chen-Pang Yeang</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/694184">From Modernizing the Chinese Language to Information Science: Chao Yuen Ren’s Route to Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 108 (2017).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthropology.columbia.edu/content/danielle-judith-zola-carr">Danielle Judith Zola Carr</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119874009">‘Ghastly Marionettes’ and the Political Metaphysics of Cognitive Literalism: Anti-Behaviourism, Language, and the Origins of Totalitarianism</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.christinavagt.com">Christina Vagt</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119882883">Design as Aesthetic Education: On the Politics and Aesthetics of Learning Environments</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.princeton.edu/people/katja-guenther">Katja Guenther</a>, “The Dancing Robot: Grey Walter’s Cybernetic Mirror,” in <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1345590894">The Mirror and the Mind: A History of Self-Recognition in the Human Sciences</a></cite> (Princeton University Press, 2022).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="mcculloch">Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://ngp.usc.edu/faculty/profile/?fid=16">Michael Arbib</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0001">Warren McCulloch’s Search for the Logic of the Nervous System</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.psych.uic.edu/department-of-psychiatry-faculty-list/154-about-us/directory/faculty/234-neil-r-smalheiser-md-phd">Neil Smalheiser</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0009">Walter Pitts</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0269889701000266">From Logical Neurons to Poetic Embodiments of Mind: Warren S. McCulloch’s Project in Neuroscience</a>,” <cite>Science in Context</cite> 14 (2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0160-9327(03)00017-6">Integrating Mind and Brain: Warren S. McCulloch, Cerebral Localization, and Experimental Epistemology</a>,” <cite>Endeavour</cite> 27 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/kenaizawa/">Kenneth Aizawa</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000017">Warren McCulloch’s Turn to Cybernetics: What Walter Pitts Contributed</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~philh/">Phil Husbands</a> and <a href="http://cswww.essex.ac.uk/staff/owen/">Owen Holland</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000019">Warren McCulloch and the British Cyberneticians</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/psychology/contact-and-getting-here/people/alan-collins">Alan Collins</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000020">An Asymmetric Relationship: The Spirit of Kenneth Craik and the Work of Warren McCulloch</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, <cite><a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/rebel-genius">Rebel Genius: Warren S. McCulloch’s Transdisciplinary Life in Science</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="politics">Politics and Planning</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/closed-world-computers-and-the-politics-of-discourse-in-cold-war-america/oclc/42636403">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1996).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-warfare-to-welfare-defense-intellectuals-and-urban-problems-in-cold-war-america/oclc/51924188">From Warfare to Welfare: Defense Intellectuals and Urban Problems in Cold War America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.0.0007">Taking Games Seriously</a>,” <cite>Technology and Culture</cite> 49 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bbk.ac.uk/politics/our-staff/academic/antoine-bousquet">Antoine Bousquet</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14682740701791359">Cyberneticizing the American War Machine: Science and Computers in the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Cold War History</cite> 8 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.egs.edu/faculty/brian-holmes/">Brian Holmes</a>, <cite><a href="https://brianholmes.wordpress.com/2009/01/19/book-materials/">Escape the Overcode: Activist Art in the Control Society</a></cite> (Van Abbemuseum, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://geography.utoronto.ca/matt-farish-home-page/">Matthew Ferish</a>, “The Cybernetic Continent: North America as Defense Laboratory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/contours-of-americas-cold-war/oclc/698116870">The Contours of America’s Cold War</a></cite> (University of Minnesota Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://democracycollaborative.org/content/john-duda">John Duda</a>, “<a href="https://www.lwbooks.co.uk/anarchist-studies/21-1/cybernetics-anarchism-and-self-organisation">Cybernetics, Anarchism and Self-Organisation</a>,” <cite>Anarchist Studies</cite> 21 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://rhetoric.berkeley.edu/people/david-bates/">David Bates</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864237">The Political Theology of Entropy: A Katechon for the Cybernetic Age</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eui.eu/DepartmentsAndCentres/HistoryAndCivilization/People/Professors/Guilhot">Nicolas Guilhot</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864244">Automatic Leviathan: Cybernetics and Politics in Carl Schmitt’s Postwar Writings</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.hf.uio.no/ikos/english/people/aca/middle-east-studies/temporary/joakimp/">Joakim Parslow</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0020743821001033">The Mechanical Atatürk: Cybernetics and State Violence in the Second Turkish Republic</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Middle East Studies</cite> 53 (2021).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="popular">Popular Culture and Counterculture</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://homepages.rpi.edu/~eglash/eglash.htm">Ron Eglash</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/095023898335474">Cybernetics in American Youth Subculture</a>,” <cite>Cultural Studies</cite> 12 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://fredturner.stanford.edu/">Fred Turner</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-counterculture-to-cyberculture-stewart-brand-the-whole-earth-network-and-the-rise-of-digital-utopianism/oclc/62533774">From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “<a href="http://www.univie.ac.at/constructivism/journal/7/3/196.clarke">From Information to Cognition: The Systems Counterculture, Heinz von Foerster’s Pedagogy, and Second-Order Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Constructivist Foundations</cite> 7 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.dubberly.com/about">Hugh Dubberly</a> and <a href="http://pangaro.com">Paul Pangaro</a>, “<a href="http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html">How Cybernetics Connects Computing, Counterculture, and Design</a>,” in <cite>Hippie Modernism: The Struggle for Utopia</cite>, edited by Andrew Blauvelt (2015).</li>
	<!--Felicity Scott?-->
</ol>

<h3 id="art">Art</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://daniels.utoronto.ca/people/lobsingerm">Mary Louise Lobsinger</a>, “Cybernetic Theory and the Architecture of Performance: Cedric Price’s Fun Palace,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/anxious-modernisms-experimentation-in-postwar-architectural-culture/oclc/46929153">Anxious Modernisms: Experimentation in Postwar Architectural Culture</a></cite> (Canadian Center for Architecture, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://artexetra.wordpress.com">Edward Shanken</a>, “<a href="http://artexetra.com/CyberneticsArtCultConv.pdf">Cybernetics and Art: Cultural Convergence in the 1960s</a>,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-energy-to-information-representation-in-science-and-technology-art-and-literature/oclc/49821329">From Energy to Information</a></cite>, edited by Bruce Clarke and Linda Henderson (Stanford University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/leonardo/v041/41.2.fernandez.html">Gordon Pask: Cybernetic Polymath</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 41 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598908">Detached from HiStory: Jasia Reichardt and Cybernetic Serendipity</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li>Etan J. Ilfeld, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00326">Contemporary Art and Cybernetics: Waves of Cybernetic Discourse within Conceptual, Video and New Media Art</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 45 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://etiennebenson.com/">Etienne Benson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.7275/R5HT2M7T">Environment between System and Nature: Alan Sonfist and the Art of the Cybernetic Environment</a>,” <cite>communication +1</cite> 3 (2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="film">Film and Video</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.gc.cuny.edu/Page-Elements/Academics-Research-Centers-Initiatives/Doctoral-Programs/Art-History/Faculty-Bios/David-Joselit">David Joselit</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-television-against-democracy/oclc/71322293">Feedback: Television Against Democracy</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://art.stonybrook.edu/faculty/zabet-patterson/">Zabet Patterson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/grey.2009.1.36.36">From the Gun Controller to the Mandala: The Cybernetic Cinema of John and James Whitney</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite> no. 36 (2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://film.fsu.edu/People/Administration/Dr.-Andrew-Syder">Andrew Syder</a>, “<a href="http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15799coll127/id/220820/">“Shaken Out of the Ruts of Ordinary Perception”: Vision, Culture and Technology in the Psychedelic Sixties</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Southern California, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://kpaulsen.com/">Kris Paulsen</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/half-inch-revolution/">Half Inch Revolution: The Guerilla Video Tape Network</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="http://procom.ryerson.ca/people/carolyn-kane">Carolyn Kane</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00871">The Tragedy of Radical Subjectivity: From Radical Software to Proprietary Subjects</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 47, no. 5 (2014).</li>
	<li><a href="https://collopy.net/">Peter Sachs Collopy</a>, “<a href="https://repository.upenn.edu/edissertations/1665/">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://medienwissenschaft.philhist.unibas.ch/de/personen/ute-holl/">Ute Holl</a>, <cite><a href="http://library.oapen.org/handle/20.500.12657/31337">Cinema, Trance and Cybernetics</a></cite> (Amsterdam University Press, 2017).
</ol>

<h4 id="sound">Sound and Music</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://annenberg.usc.edu/faculty/communication/christina-dunbar-hester">Christina Dunbar-Hester</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243909337116">Listening to Cybernetics: Music, Machines, and Nervous Systems, 1950–1980</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</cite> 35 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sterneworks.org/">Jonathan Sterne</a>, “Nature Builds No Telephones” and “Perceptual Coding and the Domestication of Noise,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mp3-the-meaning-of-a-format/oclc/769429993">MP3: The Meaning of a Format</a></cite> (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/staff/profiles/music/haworth-christopher.aspx">Christopher Haworth</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.461">Music and Cybernetics in Historical Perspective: Introduction to the Special Issue</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://deirdreloughridge.wordpress.com">Deirdre Loughridge</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.503">Daphne Oram: Cyberneticist?</a>” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eamonnbell.com">Eamonn Bell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.523">Cybernetics, Listening, and Sound-Studio Phenomenotechnique in Abraham Moles’s <cite>Théorie de l’information et perception esthétique</cite> (1958)</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.claralatham.com">Clara Latham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.559">The Sound Machine in the Body: Cybernetics and the Theremin</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://music.utexas.edu/about/people/eric-drott">Eric Drott</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.578">Music and the Cybernetic Mundane</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://ted-gordon.net">Theodore Gordon</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07494467.2021.2001939">‘Androgynous Music’: Pauline Oliveros’s Early Cybernetic Improvisation</a>,” <cite>Contemporary Music Review</cite> 40 (2022).</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="computing" /><category term="art" /><category term="war" /><category term="biology" /><category term="video" /><category term="media" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="psychiatry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.]]></summary></entry></feed>