<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/drugs.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-20T08:46:25-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/drugs.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy" /><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="art" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Video Is as Powerful as LSD”: Electronics and Psychedelics as Technologies of Consciousness</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2023/video-is-as-powerful-as-lsd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Video Is as Powerful as LSD”: Electronics and Psychedelics as Technologies of Consciousness" /><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2023/video-is-as-powerful-as-lsd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2023/video-is-as-powerful-as-lsd/"><![CDATA[<p>In the middle of the twentieth century, the invention and availability of new psychedelic drugs, and the growing cultural discourse around them, coincided with those of television, videotape, and computing. The technologies of psychedelics and electronics grew up together, and those using or thinking about one often implicated the other. When Sony and other Japanese manufacturers developed new portable videotape recorders in the late 1960s, for example, new communities of artists and tinkerers emerged around them, first in the US and Canada and then in Europe, Asia, North Africa, and Latin America. For the first time, declared these enthusiasts, many people could make their own television, breaking the broadcast oligopoly. In describing the psychological and sociological implications of this new technology, many compared it to psychedelic drugs.<p>

<p class="translation">A mediados del siglo XX, la invención y disponibilidad de nuevas drogas psicodélicas, y el creciente discurso cultural en torno a ellas, coincidieron con los de la televisión, las cintas de vídeo y la informática. Las tecnologías psicodélicas y la electrónica crecieron juntas, y quienes usaban o pensaban en una a menudo implicaban a la otra. Cuando Sony y otros fabricantes japoneses desarrollaron nuevos magnetoscopios portátiles a finales de los años sesenta, por ejemplo, surgieron nuevas comunidades de artistas a su alrededor, primero en Estados Unidos y Canadá, y después en Europa, Asia, el norte de África y América Latina. Por primera vez, declararon estos entusiastas, mucha gente podía hacer su propia televisión, rompiendo el oligopolio de la radiodifusión.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="art" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the middle of the twentieth century, the invention and availability of new psychedelic drugs, and the growing cultural discourse around them, coincided with those of television, videotape, and computing. The technologies of psychedelics and electronics grew up together, and those using or thinking about one often implicated the other. When Sony and other Japanese manufacturers developed new portable videotape recorders in the late 1960s, for example, new communities of artists and tinkerers emerged around them, first in the US and Canada and then in Europe, Asia, North Africa, and Latin America. For the first time, declared these enthusiasts, many people could make their own television, breaking the broadcast oligopoly. In describing the psychological and sociological implications of this new technology, many compared it to psychedelic drugs. A mediados del siglo XX, la invención y disponibilidad de nuevas drogas psicodélicas, y el creciente discurso cultural en torno a ellas, coincidieron con los de la televisión, las cintas de vídeo y la informática. Las tecnologías psicodélicas y la electrónica crecieron juntas, y quienes usaban o pensaban en una a menudo implicaban a la otra. Cuando Sony y otros fabricantes japoneses desarrollaron nuevos magnetoscopios portátiles a finales de los años sesenta, por ejemplo, surgieron nuevas comunidades de artistas a su alrededor, primero en Estados Unidos y Canadá, y después en Europa, Asia, el norte de África y América Latina. Por primera vez, declararon estos entusiastas, mucha gente podía hacer su propia televisión, rompiendo el oligopolio de la radiodifusión.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="war" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="fascism" /><category term="New York" /><category term="California" /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Video Synthesizers: From Analog Computing to Digital Art</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2014/video-synthesizers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Video Synthesizers: From Analog Computing to Digital Art" /><published>2014-12-11T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2014-12-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2014/video-synthesizers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2014/video-synthesizers/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, artists and engineers began building increasingly sophisticated video synthesizers, machines that produced abstract or distorted images by electronically manipulating either a video signal or the cathode ray tube on which it was displayed. This article explores how experimental videographers modeled video synthesizers on audio synthesizers, conceptualized them as analog computers, and starting in 1973, interfaced them with digital minicomputers.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="computing" /><category term="video" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, artists and engineers began building increasingly sophisticated video synthesizers, machines that produced abstract or distorted images by electronically manipulating either a video signal or the cathode ray tube on which it was displayed. This article explores how experimental videographers modeled video synthesizers on audio synthesizers, conceptualized them as analog computers, and starting in 1973, interfaced them with digital minicomputers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Brainwashing of the Cleveland 5</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cleveland-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Brainwashing of the Cleveland 5" /><published>2012-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cleveland-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cleveland-5/"><![CDATA[<p>On April 30, the FBI arrested five men affiliated with Occupy Cleveland. According to <a href="http://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/352006/bridge-bomb-plot-new-charges.pdf">Special Agent Ryan M. Taylor’s affidavit</a>, Brandon Baxter, Anthony Hayne, Joshua Stafford, Connor Stevens, and Douglas Wright were apprehended “after placing two inert IEDs at the base of the Brecksville-Northfield High Level Bridge and attempting repeatedly to detonate those IEDs.” They did so by dialing a phone number to trigger the devices—a phone number provided by the undercover FBI agent who also sold them the fake explosives.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The <a href="http://cleveland5justice.org/">Cleveland 5</a> face life in prison on three charges, to which they’ve pled not guilty: attempted use of a weapon of mass destruction to destroy property used in interstate commerce, conspiracy to use a weapon of mass destruction to destroy property used in interstate commerce, and attempted use of an explosive device to damage or destroy real property used in interstate commerce. Judge David Dowd, Jr. <a href="http://www.cleveland.com/metro/index.ssf/2012/05/judges_proposal_of_sept_11_tri.html">initially proposed</a> a trial date of September 11, then settled on September 17 after defense attorneys protested.</p>
<p>This was the first time FBI strategies of infiltration and escalation resulted in charges against participants in the Occupy movement. In this case, the agency may be responsible not only for entrapment but for even more egregious malfeasance which amounts to brainwashing.</p>
<p>On April 29—the day before the Cleveland arrests—<cite>The New York Times</cite> published an opinion piece by journalist David K. Shipler under the headline “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/29/opinion/sunday/terrorist-plots-helped-along-by-the-fbi.html?pagewanted=all">Terrorist Plots, Hatched by the F.B.I.</a>” Shipler described an increasingly utilized FBI tactic of fostering terrorist plots in order to catch potential criminals. “Typically,” writes Shipler, “the stings initially target suspects for pure speech—comments to an informer outside a mosque, angry posting on websites, emails with radicals overseas—then woo them into relationships with informers, who are often convicted felons working in exchange for leniency.” Those subjected to this tactic lack the knowledge, connections, and materials necessary to commit a crime, so the FBI supplies them. James Cromitie, for example, was convicted of attempting to bomb synagogues and shoot down military aircraft. “Only the government could have made a ‘terrorist’ out of Mr. Cromitie, whose buffoonery is positively Shakespearean in its scope,” said Judge Colleen McMahon, although she nonetheless sentenced him to 25 years in prison. “Of the 22 most frightening plans for attacks since 9/11 on American soil,” Shipler concluded, “14 were developed in sting operations.”</p>
<p>As in their entrapment of Muslims, the FBI seems to have picked low-hanging fruit in Cleveland: naive young men seeking to make a difference in the world. Even Taylor’s affidavit makes it clear these alleged conspirators were coached extensively by felon <a href="http://www.thesmokinggun.com/documents/fbi-informant-shaquille-azir-756123">Shaquille Azir</a>, an FBI informant similar to those described by Shipler. <a href="http://www.greenisthenewred.com/blog/fbi-anarchist-terrorists-may-day-ohio/5988/">Will Potter writes</a> that “what’s troubling is that the government has had a heavy hand in creating the very plot it thwarted. And on top of that, the defendants, by the admission of the FBI, said repeatedly that they had no intention of harming anyone.” Potter compares the case to that of environmentalist <a href="http://supporteric.org/">Eric McDavid</a>, who was also provided with plans, supplies, and encouragement by an FBI infiltrator.</p>
<p>Azir supplied more than encouragement and fake explosives, however. Based on interviews with friends and family members of the Cleveland 5, <a href="http://www.alternet.org/story/155581/has_the_fbi_launched_a_war_of_entrapment_against_the_occupy_movement?page=entire">Arun Gupta concludes</a> that Azir “provided the five with jobs, money, a place to live, a friendly ear, beer, pot, the prescription stimulant Adderall, and most significant, the ideas and means to carry out a plot conceived by the Bureau itself.” Similarly, <a href="http://www.counterpunch.org/2012/05/21/police-entrapment-of-nonviolent-movements/">Jake Olzen writes</a>, based on an interview with Cleveland activist Richard Schulte, that “Azir would give them a case of beer in the morning,… have them work outside on houses all day, and then give them a case of beer at night. He gave them marijuana and would wear them down by keeping them up late into the night with drinking and conversation—all the while urging them to break away from other groups, keep their arrangement secret and not to trust other activists.”</p>
<p>This treatment was brainwashing—or, as it is sometimes termed, coercive persuasion. The new social environment Azir created meets several of the conditions psychologist Margaret Singer associates with such thought-reform in her book <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL3264926W/Cults_in_Our_Midst">Cults in Our Midst</a></cite>: Azir separated the alleged conspirators from their support networks by suggesting outsiders couldn’t be trusted (a tactic Schulte provocatively describes as using “<a href="http://security.resist.ca/personal/culture.shtml">security culture</a> against activists”), controlled their time by providing them with long days of work, and kept them unaware they were being manipulated by presenting himself as a friend and mentor. According to Gupta, friends described Stafford and Baxter as “highly impressionable,” and Azir took advantage of their vulnerability. Sociologist Richard Ofshe (quoted in <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL6025390W/Brainwash">Brainwash</a></cite> by Dominic Streatfeild) explains that people subjected to such manipulation “make bad decisions because they find themselves in situations that are built to get them to make those decisions.”</p>
<p>In addition to controlling their social environment, Azir manipulated the group physiologically to make them more suggestible. Fatigue obviously helped, and marijuana may have as well: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Cmd=Retrieve&amp;list_uids=417375">Researchers in the 1970s found</a> that “the drug caused an increase in suggestibility similar to that produced by the induction of hypnosis.” Similarly, the National Commission on Marihuana and Drug Abuse’s 1972 report, “Marijuana: A Signal of Misunderstanding,” <a href="http://www.druglibrary.org/schaffer/Library/studies/nc/nc1g_8.htm">stated</a> that “cannabis intoxication produces a heightened suggestibility.” I don’t know if this phenomenon has been exploited by the FBI before. According to John Marks’ classic <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL4097029W/The_search_for_the_Manchurian_candidate">The Search for the “Manchurian Candidate,”</a></cite> though, the Office of Strategic Services used cannabis as a truth drug during World War II. The CIA, its successor agency, later experimented more extensively.</p>
<p>It is not clear whether Azir decided to brainwash the alleged conspirators himself or was instructed to do so by his FBI handlers, particularly since <a href="http://tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com/2012/05/fbi_says_it_isnt_investigating_occupy_cleveland_as.php">the agency denies</a> telling him to hire them for construction work. If Azir provided the group with drugs without FBI authorization, though, his illegal activity would represent egregious loss of control over an informant; according to <a href="https://www.fas.org/irp/agency/doj/fbi/chs-guidelines.pdf">guidelines from 2006</a>, informants may distribute controlled substances only with written authorization from both the Special Agent in Charge and a Chief Federal Prosecutor.</p>
<p>At least one of the Cleveland 5 resisted Azir’s attempt to recruit him: On April 29, according to Taylor’s affidavit, “Stevens advised he did not want to be part of the project, but still wanted to work on [Azir’s] houses. [Azir] told Wright to have Stevens call him,” and apparently persuaded him to participate.</p>
<p>That the alleged conspirators required such persuasion undermines the FBI’s claim that they are dangerous criminals. Specifically, it demonstrates that they were not predisposed to commit the crime, and thus that the case against them constitutes entrapment even under the <a href="http://www.justice.gov/usao/eousa/foia_reading_room/usam/title9/crm00645.htm">narrow definition</a> prevailing in case law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i>Two disclaimers: First, this essay represents a historian’s analysis, not legal advice, and certainly not the opinions of the Cleveland 5 or their lawyers. Second, the Cleveland 5 include friends of friends of mine. As <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/01/fbi_heorically_locks_up_ridiculous_anarchists_on_may_day/singleton/">Alex Pareene writes</a>	of this case, “Someday all Americans, regardless of creed or color, will have their circle of friends secretly infiltrated by a paid informant.”</i></p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="politics" /><category term="drugs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On April 30, the FBI arrested five men affiliated with Occupy Cleveland. According to Special Agent Ryan M. Taylor’s affidavit, Brandon Baxter, Anthony Hayne, Joshua Stafford, Connor Stevens, and Douglas Wright were apprehended “after placing two inert IEDs at the base of the Brecksville-Northfield High Level Bridge and attempting repeatedly to detonate those IEDs.” They did so by dialing a phone number to trigger the devices—a phone number provided by the undercover FBI agent who also sold them the fake explosives.]]></summary></entry></feed>