<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/technopolitics.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-20T12:15:48-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/technopolitics.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Between Paradigms: Video and Art Therapy" /><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2024/between-paradigms/"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="video" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="art" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anarchism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="New York" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As therapists developed the new field of video therapy in the 1950s and 1960s, they rarely interacted with the parallel field of art therapy or with the concept of creative expression at its core. Video therapy mostly involved recording and playing back talk therapy sessions. In only a few places did it become something like art therapy, a practice in which patients themselves made art to process their own experiences. This chapter traces how that resemblance developed at New York’s Village Project and elsewhere in the United States from about 1967 to 1975. It considers how painter Frank Gillette and philosopher-sociologist Victor Gioscia in particular drew from both modernist and emerging postmodernist intellectual currents, particularly the boundary-crossing work of media theorist Marshall McLuhan, to navigate the intersections of disciplines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behind the Book: Escape from Earth</title><link href="https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behind the Book: Escape from Earth" /><published>2022-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/discussions/2022/escape-from-earth/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="discussions" /><category term="Caltech" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="communism" /><category term="California" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Art Do Work</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Art Do Work" /><published>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/making-art-do-work/"><![CDATA[In <cite>Making Art Work</cite>, W. Patrick McCray asks why and how American artists and engineers collaborated to produce technological art in the 1960s and 1970s. In our current moment, so obviously marked by the American government’s failure to deploy scientific expertise against a pandemic, and by demonstrations against white supremacy and police brutality larger than those of the 1960s, this book also provokes additional questions. Of what did technological art make people aware? Could it in fact contribute to solving social problems like hunger, homelessness, and war? How did patriarchy and white supremacy shape this art and the awareness it produced? What roles did women and people of color play in constructing and contesting it? Although none of these questions is at the center of McCray’s book, he points toward some of the answers.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="politics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="technopolitics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Making Art Work, W. Patrick McCray asks why and how American artists and engineers collaborated to produce technological art in the 1960s and 1970s. In our current moment, so obviously marked by the American government’s failure to deploy scientific expertise against a pandemic, and by demonstrations against white supremacy and police brutality larger than those of the 1960s, this book also provokes additional questions. Of what did technological art make people aware? Could it in fact contribute to solving social problems like hunger, homelessness, and war? How did patriarchy and white supremacy shape this art and the awareness it produced? What roles did women and people of color play in constructing and contesting it? Although none of these questions is at the center of McCray’s book, he points toward some of the answers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed.

Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite>, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite> is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="computing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="fascism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed. Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, IBM and the Holocaust, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, IBM and the Holocaust is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="war" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="fascism" /><category term="New York" /><category term="California" /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technology and Society</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology and Society" /><published>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2014/technology/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesday evenings, 6:00 to 9:00, from September 2 to December 9 in Williams Hall room 219. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Tuesdays from 5:00 to 6:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>
<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you <a href="reading">read and think about them</a> before each class meeting. Your engaged and insightful participation in discussions will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<p>The other assignments consist of three short papers, of approximately five pages each. I’ll provide more detailed prompts, but in short <a href="politics">the first paper</a> should present an argument about whether and how a particular technology “has politics,” <a href="observing">the second</a> should describe and analyze your observation of people using technology, and <a href="history">the third</a> should present a brief history of a technology of your choice. You will have an opportunity to submit a draft, get my feedback, and revise your paper before I grade it. Each paper will account for 25% of your grade for the course.</p>
<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>The following four books, which we’ll be reading cover-to-cover or nearly so, are available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> is also available online, and other readings will be available through links below.</p>
<ul id="books">
	<li>Lynn White, Jr., <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite> (1962).</li>
	<li>Thomas J. Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet: Technology and Culture from the Renaissance to the Present</cite>, second edition (2011, revised from 2004 original).</li>
	<li>Ruth Schwartz Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother: The Ironies of Household Technology from the Open Hearth to the Microwave</cite> (1983).</li>
	<li>David Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old: Technology and Global History since 1900</cite> (2007).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Schedule</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>September 2: Introduction</h4>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 9: Technologies of Feudalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Langdon Winner, “<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/20024652">Do Artifacts Have Politics?</a>” (1980).</li>
			<li>White, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01086.0001.001">Medieval Technology and Social Change</a></cite>, preface and chapters 1 and 2.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, preface and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 16: Roots of Capitalism</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lewis Mumford, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01149.0001.001">Technics and Civilization</a></cite> (1934), objectives and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Cynthia Cockburn, <cite>Machinery of Dominance: Women, Men, and Technical Know-How</cite> (1985), introduction and chapter 1.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 2.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>September 23: Print Culture</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Marshall McLuhan, <cite>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</cite> (1964), chapters 1, 16, and 18.</li>
			<li>Elizabeth Eisenstein, <cite>The Printing Revolution in Early Modern Europe</cite>, second edition (2005, abridged from <cite>The Printing Press as an Agent of Change: Communications and Cultural Transformations in Early-Modern Europe</cite>, 1979), introduction and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li>Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar, <cite>Laboratory Life: The Construction of Scientific Facts</cite>, second edition (1986, revised from 1979 original), pages 43–53.</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule" style="page-break-before: always">
		<h4>September 30: The Industrialization of Manufacturing</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 3.</li>
			<li>Walter Licht, <cite>Industrializing America: The Nineteenth Century</cite> (1995), introduction and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li>Judith A. McGaw, “Gender and Papermaking” (1998, abridged from <cite>Most Wonderful Machine: Mechanization and Social Change in Berkshire Paper Making, 1801–1885</cite>, 1987).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 7: The Industrialization of Time and Space</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 4.</li>
			<li>Wolfgang Schivelbusch, <cite>The Railway Journey: The Industrialization of Time and Space in the 19th Century</cite> (1986), chapters 1–6.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="politics">the politics of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 14: The Industrialization of Housework</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Cowan, <cite>More Work for Mother</cite>, chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>October 21: Technological Systems</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Thomas P. Hughes, <cite>American Genesis: A Century of Invention and Technological Enthusiasm 1870–1970</cite> (1989), introduction and chapter 5.</li>
			<li>Leo Marx, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2010.0009"><i>Technology</i>: The Emergence of a Hazardous Concept</a>” (2010, revised from 1997 original).</li>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>October 28: Modern Cities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 6.</li>
			<li>David Nye, <cite>Electrifying America: Social Meanings of a New Technology, 1880–1940</cite> (1990), preface and chapters 2 and 3.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 4: Modern Media</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Friedrich A. Kittler, <cite>Gramophone, Film, Typewriter</cite> (1999, translated from 1986 German original), pages 1–37.</li>
			<li>Susan J. Douglas, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb01134.0001.001">Inventing American Broadcasting, 1899–1922</a></cite> (1987), introduction and chapter 6.</li>
			<li>Claude S. Fischer, <cite><a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb00141.0001.001">America Calling: A Social History of the Telephone to 1940</a></cite> (1992), chapters 2 and 3.</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="observing">observing technology in use</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 11: Alternative Modernities</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5.</li>
			<li>Paul R. Josephson, <cite>Would Trotsky Wear a Bluetooth? Technological Utopianism under Socialism, 1917–1989</cite> (2010), introduction and chapter 1.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>November 18: The Industrialization of Violence</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 7.</li>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 6 and 7.</li>
			<li>Paul N. Edwards, <cite><a href="http://cognet.mit.edu/book/closed-world">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (1996), pages 1–27.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li class="newmodule">
		<h4>November 25: <i>No class</i></h4>
		<ul>
			<li><b>Draft due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 2: Globalization</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Edgerton, <cite>The Shock of the Old</cite>, chapters 3, 4, 8 and conclusion.</li>
			<li>Carroll Pursell, <cite>The Machine in America: A Social History of Technology</cite>, second edition (2007, revised from 1994 original), chapter 13.</li>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapter 8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>December 9: Technological Systems Revisited</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Misa, <cite>Leonardo to the Internet</cite>, chapters 9 and 10.</li>
			<li>Nathan Ensmenger, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.2012.0126">The Digital Construction of Technology: Rethinking the History of Computers in Society</a>” (2012).</li>
			<li>Paolo Pedercini, “<a href="http://www.molleindustria.org/blog/videogames-and-the-spirit-of-capitalism/">Videogames and the Spirit of Capitalism</a>” (2014).</li>
			<li><b>Paper due on <a href="history">the history of a technology</a>.</b></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="capitalism" /><category term="media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Technology and Society (STSC/HSOC 003), a course offered in fall 2014 at the University of Pennsylvania. Technology plays an increasing role in our understandings of ourselves, our communities, and our societies, in how we think about politics and war, science and religion, work and play. Humans have made and used technologies, though, for thousands if not millions of years. In this course, we will use this history as a resource to understand how technologies affect social relations, and conversely how the culture of a society shapes the technologies it produces. Do different technologies produce or result from different economic systems like feudalism, capitalism, and communism? Can specific technologies promote democratic or authoritarian politics? Do they suggest or enforce different patterns of race, class, or gender relations? Among the technologies we'll consider will be large objects like cathedrals, bridges, and airplanes; small ones like guns, clocks, and birth control pills; and networks like the electrical grid, the highway system, and the internet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MIT, Ethics, and the Prosecution of Aaron Swartz</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/aaron-swartz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MIT, Ethics, and the Prosecution of Aaron Swartz" /><published>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2013/aaron-swartz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/aaron-swartz/"><![CDATA[<p>
	On January 11, autodidact, hacker, and activist <a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/">Aaron Swartz</a> committed suicide in the midst of a draconian prosecution for using guest access to MIT’s network to download millions of articles from JSTOR. I’d only had a few brief conversations with Aaron on Twitter, but I read his blog for almost a decade, making his projects and ideas a steady presence in my life. In the words of Grace Llewellyn’s <a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2674846W/The_Teenage_Liberation_Handbook"><cite>Teenage Liberation Handbook</cite></a>, for which Aaron and I <a href="http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/productivity">shared an affection</a> as unschoolers, Aaron was a “glorious generalist,” someone who has deep interests but, rather than obsessing, searches for connections between them and everything else. The world needs such people. I was crushed by Aaron’s death.
</p>
<!--more-->
<p>
	On Tuesday, MIT released its review panel’s report on “<a href="http://swartz-report.mit.edu/docs/report-to-the-president.pdf">MIT and the Prosecution of Aaron Swartz</a>.” Those of us interested in the case have been anticipating this report, particularly given the respect many of us have for computer scientist <a href="http://groups.csail.mit.edu/mac/users/hal/">Hal Abelson</a>, who was charged by MIT’s president with writing it. Personally, I learned how to program when I was about ten from <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/books/logo-macintosh">a book by Abelson and his daughter</a>, and still appreciate his approach to computer science pedagogy and work with foundations like <a href="http://creativecommons.org/">Creative Commons</a> and the <a href="http://fsf.org/">Free Software Foundation</a>.
</p>
<p>
	The Abelson report effectively depicts an MIT administration telling itself it was neutral in the case while cooperating with the prosecution, particularly by allowing prosecutors to repeatedly meet with witnesses without an MIT lawyer present once MIT had granted them initial permission, a courtesy they did not extend to the defense. It depicts an MIT that didn’t see itself as Aaron’s victim, but also never recognized its own role as legislator given the use of the <a href="http://ist.mit.edu/network/rules">MITNet Rules of Use</a> to support a claim, under the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Fraud_and_Abuse_Act">Computer Fraud and Abuse Act</a>, that Aaron exceeded authorized access to MIT’s network. Within MIT, only incoming Media Lab director <a href="http://joi.ito.com/">Joi Ito</a> suggested that MIT question the premise of the prosecution, writing to MIT’s lawyers that “since it is a criminal case and the prosecutor needs to prove beyond reasonable doubt that it was unauthorized, I think MIT is in the position to ‘cast doubt’ if it desires.” As defense attorneys asked MIT to speak out against the prosecution with increasing urgency, the Institute’s main reason for not doing so seems to have been that they believed it might actually hurt Aaron’s case, that they believed—as Aaron’s friend <a href="http://lessig.tumblr.com/post/40347463044/prosecutor-as-bully">Lawrence Lessig wrote</a> immediately after Aaron’s death—that prosecutor <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Heymann">Stephen Heymann</a> was a bully who interpreted opposition as a personal attack on his authority and responded by escalating.
</p>
<p>
	The report is nonetheless a disappointment. I don’t think I saw until now MIT President L. Rafael Reif’s formal letter to Abelson requesting the report, and I certainly hadn’t realized that Abelson’s charge was limited to fact-finding and “identify[ing] the issues that warrant further analysis in order to learn from these events.” Since Abelson and his colleagues on the review panel, economist <a href="http://economics.mit.edu/faculty/pdiamond">Peter Diamond</a> and lawyer <a href="http://grossolaw.com/grosso.htm">Andrew Grosso</a>, didn’t discover any shocking malfeasance on the part of MIT, their recommendations (which take the form of questions to avoid exceeding their charge) are rather mundane, including reforming MIT’s data retention policies and holding “a series of campus-wide deliberations around issues raised by this report.” The most critical, perhaps, is that MIT “develop additional on-campus expertise for handling potential computer crime incidents” in order to avoid reliance on outside police, reliance that in Aaron’s case inadvertently (from MIT’s perspective) involved the Secret Service.
</p>
<p>
	This limited charge proscribed the review panel from asserting outright that MIT should have behaved differently. The two quotations from their interviews which they include in their conclusion, though, say a lot. One administrator told the review panel, “MIT didn’t do anything wrong, but we didn’t do ourselves proud.” And a friend of Aaron’s pointed out that “neutrality on these cases is an incoherent stance. It’s not the right choice for a tough leader or a moral leader.”
</p>
<div style="text-align: center; font-weight: bold">. . .</div>
<p>
	Early this summer, I taught <a href="/teaching/2013/cyberculture/">a course</a> on the history and culture of the internet. In our discussion of Lessig’s book <a href="http://codev2.cc/"><cite>Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace</cite></a>, I suggested to students that it, like most political writing, was written in the genre of advice for those in power. Its central point is that “cyberspace requires choices” in how it is built, both by programmers and by legislators. Lessig’s message to these influential people was that although their decisions might seem merely technical, they are in fact deeply ethical. Although he was quite pessimistic that those in power would rise to the occasion—“we urgently need to make fundamental choices about values,” wrote Lessig, “but… the government we have now is a failure”—he wrote a book about how governance on the internet ought to function in America.
</p>
<p>
	I also showed my class Aaron’s 2012 Freedom to Connect keynote speech, “<a href="http://www.democracynow.org/2013/1/14/freedom_to_connect_aaron_swartz_1986">How We Stopped SOPA</a>,” and noted a difference in perspective between these two political documents. Aaron’s intended audience was those who are not in power. His message was that they too should seek to influence internet policy, and indeed that this is the way out of Lessig’s trap. “We won this fight because everyone made themselves the hero of their own story,” concluded Aaron. “Everyone took it as their job to save this crucial freedom. They threw themselves into it. They did whatever they could think of to do. They didn’t stop to ask anyone for permission.… The internet really is out of control.”
</p>
<p>
	Internet censorship was an issue on which Swartz and Lessig generally agreed, but their rhetoric appealed to different audiences: to caricature a bit, Lessig’s was technocratic while Swartz’s was rabble-rousing. The lesson I suggested to my students was not that Aaron’s perspective was more productive than Lessig’s; I love Lessig’s critical edge, and since I teach at the University of Pennsylvania, I expect that some of my students will become influential politicians and programmers who may build the internet more humanely under Lessig’s influence. Rather, I suggested that, in considering any political issue, it’s worth thinking through both perspectives. What could you do to improve the world in a particular way if you were in a position of authority? What could you do if you were not? We need to be able to think in both ways because most of us move back and forth between these situations over the course of our lives and even over the course of our days. I, for example, have no more influence than my neighbors in electoral politics, but make hiring and firing decisions as a board member of our local food co-op. In either context, though, I want to act ethically.</p>
<p>
	Because they were not in the role of either prosecutor or defendant, and because Aaron was not formally affiliated with the Institute, MIT’s lawyers and administrators imagined themselves to be neutral, without any ethical interest in the prosecution. The Abelson report reveals that they acted properly, for the most part, with regard to their professional and legal responsibilities. Their largest sins of commission were relatively minor, permitting the prosecutors greater access to witnesses than the defense team and acting on a subpoena which had apparently expired. It also reveals, though, that they failed—“<a href="http://tarensk.tumblr.com/post/56881327662/mit-report-is-a-whitewash-my-statement-in-response">reprehensibly</a>,” as Aaron’s partner Taren Stinebrickner-Kauffman writes, “<a href="https://archives.lessig.org/index6f09.html">more than negligent[ly]</a>,” as Lessig writes—to act on their deeper ethical responsibilities, in particular by not asserting that Aaron hadn’t actually violated their Rules of Use. In short, MIT believed that as long as they played their narrow role in the drama everything would turn out fine; they did not “take it as their job,” as Aaron would have counseled, to consider whether the prosecutor was behaving ethically and how they could influence him. Given that the case concerned not only the use of MIT property, and not only issues of intellectual and practical interest to many MIT students and faculty, but the eminent possibility of a ruined life, this was a grave ethical failure.
</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On January 11, autodidact, hacker, and activist Aaron Swartz committed suicide in the midst of a draconian prosecution for using guest access to MIT’s network to download millions of articles from JSTOR. I’d only had a few brief conversations with Aaron on Twitter, but I read his blog for almost a decade, making his projects and ideas a steady presence in my life. In the words of Grace Llewellyn’s Teenage Liberation Handbook, for which Aaron and I shared an affection as unschoolers, Aaron was a “glorious generalist,” someone who has deep interests but, rather than obsessing, searches for connections between them and everything else. The world needs such people. I was crushed by Aaron’s death.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyberculture</title><link href="https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyberculture" /><published>2013-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/teaching/2013/cyberculture/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a syllabus for Cyberculture (STSC/SOCI 260), a course on histories and cultures of the internet offered in summer 2013 at the University of Pennsylvania. The course might also be called “Several Ways of Looking at the Internet,” “Histories and Cultures of the Internet,” or “Introduction to Internet Studies.” In this course, we will explore how people use the internet to develop new conceptions of identity, build virtual communities, and affect political change. Each class we’ll study an aspect of the history and culture of the internet, covering topics such as hackers, virtuality, sovereignty, and algorithms. We’ll read books, articles, and blogs about historical and contemporary cultures of computing, from Spacewar players and phone phreaks in the 1970s to Google, Facebook, World of Warcraft, WikiLeaks, and Anonymous today. In addition, we’ll explore some of these online communities and projects ourselves, and develop our own analyses of them.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The course will meet on Tuesdays and Thursdays, 1:00 to 4:10, from May 21 to June 27 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 392. It will be a discussion-based seminar, though I will punctuate it with occasional presentations. I will be available for office hours before class on Thursdays from 12:00 to 1:00 in Claudia Cohen Hall room 332, and encourage you to come by and talk.</p>

<h3>Assignments</h3>
<p>As a seminar, this course is primarily based on learning by discussing the required readings (listed below), so it’s essential that you read and think about them before each class meeting.</p>

<p>The main component of this course other than discussions is a final project, which will involve developing your own analysis of an online community or phenomenon incorporating some ways of looking at the internet from the course. Such a project could take the form of a traditional research paper of 10–15 pages or an online presentation involving a similar amount of research and analysis; possibilities range from videos and webcomics to Twitter or Tumblr experiments and beyond. Although you are not required to make your project publicly available online, I can suggest from my own experience that it can be more exciting to produce for an audience beyond your instructor and would be happy to talk with you about appropriate online venues for sharing your project.</p>

<p>In order to help you progress toward completing your project over the course of the semester, I will ask that you meet with me to discuss your ideas for your project on May 28 or 30, submit a short (one to three page) proposal by June 6, present a progress report to the class June 11 or 13, submit a draft to me by June 20, and submit the final project on June 27, the last day of class. I will provide feedback at each of these stages. Your grade for the course will be based 20% on your proposal, 20% on your presentation, 30% on your final project, and 30% on your engaged and insightful participation in discussions.</p>

<h3>News</h3>
<p>One of the things we’ll do in this course is use recent history to find ways to think about current events. Accordingly, you may find it interesting or useful for your project to follow some news. <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/"><cite>The Atlantic</cite>’s technology channel</a> is among the best sources. <a href="http://www.wired.com/"><cite>Wired</cite></a> has many sections and blogs of varying quality, and their security blog <a href="http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/">Threat Level</a> is particularly good.</p>

	<p>The best source for cyberculture news might be Twitter, though, provided you follow the right people. My account is <a href="http://twitter.com/collopy">@collopy</a>, and I’ve made a list of <a href="http://twitter.com/collopy/cyberculture/">some Twitter users relevant to this course</a> that you can subscribe to, including the authors of texts on this syllabus. If you find anything online you’d like to share with the class, please tweet it using the (admittedly silly) hashtag <a href="http://twitter.com/search/realtime?q=%23cyberpenn">#cyberpenn</a>.</p>

<h3>Reading</h3>
<p>Please find a list of required readings below. Many readings are freely available online (and linked here), and I will make most of the others available to students. The exception is <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture</cite> by Fred Turner, the one book we’ll be reading in its entirety, which is available for sale at the Penn Book Center and for borrowing at Van Pelt Library’s Rosengarten Reserve Room. Other books are also available at the Penn Book Center for those who would like to own them.</p>

<h3 style="page-break-before: always">Foundations</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>May 21: Introduction</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Mitchell Kapor and John Perry Barlow, “<a href="http://w2.eff.org/Misc/Publications/John_Perry_Barlow/HTML/eff.html">Across the Electronic Frontier</a>” (1990).</li>
			<li>John Perry Barlow, “<a href="http://w2.eff.org/Censorship/Internet_censorship_bills/barlow_0296.declaration">A Declaration of the Independence of Cyberspace</a>” (1996).</li>
			<li>Bruce Schneier, “<a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2013/01/power_and_the_i.html">Power and the Internet</a>” (2013).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>May 23: Hackers</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Steven Levy, <cite>Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution</cite> (1984), <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/729/pg729.html">chapters 1 and 2</a>.</li>
			<li>Adrian Johns, <cite>Piracy: The Intellectual Property Wars from Gutenberg to Gates</cite> (2009), chapter 16.</li>
			<li>Stewart Brand, “<a href="http://wheels.org/spacewar/stone/rolling_stone.html">Spacewar: Fanatic Life and Symbolic Death Among the Computer Bums</a>” (originally in <cite>Rolling Stone</cite>, 1972).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>May 28: Cybernetics</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Fred Turner, <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</cite> (2006), introduction and chapters 1–4.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
			<h4>May 30: Networks (“The New Economy”)</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Turner, <cite>From Counterculture to Cyberculture</cite>, chapters 5–8.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h3>Virtual Community</h3>
<ul>
	<li>
		<h4>June 4: Virtuality</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Julian Dibbell, “<a href="http://juliandibbell.com/texts/bungle_vv.html">A Rape in Cyberspace: How an Evil Clown, a Haitian Trickster Spirit, Two Wizards, and a Cast of Dozens Turned a Database Into a Society</a>” (originally in <cite>The Village Voice</cite>, 1993).</li>
		    <li>Sherry Turkle, <cite>Life on the Screen: Identity in the Age of the Internet</cite> (1995), chapters 7–9.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 6: Identity</h4>
		<ul>
			<li>Lisa Nakamura, <cite>Cybertypes: Race, Ethnicity, and Identity on the Internet</cite> (2002), introduction and chapters 1, 2, and 5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 11: Play</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Bonnie Nardi, <cite><a href="http://doi.org/10.3998/toi.8008655.0001.001">My Life as a Night Elf Priest: An Anthropological Account of World of Warcraft</a></cite> (2010), prologue, chapters 1, 2, and 6–9, and coda.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 13: Networks (Social Network Sites)</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>danah boyd, “<a href="http://www.danah.org/papers/WhyYouthHeart.pdf">Why Youth (Heart) Social Network Sites: The Role of Networked Publics in Teenage Social Life</a>” (2007).</li>
		    <li>danah boyd, “<a href="http://www.danah.org/papers/2011/WhiteFlight.pdf">White Flight in Networked Publics? How Race and Class Shaped American Teen Engagement with MySpace and Facebook</a>” (2011).</li>
		    <li>Nathan Jurgenson, “<a href="http://mdpi.com/1999-5903/4/1/83/pdf">When Atoms Meet Bits: Social Media, the Mobile Web and Augmented Revolution</a>” (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>

<h3>Politics</h3>
<ul>
		<li>
			<h4>June 18: Sovereignty</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Lawrence Lessig, <cite><a href="http://codev2.cc/download+remix/Lessig-Codev2.pdf">Code and Other Laws of Cyberspace, Version 2.0</a></cite> (2006, revised from 1999), prefaces and chapters 1–5.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 20: Resistance</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Andy Greenberg, <cite>This Machine Kills Secrets: How WikiLeakers, Cypherpunks, and Hacktivists Aim to Free the World’s Information</cite> (2012), prologue and chapters 1, 3, and 4.</li>
		    <li>Gabriella Coleman, “<a href="http://canopycanopycanopy.com/15/our_weirdness_is_free">Our Weirdness Is Free</a>” (2012).</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
		<h4>June 25: Algorithms</h4>
		<ul>
		    <li>Tarleton Gillespie, “<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Gillespie_2014_The-Relevance-of-Algorithms.pdf">The Relevance of Algorithms</a>” (2012).</li>
		    <li>Eli Pariser, <cite>The Filter Bubble: How the New Personalized Web Is Changing What We Read and How We Think</cite> (2011), introduction and chapters 1, 4, and 6.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>
			<h4>June 27: Networks (Infrastructure)</h4>
	    <ul>
	        <li>Andrew Blum, <cite>Tubes: A Journey to the Center of the Internet</cite> (2012), prologue and chapters 1, 2, and 7.</li>
	    </ul>
	</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a syllabus for Cyberculture (STSC/SOCI 260), a course on histories and cultures of the internet offered in summer 2013 at the University of Pennsylvania. The course might also be called “Several Ways of Looking at the Internet,” “Histories and Cultures of the Internet,” or “Introduction to Internet Studies.” In this course, we will explore how people use the internet to develop new conceptions of identity, build virtual communities, and affect political change. Each class we’ll study an aspect of the history and culture of the internet, covering topics such as hackers, virtuality, sovereignty, and algorithms. We’ll read books, articles, and blogs about historical and contemporary cultures of computing, from Spacewar players and phone phreaks in the 1970s to Google, Facebook, World of Warcraft, WikiLeaks, and Anonymous today. In addition, we’ll explore some of these online communities and projects ourselves, and develop our own analyses of them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taking Over the NRA</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/taking-over-nra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking Over the NRA" /><published>2013-02-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2013-02-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2013/taking-over-nra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2013/taking-over-nra/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s an episode of <cite>The West Wing</cite>—“<a href="http://westwing.wikia.com/wiki/The_Portland_Trip">The Portland Trip</a>”—in which Republican congressman Matt Skinner quips to presidential aide Josh Lyman, “I never understood why you gun control people don’t all join the NRA. They’ve got two million members, you bring three million to the next meeting, call a vote. ‘All those in favor of tossing guns?’ Bam. Move on.”</p>
<!--more-->

<p>Skinner isn’t exactly proposing direct action, but the president’s staff on <cite>The West Wing</cite> clearly consider this sort of activist politics beneath them. Josh is dismissive not, it seems to me, because it’s a bad idea, but simply because it’s not the way establishment liberals do things. “It’s a heck of a strategy, Matt,” he says. “I’ll bring that up at a meeting.”</p>

<p>As American started talking seriously about gun control in the weeks after December’s shooting at Sandy Hook Elementary School, this scene played over and over in my head. What if a lobbying organization like the National Rifle Association could be made responsive to the public—or at least to those who care enough about its issue to join whether they agree with its current political stances or not? At the very least, this fictional congressman had a more creative approach to gun control activism than the ineffective assault weapons bans championed by many Democratic legislators.</p>

<p>If the NRA is any kind of democracy, it’s representative rather than direct, so I started looking into how the NRA’s Board of Directors is elected. While the Association’s policies regarding elections aren’t available online, you can find blogs where members gripe about the system’s shortcomings and occasionally describe it in some detail. I was intrigued enough to write to the NRA and ask for a copy of their bylaws, which they were kind enough to mail me.</p>

<img style="display: block; margin: auto;" title="Envelope from the NRA" src="/images/envelope.gif" width="357" height="243">

<p>My conclusion is that Skinner’s idea wouldn’t work. Even if you could persuade three million—or five million, or ten million—progressives to join the NRA, the organization’s bylaws ensure they couldn’t take it over. Aaron Sorkin frequently says <a href="http://www.vulture.com/2012/06/aaron-sorkin-newsroom-interview.html">in interviews</a> he can “write about people who are smarter than I am and know more than I do, and I am able to do that simply by being tutored almost phonetically, sometimes.” Much of what passes for intelligence among his characters is merely cleverness. It would not be difficult for an actual Republican congressman to understand that the NRA can resist conquest by “gun control people.” For the rest of us, however, here’s how it works:</p>

<img title="The National Rifle Association of America Bylaws" src="/images/bylaws.gif" style="display: block; float: right; margin: 10px;" width="175" height="375">

<p>In addition to a fairly typical clause offering membership only to those “who subscribe… to the objectives and purposes of the Association,” the bylaws bar new members from voting unless they purchase a “Life Membership,” <a href="https://membership.nrahq.org/forms/signup.asp">currently available for $1000</a>. Article III, section 6, item e, part 1 states that only “lifetime members and annual members with five or more consecutive years of membership… who have attained the age of 18 years and who are citizens of the United States of American shall be entitled to a vote” when electing Directors.</p>

<p>The bylaws also prescribe the process by which aspiring Directors of the NRA get their names on the ballot. Most are nominated by a Nominating Committee (on which <cite>Mother Jones</cite> journalist Frank Smyth has <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2013/01/nra-board-newtown-bushmaster">some interesting reporting</a>) appointed by the Board of Directors and thus unlikely to rock the boat. Alternately, a candidate may be placed on the ballot by a petition of a mere 250 signatures of members eligible to vote.</p>

<p><a href="http://firearmscoalition.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;id=599">According to NRA member Jeff Knox</a>, this petition process was instituted in 1977 as part of “a major member revolt at the annual meeting in Cincinnati [in which] a more politically aggressive faction grabbed the reigns of the organization.” <a href="http://www.thenation.com/blog/172125/how-nra-became-organization-aspiring-vigilantes-part-2">As Rick Perlstein writes</a>, it was in this coup that the NRA became more concerned with opposing gun control than with outdoor sports. Making the NRA more democratic by introducing petitions was a way to keep it accountable to a politically involved membership.</p>

<p>Now, though, the NRA’s membership is in favor of substantially more gun control than their leadership, even if it isn’t flooded with three million “gun control people”; <a href="http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp1300512">74% of NRA members support background checks for all gun purchases</a>. There are a number of reasons why the NRA’s leadership doesn’t reflect membership opinion, but among them is surely that, according to Knox and other members, only 7% of eligible members vote. (This number is probably low, since <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/mojo/2013/01/nra-membership-numbers">it’s likely that many of the NRA’s Life Members are dead</a>, but it’s still probable that only a minority of eligible members vote.) The shortest path to the NRA becoming a more moderate organization might be simply for moderates to run for the Board of Directors—by petition if necessary—and for other moderates to vote for them. The “hardliners” who made the NRA what it is today may have also left a way out.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="conservatism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s an episode of The West Wing—“The Portland Trip”—in which Republican congressman Matt Skinner quips to presidential aide Josh Lyman, “I never understood why you gun control people don’t all join the NRA. They’ve got two million members, you bring three million to the next meeting, call a vote. ‘All those in favor of tossing guns?’ Bam. Move on.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cyber-Utopianism Before the Internet</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cyber-utopianism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cyber-Utopianism Before the Internet" /><published>2012-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-08-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cyber-utopianism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cyber-utopianism/"><![CDATA[<p>In his 2011 book <cite><a href="http://netdelusion.com/">The Net Delusion: The Dark Side of Internet Freedom</a></cite>, <a href="http://evgenymorozov.com/">Evgeny Morozov</a> defines <em>cyber-utopianism</em> as “a naîve belief in the emancipatory nature of online communication that rests on a stubborn refusal to acknowledge its downside.” This belief, he writes, has entered U.S. foreign policy through the State Department’s internet freedom agenda. Its effects can also be seen in the media, as in misplaced enthusiasm about the role of Twitter in the Iranian uprising of 2009. Foundational to Morozov’s portrayal is Andrew Sullivan’s <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/daily-dish/archive/2009/06/the-revolution-will-be-twittered/200478/">announcement on his blog</a> that Iranians began communicating using Twitter after the government shut down the cell phone network. “That a new information technology could be improvised for this purpose so swiftly is a sign of the times,” wrote Sullivan. “You cannot stop people any longer. You cannot control them any longer. They can bypass your established media; they can broadcast to one another; they can organize as never before.”</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Intriguingly, Morozov traces cyber-utopianism to “former hippies’” attempts “to prove that the Internet could deliver what the 1960s couldn’t: boost democratic participation, trigger a renaissance of moribund communities, strengthen associational life, and serve as a bridge from bowling alone to blogging together.” Morozov is right that the counterculture had some influence on the cyber-utopianism of today, but it’s perhaps deeper than he acknowledges. Hippies did not wait for the emergence of the internet to embrace the vision of a networked society; rather, the countercultural politics of the 1960s already incorporated a belief in the democratizing power of decentralized, electronic media. Indeed, despite Sullivan’s suggestion that the people’s power is unprecedented, one can find rhetoric virtually identical to his decades earlier.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" title="Portapak" src="/images/portapak.jpg" alt="" width="370" height="250"/></p>
<p>The focus of this earlier cyber-utopianism was on breaking the oligopoly of broadcast television with cable television, satellites, and other new electronic technologies. Central to this vision was a portable device designed, like the cell phone, for an individual user: Sony’s VideoRover II, released in 1968. This portapak, as users called it, was much lighter and less imposing than traditional television cameras. From the beginning, users interpreted it as a new medium for artistic and political expression. In his 1972 memoir <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL4116949W/The_Stoned_Apocalypse">The Stoned Apocalypse</a></cite>, spiritual seeker and prolific erotica writer Marco Vassi anticipated Sullivan by 37 years: “The enthusiasm for videotape,” he wrote, “came from the evenings we spent using the equipment with each other, to create portraits, and modes of psychological insight, and sheer technological art. I suppose we all had our first flashes of power through those sessions, the realization that if one had access to the technology, he had as strong a voice in shaping the destiny of the world as the politicians and generals.” Many also saw video as an inherently democratic technology that would distribute this power to be heard more equitably.</p>
<p>This ideology was most fully elaborated by the video collective <a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/e/history.html">Raindance</a>, particularly in Michael Shamberg’s 1971 book <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL7098564W/Guerrilla_television">Guerrilla Television</a></cite>. Shamberg, who went on to become a Hollywood producer, presented television itself as a revolutionary technology which had already created a new “electronic environment,” “Media-America.” He was a technological determinist who believed that society was structured by its media; politics was mere superstructure which would follow automatically. “It’s nostalgia,” he wrote, “to think that… balance can be restored politically when politics are a function of Media-America, not vice-versa. Only through a radical re-design of its information structures to incorporate two-way, decentralized inputs can Media-America optimize the feedback it needs to come back to its senses.”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" title="Media-America" src="/images/media-america.jpg" alt="" width="386" height="250"/></p>
<p>Shamberg’s influences are evident even in this short quotation. Foremost among them was media theorist <a href="http://marshallmcluhan.com/biography/">Marshall McLuhan</a>, who proposed that electronic media were creating a new social environment for humanity, a highly participatory “global village.” McLuhan&#8217;s research assistant <a href="http://earthscore.org/about.html">Paul Ryan</a> (no relation to the politician) was an experimental videographer who associated with Raindance; it was Ryan who developed the metaphor Shamberg employed of videography as guerrilla warfare in <a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/volume1nr3/pdf/VOLUME1NR3_art01.pdf">an article</a> in Raindance’s magazine <cite><a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/e/">Radical Software</a></cite>. Both McLuhan and Ryan were in turn deeply influenced by the Jesuit paleontologist and mystic <a href="http://teilharddechardin.org/biography.html">Pierre Teilhard de Chardin</a>, particularly his interpretation of human communication as constituting a global mind or “noosphere.” A more effective noosphere—a “videophere,” in art critic <a href="http://geneyoungblood.com/">Gene Youngblood</a>’s terminology—became the political ideal of experimental videography.</p>
<p>More concretely, Shamberg believed that video would revolutionize particular social relations. “Going out to the suburbs with video cameras and taping commuters,” for example, could show them “how wasted they look from buying the suburban myth.” Being videotaped could sensitize police and prevent brutality. Shamberg’s technological optimism focused specifically on communication technology, as he saw new forms of television and other media as both the sources of social change and the proper replacements for an obsolete political sphere.</p>
<p>There were also those who warned against seeing video as a source of social change, though. Among them was Vassi, himself a founding member of Raindance. “There is some talk, and there will be more, in so-called underground tape circles about the revolutionary impact of tape,” <a href="http://radicalsoftware.org/volume1nr1/pdf/VOLUME1NR1_0020.pdf">wrote Vassi</a> in <cite>Radical Software</cite>. “I think it’s too late for all that. Every innovation in technology brought about by heads will be used by the power-trip neanderthals to furnish a more sophisticated 1984.… I think the thing to watch out for is this: That there be as little talking about all this as possible, not to keep the enemy from overhearing or any of that nonsense, but to guard against coming to believe one’s own rhetoric.”</p>
<p>All of which brings us back to the recent past. In January 2010, a few months after the Iranian uprising, Secretary of State Hillary Clinton delivered a speech, “<a href="http://www.state.gov/secretary/rm/2010/01/135519.htm">Remarks on Internet Freedom</a>,” at the Newseum in Washington. “The spread of information networks is forming a new nervous system for our planet,” she told her audience. “When something happens in Haiti or Hunan, the rest of us learn about it in real time—from real people.” Clinton invoked the same emphasis on direct communication—media without mediation—which Shamberg celebrated in video and Sullivan in Twitter, and the same notion of a global mind which McLuhan and Ryan found in Teilhard. ”Now, in many respects, information has never been so free,” Clinton continued, agreeing with countercultural entrepreneur <a href="http://sb.longnow.org/SB_homepage/">Stewart Brand</a>, who declared in 1984 that “information wants to be free.”</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter" title="Hillary Clinson" src="/images/clinton.jpg" alt="" width="355" height="200"/></p>
<p>Clinton’s optimism was tempered, though. “We must also recognize that these technologies are not an unmitigated blessing,” she continued. “These tools are also being exploited to undermine human progress and political rights.” Beyond that, we should heed Vassi’s warning and recognize the threat that we will be seduced by our tools and their false but persistent promise of revolutionary change without our active political effort. These information technologies can contribute to the success of political movements, but not if their users see them as replacements for political life.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="computing" /><category term="internet" /><category term="video" /><category term="technology" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="liberalism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In his 2011 book The Net Delusion: The Dark Side of Internet Freedom, Evgeny Morozov defines cyber-utopianism as “a naîve belief in the emancipatory nature of online communication that rests on a stubborn refusal to acknowledge its downside.” This belief, he writes, has entered U.S. foreign policy through the State Department’s internet freedom agenda. Its effects can also be seen in the media, as in misplaced enthusiasm about the role of Twitter in the Iranian uprising of 2009. Foundational to Morozov’s portrayal is Andrew Sullivan’s announcement on his blog that Iranians began communicating using Twitter after the government shut down the cell phone network. “That a new information technology could be improvised for this purpose so swiftly is a sign of the times,” wrote Sullivan. “You cannot stop people any longer. You cannot control them any longer. They can bypass your established media; they can broadcast to one another; they can organize as never before.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybernetics of the LRAD</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybernetics of the LRAD" /><published>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-of-lrad/"><![CDATA[<p>
	The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/">marketed</a> to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was <a href="http://gizmodo.com/5369190/lrad-sound-cannon-used-on-pittsburgh-g20-protesters">first deployed in the United States</a> at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/05/14/chicago_cops_new_weapon/singleton/">will likely again</a> project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.
</p>
<!--more-->
<iframe class="video" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TInNg6QbHXc" title="Video player" frameborder="0" allow="picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen;"></iframe>
<p>
	As Aaron Bady <a href="http://thenewinquiry.com/blogs/hearing-like-an-lrad/">points out</a>, the LRAD brings together violence and speech. “To ask the question of whether an LRAD is designed to hurt people or designed to communicate across long distances with people,” writes Bady, “is to mystify its central design function: It is a technology whose purpose is to FORCE you to listen and obey, and one which is less interested in the difference than you’d think.” The LRAD makes it impossible to think of policing—particularly the iconic “order to disperse” delivered to political demonstrators from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haymarket_affair#Bombing_and_gunfire">Chicago in 1886</a> to Pittsburgh in 2009 (shown above)—as a process in which orders come first and force follows only in the case of disobedience. The medium through which orders are communicated is itself forceful; the LRAD is a <em>weapon</em>, which is why the LRAD Corporation sells it, according to their <a href="http://www.lradx.com/site/content/view/323">fact sheet</a>, “only to qualified government agencies and commercial entities that are fully trained in the device’s operation.” Bady concludes, then, that the LRAD demonstrates policing is “simply about power. Communication is a means of making you obey,” and, from the perspective of the LRAD, nothing more.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD conflates communication and force not only conceptually but materially: The same sound serves both purposes. It thus taps into a deep seam in twentieth century science and philosophy that is concerned precisely with the relationship between communication and action. It could be interpreted, for instance, in terms of <a href="http://online.sfsu.edu/~kbach/spchacts.html">speech act theory</a>: A loud LRAD order to disperse is both a threatening speech act and itself an act of force.
</p>
<p>
	Since the use of violence to establish control is intrinsic to the LRAD, though, its collapsing of communication and force resonates less with speech acts than the mid-century science of cybernetics. As MIT mathematician Norbert Wiener subtitled <a href="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL14113345M/Cybernetics_or_Control_and_communication_in_the_animal_and_the_machine.">his 1948 book</a> in which he named the discipline, cybernetics involved the study of “control and communication in the animal and machine.” The field developed in the late 1940s through collaborations between scientists interested in understanding minds, societies, and machines in the same terms—collaborations such as the <a href="http://asc-cybernetics.org/foundations/history/MacySummary.htm">Macy Conferences</a>—and cyberneticians conflated control and communication in part to establish parallels between these different entities. This collapsing of categories also owed something, though, to the origins of cybernetics in military research.
</p>
<p>
	Wiener did much of his thinking about analogies between humans and mechanical control systems during World War II while designing an “antiaircraft predictor,” designed to aim a gun in order to shoot down a maneuvering plane. Such a predictor was necessary because during the twenty seconds a shell took to reach its target, the pilot would maneuver, apparently unpredictably. In his article “<a href="http://jerome-segal.de/Galison94.pdf">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” and a <a href="http://cabinetmagazine.org/issues/12/najafi2.php">followup interview</a> in <cite>Cabinet</cite>, historian of science <a href="https://galison.scholar.harvard.edu">Peter Galison</a> argues that Wiener conceived of the enemy pilot as essentially mechanical, and his predictor as a machine that mirrored its behavior. “With no access to anything in the enemy plane,” he says, “Wiener simply treated the pilot-plane assembly as a complex machine—a servomechanism—that once characterized could be simulated in order to predict what it would do. And then it could be blown out of the sky.”
</p>
<p>
	Although Wiener’s work stood in a long tradition of <a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL8396574W/Between_Human_and_Machine">control engineering</a>—since his goal was simply to control a gun—his system also relied on interpreting the plane’s motions as communication to the predictor, which then “learned” its patterns by observing with radar. Even though, “because of the antagonistic relationship between attacker and defender, the anti-aircraft operator was obviously in no position to talk to or even see the pilot,” the latter’s movements still revealed—communicated—his intentions. From Wiener’s perspective as an engineer, though, there was no distinction between control and communication in this system; both were simply messages. There were messages conveyed by the pilot to the plane (through a joystick, say), from the plane to the predictor (through radar), from the predictor to the gun (through a mechanical connection), and from the gun to the plane (through a shell), but each relationship was one of both control and communication, of both force and speech.
</p>
<p>
	The U.S. military also embraced this conflation. During the decades after World War II “command and control,” previously two competing models of military management, became a single practice. <em>Command</em> traditionally involved an officer giving an order which was then interpreted and implemented by those below him in a hierarchy, often as more specific commands to their subordinates. It involved the ambiguity we expect from human communication, if not the dialogue. <em>Control</em>, on the other hand, was direct and (at least ideally) unambiguous. Nuclear weapons, which had to be deployed rapidly and only upon the decision of senior commanders, were subject to control rather than command. This distinction collapsed, though, as nuclear weapons were integrated into conventional military tactics. “By the early 1960s,” writes historian of technology <a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a> in <cite><a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2937046W/The_Closed_World">The Closed World</a></cite>, “military parlance treated the two as virtually identical. A decade later, ‘command, control, communications, and information’ (C<sup>3</sup>I) had become a single unified process.”
</p>
<p>
	It is from this postwar military ideology that the LRAD and its inventor Elwood Norris emerged. According to <a href="http://keynotespeakers.com/speaker_detail.php?speakerid=4074">his speaking bio</a>, Norris served in the Air Force as a nuclear weapons specialist in the 1950s before becoming an independent inventor. He was <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2009/03/06/smallbusiness/killer_sounds.fsb/">hired by the Navy</a> to design the LRAD in 2000 after the U.S.S. Cole bombing, and the original purpose of the device was to deter guerrillas from U.S. warships. It has since been used to deter Somali pirates from commercial ships and “to blast a series of Arabic phrases, such as ‘Go away or we will kill you,’” in Baghdad and Fallujah.
</p>
<p>
	The LRAD, then, is a military technology that has come home to U.S. soil as a command-and-control system for conveying both orders and force from police to civilians. Its erasure of the distinction between control and communication is not a unique phenomenon that emerges when you build a very loud speaker; rather, its inventor designed a speaker loud enough to “influence behavior and create safety zones” because he and his employers already conflated force and speech.
</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="conservatism" /><category term="war" /><category term="engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The LRAD, or Long Range Acoustic Device, is an extremely loud speaker—loud enough to damage hearing—that is marketed to militaries and police forces for both communication and “escalation of force.” It was first deployed in the United States at the Pittsburgh G20 protests in 2009 and will likely again project orders and siren sounds this weekend in Chicago during demonstrations prompted by NATO’s summit meeting. It also embodies a logic which has pervaded American thought since World War II, a logic which conflates communication and control.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">History of Cybernetics Bibliography</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="History of Cybernetics Bibliography" /><published>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2012-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2012/cybernetics-bibliography/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>If you’ve come here after asking yourself (or Google) what cybernetics is, I recommend starting with Bernard Geoghegan and Benjamin Peters’ entry “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” from the <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite>, and Geoffrey Bowker’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>.” Ronald Kline’s <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment</a></cite> is the synthetic history the field has been waiting for. William Aspray’s “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>” places cybernetics in the context of developments in computing and information theory, while Peter Galison’s “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>” is a classic account of the field’s military origins. The texts listed below survey the many forms cybernetics took in the decades that followed.</p>
	
<p>This bibliography is limited in three ways: It includes only books and articles which focus on cybernetics rather than the related histories of cyborgs and information theory; it includes only texts in English, though there are also substantial French and German literatures on the subject; and it excludes articles and dissertations that have been superseded by books by the same authors. Within these limitations, I welcome references to additional books and articles. I last updated this list on November 26, 2023.</p>

<h3>The Big Picture <small>(but mostly Anglo-American)</small></h3>
<ol class="start">
	<li>A. A. Verveen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0025-5564(71)90004-6">In Search of Processes: The Early History of Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Mathematical Biosciences</cite> 11 (1971).
	<li>Michael Apter, “Cybernetics: A Case Study of a Scientific Subject-Complex,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/sociology-of-science/oclc/591825">The Sociology of Science</a></cite>, edited by Paul Halmos (University of Keele, 1972).</li>
	<li>Robert Lilienfeld, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-systems-theory-an-ideological-analysis/oclc/3275488">The Rise of Systems Theory: An Ideological Analysis</a></cite> (Wiley, 1978).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/285691">How to Be Universal: Some Cybernetic Strategies, 1943–70</a>,” <cite>Social Studies of Science</cite> 23 (1993).</li>
	<li><a href="http://nkhayles.com/">Katherine Hayles</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-we-became-posthuman-virtual-bodies-in-cybernetics-literature-and-informatics/oclc/39539341">How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in Cybernetics, Literature, and Informatics</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 1999).</li>
	<li>Charles Fran&ccedil;ois, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1099-1743(199905%2F06)16%3A3%3C203%3A%3AAID-SRES210%3E3.0.CO%3B2-1">Systemics and Cybernetics in a Historical Perspective</a>,” <cite>Systems Research and Behavioral Science</cite> 16 (1999).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sonoma.edu/hutchins/faculty/debora-hammond.html">Debora Hammond</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-of-synthesis-exploring-the-social-implications-of-general-systems-theory/oclc/939936819">The Science of Synthesis: Exploring the Social Implications of General Systems Theory</a></cite> (University Press of Colorado, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gbowker/">Geoffrey Bowker</a>, “The Empty Archive: Cybernetics and the 1960s,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/memory-practices-in-the-sciences/oclc/60776866">Memory Practices in the Sciences</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2008.9">The Historiographic Conceptualization of Information: A Critical Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 30 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://english.emory.edu/home/people/faculty/faculty_pages/johnston.html">John Johnston</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/allure-of-machinic-life-cybernetics-artificial-life-and-the-new-ai/oclc/255975196">The Allure of Machinic Life: Cybernetics, Artificial Life, and the New AI</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2008).</li>
	<li>Philipp Aumann, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.2011.78">The Distinctiveness of a Unifying Science: Cybernetics’ Way to West Germany</a>” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 33 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000018">Cybernetic Sense</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/beautiful-data-a-history-of-vision-and-reason-since-1945/oclc/875884461">Beautiful Data: A History of Vision and Reason since 1945</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2014).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-moment-or-why-we-call-our-age-the-information-age/oclc/890127838">The Cybernetics Moment; or, Why We Call Our Age the Information Age</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="http://medientheorie.com/">Claus Pias</a>, “The Age of Cybernetics,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-the-macy-conferences-1946-1953-transactions/oclc/945975579">Cybernetics: The Macy Conferences, 1946–1954; The Complete Transactions</a></cite> (diaphanes, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://ridt.co/">Thomas Rid</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/rise-of-the-machines-a-cybernetic-history/oclc/921868924">Rise of the Machines: A Cybernetic History</a></cite> (Norton, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a> and <a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118766804.wbiect041">Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Encyclopedia of Communication Theory and Philosophy</cite> (2016).</li>
	<li><a href="http://elizabethpetrick.com">Elizabeth Petrick</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243919881212">Building the Black Box: Cyberneticians and Complex Systems</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, and Human Values</cite> (2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Origins</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Otto Mayr, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/origins-of-feedback-control/oclc/102836">The Origins of Feedback Control</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1970).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.ischool.utexas.edu/~bill/">William Aspray</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MAHC.1985.10018">The Scientific Conceptualization of Information: A Survey</a>,” <cite>IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</cite> 7 (1985).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/between-human-and-machine-feedback-control-and-computing-before-cybernetics/oclc/51493422">Between Human and Machine: Feedback, Control, and Computing before Cybernetics</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002).</li>
</ol>

<h3>United States</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20027476">The Americanization of Unity</a>,” <cite>Daedalus</cite> 127 (1998).</li>
	<li>Peter Krieg, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920510581729">The Human Face of Cybernetics: Heinz von Foerster and the History of a Movement That Failed</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 34 (2005).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/">Stuart Umpleby</a>, “<a href="http://www.gwu.edu/~umpleby/cybernetics/2005_WAS_History_of_Cybernetics_Movement.doc">A History of the Cybernetics Movement in the United States</a>,” <cite>Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences</cite> 91 (2005).</li>
	<li>Christopher Johnson, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43151893">Analogue Apollo: Cybernetics and the Space Age</a>,” <cite>Paragraph</cite> 31 (2008).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Norbert Wiener</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/john-von-neumann-and-norbert-wiener-from-mathematics-to-the-technologies-of-life-and-death/oclc/6304716">John von Neumann and Norbert Wiener: From Mathematics to the Technologies of Life and Death</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1982).</li>
	<li>Pesi Masani, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/norbert-wiener-1894-1964/oclc/19389460">Norbert Wiener, 1894–1964</a></cite> (Birkhauser, 1990).</li>
	<li><a href="http://galison.scholar.harvard.edu/">Peter Galison</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1343893">The Ontology of the Enemy: Norbert Wiener and the Cybernetic Vision</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 21 (1994).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.unizar.es/sociocybernetics/chen/felix/">Felix Geyer</a> and Johannes van der Zouwen, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684929410068334">Norbert Wiener and the Social Sciences</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 23 (1994).
	<li><a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=112">David Jerison</a> and <a href="http://math.mit.edu/people/profile.php?pid=268">Daniel Stroock</a>, “Norbert Wiener,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://conwayandsiegelman.stillpointpress.net/">Flo Conway and Jim Siegelman</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/dark-hero-of-the-information-age-in-search-of-norbert-wiener-the-father-of-cybernetics/oclc/56656253">Dark Hero of the Information Age: In Search of Norbert Wiener, the Father of Cybernetics</a></cite> (Basic Books, 2004).</li>
	<li><a href="http://maramills.org/">Mara Mills</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/10407391-1428852">On Disability and Cybernetics: Helen Keller, Norbert Wiener, and the Hearing Glove</a>,” <cite>differences</cite> 22 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19409419.2013.775544">Toward a Genealogy of a Cold War Communication Science: The Strange Loops of Leo and Norbert Wiener</a>,” <cite>Russian Journal of Communication</cite> 5 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.uni-weimar.de/de/medien/professuren/medienwissenschaft/theorie-medialer-welten/personen/schmidgen/">Henning Schmidgen</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119880662">Cybernetic Times: Norbert Wiener, John Stroud, and the ‘Brain Clock’ Hypothesis</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Soviet and Comparative Studies</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/david-holloway">David Holloway</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/284545">Innovation in Science—The Case of Cybernetics in the Soviet Union</a>,” <cite>Science Studies</cite> 4 (1974).</li>
	<li>Peter Elias, “The Rise and Fall of Cybernetics in the US and the USSR,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/legacy-of-norbert-wiener-a-centennial-symposium-in-honor-of-the-100th-anniversary-of-norbert-wieners-birth-october-8-14-1994-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-cambridge-massachusetts/oclc/36307811">The Legacy of Norbert Wiener: A Centennial Symposium</a></cite> (1997).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-newspeak-to-cyberspeak-a-history-of-soviet-cybernetics/oclc/48477582">From Newspeak to Cyberspeak: A History of Soviet Cybernetics</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://mindell.scripts.mit.edu/homepage/">David Mindell</a>, <a href="http://jerome-segal.de/">J&eacute;r&ocirc;me Segal</a>, and <a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/homepage/">Slava Gerovitch</a>, “From Communications Engineering to Communications Science: Cybernetics and Information Theory in the United States, France, and the Soviet Union,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/science-and-ideology-a-comparative-history/oclc/49395331">Science and Ideology: A Comparative History</a></cite>, edited by Mark Walker (Routledge, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, “<a href="http://ijoc.org/ojs/index.php/ijoc/article/view/212">Betrothal and Betrayal: The Soviet Translation of Norbert Wiener’s Early Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Communications</cite> 2 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="https://petersbenjamin.wordpress.com/">Benjamin Peters</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/how-not-to-network-a-nation-the-uneasy-history-of-the-soviet-internet/oclc/927438758">How Not to Network a Nation: The Uneasy History of the Soviet Internet</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://cla.auburn.edu/history/people/faculty/instructors/diana-kurkovsky-west/">Diana Kurkovsky West</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886520">Cybernetics for the Command Economy: Foregrounding Entropy in Late Soviet Planning</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.lafayette.edu/sanbornj/">Joshua Sanborn</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/kri.2022.0044">Cybernetics and Surveillance: The Secret Police Enter the Computer Age</a>,” <cite>Kritika</cite> 23 (2022).</li>
</ol>

<h3>France and “French Theory”</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://socio.umontreal.ca/repertoire-departement/vue/lafontaine-celine/">C&eacute;line Lafontaine</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276407084637">The Cybernetic Matrix of ‘French Theory,’</a>” <cite>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</cite> 24 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~ll2410/">Lydia Liu</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/648527">The Cybernetic Unconscious: Rethinking Lacan, Poe, and French Theory</a>,” <cite>Critical Inquiry</cite> 36 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.cornell.edu/jacob-krell">Jacob Krell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119886988">What is the ‘Cybernetic’ in the ‘History of Cybernetics’? A French Case, 1968 to the Present</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.sowi.hu-berlin.de/en/lehrbereiche-en/general-sociology/team/vincent-august/index">Vincent August</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1368431021991046">Network Concepts in Social Theory: Foucault and Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>European Journal of Social Theory</cite> 24 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bernardg.com/">Bernard Geoghegan</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1346150607">Code: From Information Theory to French Theory</a></cite> (Duke University Press, 2023)</li>
</ol>

<h3>Chile</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-revolutionaries-technology-and-politics-in-allendes-chile/oclc/713834502">Cybernetic Revolutionaries: Technology and Politics in Allende’s Chile</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/people/staff/martin-collins">Martin Collins</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2013.776857">introduction to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://usnwc.edu/Faculty-and-Departments/Directory/Michael-Aaron-Dennis">Michael Dennis</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756240">Scientific and Technical Knowledge and the Making of Political Order</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756239">Beyond the Closed World</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://drexel.edu/coas/faculty-research/faculty-directory/TiagoSaraiva/">Tiago Saraiva</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756238">The History of Cybernetics in McOndo</a>,” <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="https://edenmedina.mit.edu/">Eden Medina</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07341512.2012.756237">author response to forum on <cite>Cybernetic Revolutionaries</cite></a>, <cite>History and Technology</cite> 28 (2012).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Biology</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1215/01636545-1979-20-206">The Biological Enterprise: Sex, Mind, and Profit from Human Engineering to Sociobiology</a>,” <cite>Radical History Review</cite> no. 20 (1979).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “The High Cost of Information in Post World War II Evolutionary Biology: Ergonomics, Semiotics, and the Sociobiology of Communications Systems,” <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/philosophical-forum/oclc/1787155">Philosophical Forum</a></cite> 13 (1981–2).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “Signs of Dominance: From a Physiology to a Cybernetics of Primate Society, C.R. Carpenter, 1930–1970,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/studies-in-history-of-biology/oclc/2957828">Studies in History of Biology</a></cite> 6, edited by William Coleman and Camille Limoges (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1983).</li>
	<li><a href="http://people.ucsc.edu/~haraway/">Donna Haraway</a>, “A Semiotics of the Naturalistic Field, from C.R. Carpenter to S.A. Altmann, 1930–55,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/primate-visions-gender-race-and-nature-in-the-world-of-modern-science/oclc/19672184">Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</a></cite> (Routledge, 1989).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “The Body of a New Machine: Situating the Organism between Telegraphs and Computers,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/refiguring-life-metaphors-of-twentieth-century-biology/oclc/31606662">Refiguring Life: Metaphors of Twentieth-Century Biology</a></cite> (Columbia University Press, 1995).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/who-wrote-the-book-of-life-a-history-of-the-genetic-code/oclc/41967065">Who Wrote the Book of Life? A History of the Genetic Code</a></cite> (Stanford University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/keller.html">Evelyn Fox Keller</a>, “Taming the Cybernetic Metaphor” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/making-sense-of-life-explaining-biological-development-with-models-metaphors-and-machines/oclc/48100379">Making Sense of Life: Explaining Biological Development with Models, Metaphors, and Machines</a></cite> (Harvard University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sydney.edu.au/arts/history/staff/profiles/warwick.anderson.php">Warwick Anderson</a> and Ian MacKay, “The Science of Self,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/intolerant-bodies-a-short-history-of-autoimmunity/oclc/894511336">Intolerant Bodies: A Short History of Autoimmunity</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4>Ecology</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://faculty.umb.edu/pjt/">Peter Taylor</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/4331051">Technocratic Optimism, H.T. Odum, and the Partial Transformation of Ecological Metaphor after World War II</a>,” <cite>Journal of the History of Biology</cite> 21 (1988).</li>
	<li><a href="http://host.jhu.edu/directory/sharon-kingsland/">Sharon Kingsland</a>, “Defining the Ecosystem,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/evolution-of-american-ecology-1890-2000/oclc/56982282">The Evolution of American Ecology, 1890–2000</a></cite> (John Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li>William Bryant, “<a href="http://search.proquest.com/docview/305339541/">Whole System, Whole Earth: The Convergence of Technology and Ecology in Twentieth-Century American Culture</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Iowa, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “Neocybernetics of Gaia: The Emergence of Second-Order Gaia Theory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gaia-in-turmoil-climate-change-biodepletion-and-earth-ethics-in-an-age-of-crisis/oclc/313017382">Gaia in Turmoil: Climate Change, Biodepletion, and Earth Ethics in an Age of Crisis</a></cite>, edited by Eileen Crist and H. Bruce Rinker (MIT Press, 2010).</li>
	<li>Nancy Slack, “Good Friends: Margaret Mead and Gregory Bateson” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/g-evelyn-hutchinson-and-the-invention-of-modern-ecology/oclc/758332328">G. Evelyn Hutchinson and the Invention of Modern Ecology</a></cite> (Yale University Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.usf.edu/arts-sciences/departments/humanities-cultural-studies/faculty/daniel-belgrad.aspx">Daniel Belgrad</a>, <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1153210310">The Culture of Feedback: Ecological Thinking in ’70s America</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2019).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Social Sciences</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li>Steve Heims, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetics-group/oclc/23047769">Constructing a Social Science for Postwar America: The Cybernetics Group, 1946–1953</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.albany.edu/~gpr/">George Richardson</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-thought-in-social-science-and-systems-theory/oclc/22731896">Feedback Thought in Social Science and Systems Theory</a></cite> (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1991).</li>
	<li><a href="http://emsent.nl/">Esther-Mirjam Sent</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/perspectives_on_science/v008/8.4sent.html">Herbert A. Simon as a Cyborg Scientist</a>,” <cite>Perspectives on Science</cite> 8 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://reilly.nd.edu/people/reilly-fellows/philip-mirowski/">Philip Mirowski</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/machine-dreams-economics-becomes-a-cyborg-science/oclc/45636899">Machine Dreams: Economics Becomes a Cyborg Science</a></cite> (Cambridge University Press, 2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Crowther-Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/herbert-a-simon-the-bounds-of-reason-in-modern-america/oclc/55511492">Herbert A. Simon: The Bounds of Reason in Modern America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005).</li>
	<li><a href="http://cas.ou.edu/hunter-heyck">Hunter Heyck</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/age-of-system-understanding-the-development-of-modern-social-science/oclc/891185841">Age of System: Understanding the Development of Modern Social Science</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.stefanos-geroulanos.com">Stefanos Geroulanos</a> and <a href="https://leifweatherby.org/">Leif Weatherby</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119887098">“Cybernetics and the Human Sciences” special issue introduction</a>, <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sts.cornell.edu/people/Kline.cfm">Ronald Kline</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119872111">How Disunity Matters to the History of Cybernetics in the Human Sciences in the United States, 1940–80</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li>Poornima Paidipaty, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1463499619899747">‘Tortoises All the Way Down’: Geertz, Cybernetics and ‘Culture’ at the End of the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Anthropological Theory</cite> 20 (2020).</li>
</ol>

<h4>Gregory Bateson</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://cla.umn.edu/about/directory/profile/lipse001">David Lipset</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/gregory-bateson-the-legacy-of-a-scientist/oclc/5894222">Gregory Bateson: The Legacy of a Scientist</a></cite> (Prentice Hall, 1980).</li>
	<li><a href="http://hss.sas.upenn.edu/people/tresch">John Tresch</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2783231">Heredity is an Open System: Gregory Bateson as Descendant and Ancestor</a>,” <cite>Anthropology Today</cite> 14 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.armoniedeldisordine.it/">Leone Montagnini</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777522">Looking for ‘Scientific’ Social Science: The Macy Conferences on Cybernetics in Bateson’s Itinerary</a>,” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li>Frank Thomas, Rebekah Waits, and Gail Hartsfield, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/03684920710777397">The Influence of Gregory Bateson: Legacy or Vestige?</a>” <cite>Kybernetes</cite> 36 (2007).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.northeastern.edu/camd/artdesign/people/william-kaizen/">William Kaizen</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598913">Steps to an Ecology of Communication: <cite>Radical Software</cite>, Dan Graham, and the Legacy of Gregory Bateson</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://history.ua.edu/faculty/erik-peterson/">Erik Peterson</a>, “<a href="http://etd.nd.edu/ETD-db/theses/available/etd-04132010-142514/">Finding Mind, Form, Organism, and Person in a Reductionist Age: The Challenge of Gregory Bateson and C. H. Waddington to Biological and Anthropological Orthodoxy, 1924–1980</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Notre Dame, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://orithalpern.net/">Orit Halpern</a>, “<a href="http://sfonline.barnard.edu/feminist-media-theory/schizophrenic-techniques-cybernetics-the-human-sciences-and-the-double-bind/">Schizophrenic Techniques: Cybernetics, the Human Sciences, and the Double Bind</a>,” <cite>S&amp;F Online</cite> 10 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://laps-dept.apps01.yorku.ca/anth/faculty/emeriti/harries.html">Peter Harries-Jones</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/upside-down-gods-gregory-batesons-world-of-difference/oclc/952953457">Upside-Down Gods: Gregory Bateson’s World of Difference</a></cite> (Fordham University Press, 2016).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthonychaney.com/">Anthony Chaney</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/runaway-gregory-bateson-the-double-bind-and-the-rise-of-ecological-consciousness/oclc/1032366653">Runaway: Gregory Bateson, the Double Bind, and the Rise of Ecological Consciousness</a></cite> (University of North Carolina Press, 2017).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Sciences of Mind</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.sv.uio.no/psi/personer/vit/geirki/">Geir Kirkeb&oslash;en</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/053901895034001002">From a Naked Emperor to Just Clothes: The Rise and Fall of Cybernetic Family Therapy</a>,” <cite>Social Science Information</cite> 34 (1995).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.brown.edu/Departments/CLPS/people/james-anderson">James Anderson</a> and Edward Rosenfeld, <cite><a href="https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/6626.001.0001">Talking Nets: An Oral History of Neural Networks</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1998).</li>
	<li><a href="https://dlcl.stanford.edu/people/jean-pierre-dupuy">Jean-Pierre Dupuy</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mechanization-of-the-mind-on-the-origins-of-cognitive-science/oclc/44026149">The Mechanization of the Mind: The Origins of Cognitive Science</a></cite>, translated by M. B. DeBevoise (Princeton University Press, 2000).</li>
	<li>Roberto Cordeschi, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/discovery-of-the-artificial-behavior-mind-and-machines-before-and-beyond-cybernetics/oclc/49860160">The Discovery of the Artificial: Behavior, Mind and Machines Before and Beyond Cybernetics</a></cite> (Kluwer Academic Publishers, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1024147708370">From Theory to Data: Representing Neurons in the 1940s</a>,” <cite>Biology and Philosophy</cite> 18 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1162/biot.2006.1.4.418">Cybernetics and Theoretical Approaches in 20th-Century Brain and Behavior Sciences</a>,” <cite>Biological Theory</cite> 1 (2006).</li>
	<li><a href="http://socialsciences.exeter.ac.uk/sociology/staff/pickering/">Andrew Pickering</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/cybernetic-brain-sketches-of-another-future/oclc/615626770">The Cybernetic Brain: Sketches of Another Future</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://histsci.fas.harvard.edu/people/rebecca-lemov">Rebecca Lemov</a>, “<a href="http://limn.it/running-amok-in-labyrinthine-systems-the-cyber-behaviorist-origins-of-soft-torture/">Running Amok in Labyrinthine Systems: The Cyber-Behaviorist Origins of Soft Torture</a>,” <cite>Limn</cite> 1 (2011).</li>
	<li><a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/dweinste">Deborah Weinstein</a>, “‘Systems Everywhere’: Schizophrenia, Cybernetics, and the Double Bind,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/pathological-family-postwar-america-and-the-rise-of-family-therapy/oclc/800721205">The Pathological Family: Postwar America and the Rise of Family Therapy</a></cite> (Cornell University Press, 2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://mediashiga.net/">John Shiga</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/of-other-networks/">Of Other Networks: Closed-World and Green-World Networks in the Work of John C. Lilly</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://hps.utoronto.ca/staff/chen-pang-yeang/">Chen-Pang Yeang</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/694184">From Modernizing the Chinese Language to Information Science: Chao Yuen Ren’s Route to Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Isis</cite> 108 (2017).</li>
	<li><a href="https://anthropology.columbia.edu/content/danielle-judith-zola-carr">Danielle Judith Zola Carr</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119874009">‘Ghastly Marionettes’ and the Political Metaphysics of Cognitive Literalism: Anti-Behaviourism, Language, and the Origins of Totalitarianism</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.christinavagt.com">Christina Vagt</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119882883">Design as Aesthetic Education: On the Politics and Aesthetics of Learning Environments</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://history.princeton.edu/people/katja-guenther">Katja Guenther</a>, “The Dancing Robot: Grey Walter’s Cybernetic Mirror,” in <cite><a href="https://search.worldcat.org/title/1345590894">The Mirror and the Mind: A History of Self-Recognition in the Human Sciences</a></cite> (Princeton University Press, 2022).</li>
</ol>

<h4>Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://ngp.usc.edu/faculty/profile/?fid=16">Michael Arbib</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0001">Warren McCulloch’s Search for the Logic of the Nervous System</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.psych.uic.edu/department-of-psychiatry-faculty-list/154-about-us/directory/faculty/234-neil-r-smalheiser-md-phd">Neil Smalheiser</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/pbm.2000.0009">Walter Pitts</a>,” <cite>Perspectives in Biology and Medicine</cite> 43 (2000).</li>
	<li>Lily Kay, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0269889701000266">From Logical Neurons to Poetic Embodiments of Mind: Warren S. McCulloch’s Project in Neuroscience</a>,” <cite>Science in Context</cite> 14 (2001).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0160-9327(03)00017-6">Integrating Mind and Brain: Warren S. McCulloch, Cerebral Localization, and Experimental Epistemology</a>,” <cite>Endeavour</cite> 27 (2003).</li>
	<li><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/kenaizawa/">Kenneth Aizawa</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000017">Warren McCulloch’s Turn to Cybernetics: What Walter Pitts Contributed</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://users.sussex.ac.uk/~philh/">Phil Husbands</a> and <a href="http://cswww.essex.ac.uk/staff/owen/">Owen Holland</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000019">Warren McCulloch and the British Cyberneticians</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/psychology/contact-and-getting-here/people/alan-collins">Alan Collins</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1179/0308018812Z.00000000020">An Asymmetric Relationship: The Spirit of Kenneth Craik and the Work of Warren McCulloch</a>,” <cite>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</cite> 37 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.triuhistory.ca/tara-abraham/">Tara Abraham</a>, <cite><a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/rebel-genius">Rebel Genius: Warren S. McCulloch’s Transdisciplinary Life in Science</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2016).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Politics and Planning</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://pne.people.si.umich.edu/">Paul Edwards</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/closed-world-computers-and-the-politics-of-discourse-in-cold-war-america/oclc/42636403">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse in Cold War America</a></cite> (MIT Press, 1996).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-warfare-to-welfare-defense-intellectuals-and-urban-problems-in-cold-war-america/oclc/51924188">From Warfare to Welfare: Defense Intellectuals and Urban Problems in Cold War America</a></cite> (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2003).</li>
	<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/sts/people/light.html">Jennifer Light</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tech.0.0007">Taking Games Seriously</a>,” <cite>Technology and Culture</cite> 49 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://bbk.ac.uk/politics/our-staff/academic/antoine-bousquet">Antoine Bousquet</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14682740701791359">Cyberneticizing the American War Machine: Science and Computers in the Cold War</a>,” <cite>Cold War History</cite> 8 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.egs.edu/faculty/brian-holmes/">Brian Holmes</a>, <cite><a href="https://brianholmes.wordpress.com/2009/01/19/book-materials/">Escape the Overcode: Activist Art in the Control Society</a></cite> (Van Abbemuseum, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://geography.utoronto.ca/matt-farish-home-page/">Matthew Ferish</a>, “The Cybernetic Continent: North America as Defense Laboratory,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/contours-of-americas-cold-war/oclc/698116870">The Contours of America’s Cold War</a></cite> (University of Minnesota Press, 2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://democracycollaborative.org/content/john-duda">John Duda</a>, “<a href="https://www.lwbooks.co.uk/anarchist-studies/21-1/cybernetics-anarchism-and-self-organisation">Cybernetics, Anarchism and Self-Organisation</a>,” <cite>Anarchist Studies</cite> 21 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://rhetoric.berkeley.edu/people/david-bates/">David Bates</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864237">The Political Theology of Entropy: A Katechon for the Cybernetic Age</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eui.eu/DepartmentsAndCentres/HistoryAndCivilization/People/Professors/Guilhot">Nicolas Guilhot</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0952695119864244">Automatic Leviathan: Cybernetics and Politics in Carl Schmitt’s Postwar Writings</a>,” <cite>History of the Human Sciences</cite> 33 (2020).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.hf.uio.no/ikos/english/people/aca/middle-east-studies/temporary/joakimp/">Joakim Parslow</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0020743821001033">The Mechanical Atatürk: Cybernetics and State Violence in the Second Turkish Republic</a>,” <cite>International Journal of Middle East Studies</cite> 53 (2021).</li>
</ol>

<h3>Popular Culture and Counterculture</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://homepages.rpi.edu/~eglash/eglash.htm">Ron Eglash</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/095023898335474">Cybernetics in American Youth Subculture</a>,” <cite>Cultural Studies</cite> 12 (1998).</li>
	<li><a href="http://fredturner.stanford.edu/">Fred Turner</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-counterculture-to-cyberculture-stewart-brand-the-whole-earth-network-and-the-rise-of-digital-utopianism/oclc/62533774">From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, the Whole Earth Network, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism</a></cite> (University of Chicago Press, 2006).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.depts.ttu.edu/english/general_info/directory/faculty_profile_pages/clarke_detailed.php">Bruce Clarke</a>, “<a href="http://www.univie.ac.at/constructivism/journal/7/3/196.clarke">From Information to Cognition: The Systems Counterculture, Heinz von Foerster’s Pedagogy, and Second-Order Cybernetics</a>,” <cite>Constructivist Foundations</cite> 7 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://www.dubberly.com/about">Hugh Dubberly</a> and <a href="http://pangaro.com">Paul Pangaro</a>, “<a href="http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html">How Cybernetics Connects Computing, Counterculture, and Design</a>,” in <cite>Hippie Modernism: The Struggle for Utopia</cite>, edited by Andrew Blauvelt (2015).</li>
	<!--Felicity Scott?-->
</ol>

<h3>Art</h3>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://daniels.utoronto.ca/people/lobsingerm">Mary Louise Lobsinger</a>, “Cybernetic Theory and the Architecture of Performance: Cedric Price’s Fun Palace,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/anxious-modernisms-experimentation-in-postwar-architectural-culture/oclc/46929153">Anxious Modernisms: Experimentation in Postwar Architectural Culture</a></cite> (Canadian Center for Architecture, 2000).</li>
	<li><a href="http://artexetra.wordpress.com">Edward Shanken</a>, “<a href="http://artexetra.com/CyberneticsArtCultConv.pdf">Cybernetics and Art: Cultural Convergence in the 1960s</a>,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/from-energy-to-information-representation-in-science-and-technology-art-and-literature/oclc/49821329">From Energy to Information</a></cite>, edited by Bruce Clarke and Linda Henderson (Stanford University Press, 2002).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/leonardo/v041/41.2.fernandez.html">Gordon Pask: Cybernetic Polymath</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 41 (2008).</li>
	<li><a href="http://arthistory.cornell.edu/people/fernandez.cfm">Maria Fernandez</a>, “<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/40598908">Detached from HiStory: Jasia Reichardt and Cybernetic Serendipity</a>,” <cite>Art Journal</cite> 67 (2008).</li>
	<li>Etan J. Ilfeld, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00326">Contemporary Art and Cybernetics: Waves of Cybernetic Discourse within Conceptual, Video and New Media Art</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 45 (2012).</li>
	<li><a href="http://etiennebenson.com/">Etienne Benson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.7275/R5HT2M7T">Environment between System and Nature: Alan Sonfist and the Art of the Cybernetic Environment</a>,” <cite>communication +1</cite> 3 (2014).</li>
</ol>

<h4>Film and Video</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://www.gc.cuny.edu/Page-Elements/Academics-Research-Centers-Initiatives/Doctoral-Programs/Art-History/Faculty-Bios/David-Joselit">David Joselit</a>, <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/feedback-television-against-democracy/oclc/71322293">Feedback: Television Against Democracy</a></cite> (MIT Press, 2007).</li>
	<li><a href="http://art.stonybrook.edu/faculty/zabet-patterson/">Zabet Patterson</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/grey.2009.1.36.36">From the Gun Controller to the Mandala: The Cybernetic Cinema of John and James Whitney</a>,” <cite>Grey Room</cite> no. 36 (2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://film.fsu.edu/People/Administration/Dr.-Andrew-Syder">Andrew Syder</a>, “<a href="http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15799coll127/id/220820/">“Shaken Out of the Ruts of Ordinary Perception”: Vision, Culture and Technology in the Psychedelic Sixties</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Southern California, 2009).</li>
	<li><a href="http://kpaulsen.com/">Kris Paulsen</a>, “<a href="http://amodern.net/article/half-inch-revolution/">Half Inch Revolution: The Guerilla Video Tape Network</a>,” <cite>Amodern</cite> 2 (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="http://procom.ryerson.ca/people/carolyn-kane">Carolyn Kane</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/LEON_a_00871">The Tragedy of Radical Subjectivity: From Radical Software to Proprietary Subjects</a>,” <cite>Leonardo</cite> 47, no. 5 (2014).</li>
	<li><a href="https://collopy.net/">Peter Sachs Collopy</a>, “<a href="https://repository.upenn.edu/edissertations/1665/">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</a>” (doctoral dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 2015).</li>
	<li><a href="https://medienwissenschaft.philhist.unibas.ch/de/personen/ute-holl/">Ute Holl</a>, <cite><a href="http://library.oapen.org/handle/20.500.12657/31337">Cinema, Trance and Cybernetics</a></cite> (Amsterdam University Press, 2017).
</ol>

<h4>Sound and Music</h4>
<ol class="continue">
	<li><a href="http://annenberg.usc.edu/faculty/communication/christina-dunbar-hester">Christina Dunbar-Hester</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243909337116">Listening to Cybernetics: Music, Machines, and Nervous Systems, 1950–1980</a>,” <cite>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</cite> 35 (2010).</li>
	<li><a href="http://sterneworks.org/">Jonathan Sterne</a>, “Nature Builds No Telephones” and “Perceptual Coding and the Domestication of Noise,” in <cite><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/mp3-the-meaning-of-a-format/oclc/769429993">MP3: The Meaning of a Format</a></cite> (2013).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/staff/profiles/music/haworth-christopher.aspx">Christopher Haworth</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.461">Music and Cybernetics in Historical Perspective: Introduction to the Special Issue</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://deirdreloughridge.wordpress.com">Deirdre Loughridge</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.503">Daphne Oram: Cyberneticist?</a>” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.eamonnbell.com">Eamonn Bell</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.523">Cybernetics, Listening, and Sound-Studio Phenomenotechnique in Abraham Moles’s <cite>Théorie de l’information et perception esthétique</cite> (1958)</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://www.claralatham.com">Clara Latham</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.559">The Sound Machine in the Body: Cybernetics and the Theremin</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="https://music.utexas.edu/about/people/eric-drott">Eric Drott</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/res.2021.2.4.578">Music and the Cybernetic Mundane</a>,” <cite>Resonance</cite> 2 (2021).</li>
	<li><a href="http://ted-gordon.net">Theodore Gordon</a>, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/07494467.2021.2001939">‘Androgynous Music’: Pauline Oliveros’s Early Cybernetic Improvisation</a>,” <cite>Contemporary Music Review</cite> 40 (2022).</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="politics" /><category term="computing" /><category term="art" /><category term="war" /><category term="biology" /><category term="video" /><category term="media" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="psychiatry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a bibliography of historical and sociological works on cybernetics, a science of “control and communication in the animal and the machine” which flourished from World War II into the 1970s.]]></summary></entry></feed>