<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://collopy.net/feed/research/fascism.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://collopy.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-26T12:33:54-08:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/feed/research/fascism.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Sachs Collopy</title><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><entry><title type="html">Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Thomas J. Watson for Caltech’s Committee on Naming and Recognition" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2020/thomas-j-watson/"><![CDATA[<p>Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed.</p>

<p>Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite>, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, <cite>IBM and the Holocaust</cite> is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="computing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="fascism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thomas J. Watson Sr. was leader of IBM—carrying at various times the titles of general manager, CEO, president, and chairman—from 1914 to 1956. During this period, the company became a major player in the American and international data processing industries, setting the stage for its dominance of computing in the decades that followed. Watson is a controversial figure principally because of IBM’s relationship with the government of Nazi Germany. The history of this relationship, and of Watson’s role in it, is complex. It is the subject of a bestselling 2001 book, IBM and the Holocaust, by journalist Edwin Black. Unfortunately, IBM and the Holocaust is generally regarded as hyperbolic and inaccurate by historians who research related subjects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s</title><link href="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Be Videotaped: Making a Technology of Consciousness in the Long 1960s" /><published>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://collopy.net/writing/2015/revolution-will-be-videotaped/"><![CDATA[<p>In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.</p>]]></content><author><name>Peter Sachs Collopy</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="politics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="media" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="cybernetics" /><category term="video" /><category term="art" /><category term="visual culture" /><category term="analog/digital" /><category term="synthesizers" /><category term="evolution" /><category term="war" /><category term="technopolitics" /><category term="science" /><category term="human sciences" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="anthropology" /><category term="religion" /><category term="Christianity" /><category term="utopianism" /><category term="communism" /><category term="psychiatry" /><category term="fascism" /><category term="New York" /><category term="California" /><category term="biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the late 1960s, video recorders became portable, leaving the television studio for the art gallery, the psychiatric hospital, and the streets. The technology of recording moving images on magnetic tape, previously of use only to broadcasters, became a tool for artistic expression, psychological experimentation, and political revolution. Video became portable not only materially but also culturally; it could be carried by an individual, but it could also be carried into institutions from the RAND Corporation to the Black Panther Party, from psychiatrists’ offices to art galleries, and from prisons to state-funded media access centers. Between 1967 and 1973, American videographers across many of these institutional contexts participated in a common discourse, sharing not only practical knowledge about the uses and maintenance of video equipment, but visions of its social significance, psychological effects, and utopian future. For many, video was a technology which would bring about a new kind of awareness, the communal consciousness that—influenced by the evolutionary philosophy of Henri Bergson—Pierre Teilhard de Chardin referred to as the noosphere and Marshall McLuhan as the global village. Experimental videographers across several fields were also influenced by the psychedelic research of the 1950s and early 1960s, by the development of cybernetics as a science of both social systems and interactions between humans and machines, by anthropology and humanistic psychology, and by revolutionary political movements in the United States and around the world.]]></summary></entry></feed>